<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Christians iewell. Or, The treasure of a good conscience. By William Worship, Doctor of Diuinitie</title>
            <author>Worship, William.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1617</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 202 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 132 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15711</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25985</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114443</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849668</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849668</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14830</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15711)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14830)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1536:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Christians iewell. Or, The treasure of a good conscience. By William Worship, Doctor of Diuinitie</title>
                  <author>Worship, William.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[20], 243, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Stansby, for Iohn Parker,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1617.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>C3 is a cancel.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Conscience --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14830:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14830:1"/>
            <p>THE CHRISTIAN IEWELL. OR, THE TREASVRE OF <hi>a Good Conſcience.</hi> By WILLIAM WORSHIP, Doctor of Diuinitie.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>1. TIM. 1. 20.</bibl> Hauing Faith, and a Good Conſcience.</q>
            <q>Multi quaerunt Scientiam, Pauci Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientiam. <bibl>
                  <hi>Bern.</hi> in For. Hon. vit.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by WILLIAM STANSBY, for <hi>Iohn Parker.</hi> 1617.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:14830:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14830:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, <hi>Sir</hi> FRANCIS BACON, Knight, <hi>Lord Keeper of the Great Seale,</hi> my very ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar good <hi>Lord;</hi> All in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of true Honour, with the glorious comforts of <hi>Grace.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE <hi>Goſpell</hi> (Right <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable</hi>) is like the <hi>Booke</hi> of <hi>Canticles;</hi> which begins with a <hi>Kiſſe,</hi> and ends in <hi>Spices.</hi> The ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſound of it imports <hi>Glad
<pb facs="tcp:14830:3"/> Tidings of</hi> PEACE; without<note place="margin">Rom. 10. 15.</note> which, this Inch of time al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lotted, is but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>a Dead kinde of Life,</hi> as <hi>Plato</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. De Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pub.</note> ſpeaks of a <hi>Guilty Conſcience.</hi> Forwere a man <hi>The Darling of the World,</hi> with <hi>Titus Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſian;</hi> were he ſo repleni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with all earthly good things, as that no mortall creature <hi>durſt</hi> wiſh the like,<note place="margin">De Ciuit. Dei, l. 5. c. 25.</note> as S. <hi>Augustine</hi> ſpeakes of <hi>Constantine the Great:</hi> yet if in this matchleſſe proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, hee want the fauour of GOD, and <hi>Tranquillitie</hi> of minde; he is no better than<note place="margin">AElian. l. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Xerxes Plane-Tree,</hi> which tooke no delight in it ſelfe, though it was richly hung with <hi>Bracelets, Tablets, Span<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gles, Chaines of Gold.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:14830:3"/>
            <p>This <hi>Peace</hi> of GOD, ſo<note place="margin">Phil. 4 7. Gal. 6. 16. Col. 3. 15.</note> much magnified in <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> is better known by <hi>fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> than <hi>Diſcourſe;</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the fayreſt <hi>Iewell</hi> vnder Heauen, is peculiarly giuen to the <hi>Elect,</hi> who cheriſh the ſparke therof, with workes of <hi>Pietie</hi> to GOD, and <hi>Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie</hi> to their Neighbour.</p>
            <p>Thus, in briefe, hath your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> the drift, and ſcope of this preſent <hi>Indeuour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now that I, a <hi>Graſſe-hop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per</hi> (in reſpect of many lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned) dare thus boldly, and hoarcely ſing in the eyes and hearing of <hi>Him,</hi> who is <hi>Magnus</hi> in <hi>Magnis, Primꝰ</hi> in<note place="margin">Hieron. Ad Pammach:</note> 
               <hi>Primis, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Herôum,</hi> is, (I confeſſe) <hi>Piaculum:</hi> whereunto notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:14830:4"/> the <hi>Nobleneſſe</hi> of your <hi>Honours</hi> diſpoſition (which is wont with <hi>Artaxerxes,</hi> to<note place="margin">AElian. l. 1.</note> take in worth <hi>Synaetas</hi> hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of water) the <hi>Correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> of the <hi>Treatiſe</hi> with that High place of <hi>Iuſtice</hi> whereto God hath aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced you; together with the zeale of declaring my thankefulnes, and duty for ſo many <hi>Incouragements</hi> vouchſafed from your <hi>Lordſhip,</hi> haue, in a manner, inſtigated me.</p>
            <p>Goe on (moſt Noble <hi>Lord</hi>) to be a <hi>Sanctuarie</hi> to <hi>Conſcience;</hi> a <hi>Place</hi> of <hi>Refuge</hi> to the <hi>Innocent,</hi> &amp; <hi>Oppreſſed;</hi> and remember to ſerue that GOD with a faithfull heart, who ſo graciouſly hath ſet
<pb facs="tcp:14830:4"/> you in the ſeate of your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned <hi>Father;</hi> and go not onely beyond <hi>Him,</hi> but <hi>Your Selfe</hi> too. And as hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> hath eſteemed of <hi>Siluer,</hi> as of <hi>Tinne;</hi> and contemned the <hi>Wedge</hi> of <hi>Gold,</hi> which ſo many great Idolaters doe crouch to: ſo ſtill, in this <hi>Exuberance</hi> of all things, continue con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tant: <hi>Et nudum Chriſtum, nudus ſequere. Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hieron.</note> 
               <hi>Grande, Difficile; ſed Magna ſunt praemia.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your <hi>Lordſhips</hi> moſt bounden, and duti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>Chaplaine,</hi> William Worſhip.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="author_to_book">
            <pb facs="tcp:14830:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14830:5"/>
            <head>THE AVTHOVR TO HIS BOOKE.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>POore</hi> Booke (for all the <hi>IEWELL</hi> on thy brow)</l>
               <l>Goe, paſſe along; and Bellman-like awake</l>
               <l>The <hi>Sybarite,</hi> that liues he cares not how,</l>
               <l>And will no pleaſure but in Pleaſure take.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Who, while he leanes, hath <hi>PINKES</hi> vpon his eye,</l>
               <l>And <hi>POPPIES</hi> on his boſome as he ſits:</l>
               <l>And ſtreaking out his limmes, delights to lye</l>
               <l>On Roſes faire, and daintie Violits.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Bounce at his doore; and if he aske, <hi>WHO'S THERE?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Tell him, <hi>A MESSENGER</hi> from <hi>CONSCIENCE:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Hee'le ſay, <hi>SHE'S HANG'D:</hi> but then bid thou him feare</l>
               <l>That Death him ſelfe: for if his skill in <hi>Fence</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Shall ward the blow that fatall <hi>Land-trees</hi> lend,</l>
               <l>Rather than fayle, <hi>WAPPING</hi> may be his end.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:14830:6"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14830:6"/>
            <head>The Contents of this Booke.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> WHat Conſcience is not.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> What Conſcience is: from the Notation.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> What Conſcience is: from the Definition.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. IIII.</hi> Of the Offices of Conſcience; and firſt, that it is an Arbitrator.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> That Conſcience is a Conuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> That Conſcience is an Espiall.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> That Conſcience is a Peacher.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> That Conſcience is a Monitor.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:14830:7"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> That Conſcience is a Schoole-Maſter.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> That Conſcience is a Domeſticall Chaplaine.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. XI.</hi> That Conſcience is a Prognoſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cator.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. XII.</hi> That Conſcience is a Regiſter.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIII.</hi> That Conſcience is a Iudge.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIIII.</hi> Of the Properties of Conſcience, and firſt, of Teſtification.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. XV.</hi> Of the ſecond Propertie of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, which is Ligation.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVI.</hi> Of the third and fourth Proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Conſcience, which are, Excuſation, and Accuſation.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVII.</hi> Of the kindes of Conſcience,
<pb facs="tcp:14830:7"/> which are, Good, and Euill: and firſt of the Good one.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVIII.</hi> That the knowledge of Gods Word is neceſſary to the Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Conſcience.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIX.</hi> That Faith is neceſſary to the goodneſſe of Conſcience.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. XX.</hi> That Repentance is neceſſary to the Goodneſſe of Conſcience.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXI.</hi> That Peace is neceſſary to the Goodneſſe of Conſcience.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXII.</hi> Of the Bleſſednes of that Man, whoſe Conſcience is quieted through the Pardon of his ſinnes.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXIII.</hi> Of the vnſpeakeable Comfort of a Good Conſcience.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXIIII.</hi> That the Comfort of Conſcience
<pb facs="tcp:14830:8"/> is Inward, and Independent of the Creatures.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXV,</hi> That the Comfort of Conſcience is Noble, and Sincere.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXVI.</hi> That the Comfort of Conſcience is Immutable and Durable.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXVII.</hi> That Peace of Conſcience is the beſt Muſicke.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXVIII.</hi> That Peace of Conſcience is the beſt Phyſicke.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXIX.</hi> That Peace of Conſcience is an Ineſtimable <hi>IEWEL.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXX.</hi> That a good Conſcience com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forteth in Infamie.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXI.</hi> That a good Conſcience comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in Pouerty.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXII.</hi> That a good Conſcience com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forteth
<pb facs="tcp:14830:8"/> in Impriſonment.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXIII.</hi> That a good Conſcience com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forteth in Sickneſſe.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXIIII.</hi> That a good Conſcience com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forteth at the time of Death.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXV.</hi> That a good Conſcience com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forteth at the Day of Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXVI.</hi> A complaint that good Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is ſo little ſet by.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXVII.</hi> That Gods deareſt Children are often troubled in Conſcience.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXVIII.</hi> Of ſundrie Comforts againſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſiue Sorrow for Sinne: and firſt, Of the conſideration of the Infiniteneſſe of Gods Mercie.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXIX.</hi> Of the ſecond Comfort in trouble
<pb facs="tcp:14830:9"/> of Conſcience, which is, The Meditation of the Bloud of Chriſt.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. XL.</hi> Of the third Comfort in trouble of Conſcience, which is, the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>definitenes of Gods Promiſes.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. XLI.</hi> Of the fourth Comfort in trouble of Conſcience, which is, The Example of Hainous Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, that haue been pardoned vpon their Repentance.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. XLII.</hi> Of the fift Comfort in trouble of Conſcience, which is, The Conſideration of Gods Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly Chastiſements accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panying it.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. XLIII.</hi> Of the Sixth Comfort in Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of Conſcience, which is Mourning for ſinne.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. XLIIII.</hi> Of the Seuenth Comfort in
<pb facs="tcp:14830:9"/> Trouble of Conſcience, which is Prayer.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. XLV.</hi> Of the Eighth Comfort in Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of Conſcience, which is Reading of Scripture.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. XLVI.</hi> Of the Ninth Comfort in Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of Conſcience, which is Singing of Pſalmes.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. XLVII.</hi> Of the Tenth Comfort in Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of Conſcience, which is the Teſtimonie of the Miniſter.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. XLVIII.</hi> Of the Eleuenth Comfort in Trouble of Conſcience, which is Conference with the Godly.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. XLIX.</hi> Of the Twelfth Comfort in Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of Conſcience, which is Painfulneſſe in our Calling.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. L.</hi> Of the Thirteenth Comfort in Trouble of Conſcience, which
<pb facs="tcp:14830:10"/> is the Conſideration of the Truth of Gods Promiſes.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. LI.</hi> Of the Fourteenth Comfort in Trouble of Conſcience, which is the Conſideration of the Iuſtice of God.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. LII.</hi> That all the fore-named Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts are vneffectuall, without the Preſence of the Holy Ghoſt.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. LIII.</hi> An Exhortation to the children of God, that the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſtri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e againſt their Dumpiſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſſe, and that they be cheerefull in the Lord.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. LIIII.</hi> A ſhort Prayer for Comfort in Trouble of Conſcience.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. LV.</hi> Of Euill Conſcience; and firſt, of the Large one.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. LVI.</hi> Of the Second kind of Euill Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,
<pb facs="tcp:14830:10"/> which is Nice, or Spiced.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. LVII.</hi> Of the Third kind of Euill Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, which is the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe one.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. LVIII.</hi> Of the Fourth kind of Euill Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, which is the Cauteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. LIX.</hi> Of the Degrees, and Steps that leade to this Searedneſſe of Conſcience.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. LX.</hi> Of the fearefull eſtate of thoſe that haue Searedneſſe of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. LXI.</hi> Of the Fifth kind of Euill Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, which is the Deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate one.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. LXII.</hi> That it is exceeding dangerous
<pb facs="tcp:14830:11"/> for a Man in horror of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, to kill himſelfe.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. LXIII.</hi> Certaine forcible Reaſons a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Deſpayre.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:14830:11"/>
            <head>THE CHRISTIANS IEWELL.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> What Conſcience is not.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigen,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In Epiſt. ad Rom. cap. 2. 15.</note> that <hi>Conſcience</hi> was a certain <hi>Spirit,</hi> diſtinct in nature from the ſubſtance of the <hi>Soule,</hi> and ioyned to it as an inſeparable Companion.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:14830:12"/> And to fortifie this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, hee vſurped the place of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans; The ſame Spirit wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 16</note> 
                  <hi>with our Spirit, that wee are the Children of God.</hi> But as this aſſertion is ſtrange, and repugnant to reaſon, which abhorres <hi>du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alitie</hi> of <hi>Soules</hi> cohabiting in one body; ſo the <hi>Text</hi> allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, is apparantly wreſted from the natiue ſenſe, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares by Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In Expoſit. quar. Prop. Ex Ep<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ad Rom. In Epiſt. ad Rom.</note> and <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> who fitly expound it of the <hi>Spirit of</hi> GOD, confirming mans heart regenerate by <hi>Grace.</hi> To which Interpretation though ſome other <hi>Expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ors</hi> doe not vnanimouſly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>end their voyces, to make
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:14830:12"/> vp the <hi>Diapaſon;</hi> yet fauor they no whit, the violent, and vngrounded Gloſſe of <hi>Origen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If here we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> deſcend to the <hi>Schoolemen,</hi> they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord<note place="margin">Scotus. Aquinas. Sum. 1. Q. 79. Art. 13.</note> not. Some hold it to be an <hi>Habit,</hi> others an <hi>Act:</hi> but it will be found, after iuſt diſcuſſion, that <hi>Habits,</hi> and <hi>Acts</hi> are tranſient and periſhing, where <hi>Conſcience</hi> cannot be loſt, though the edge of her operation bee ſometimes dulled.</p>
               <p>As for thoſe <hi>Minuti Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophi,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Plutarch. Mor.</note> the <hi>Grylls,</hi> &amp; <hi>Trough-Philoſophers</hi> of the World, who degrading <hi>Conſcience</hi> from her ſeat of <hi>Honour,</hi> haue thruſt her downe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the <hi>Humours,</hi> and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:14830:13"/> there left her in the <hi>Lees,</hi> as if her <hi>affects</hi> were but the <hi>paſsions</hi> of <hi>melancholy;</hi> albe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it the <hi>Paradoxe</hi> bee ſo baſe, and ſenſual, that it deſerues no anſwere; yet for vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of <hi>Truth,</hi> and out of a certaine homage to <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue,</hi> I muſt giue them this counter-checke, that the blacke and ſtubborne <hi>hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of melancholy,</hi> is char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and maſtered by <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke, Dyet, Muſicke, Exerciſe, Societie;</hi> where the gaſh of <hi>Conſcience</hi> can neuer bee healed, but by a ſpirituall and heauenly <hi>Balme.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:14830:13"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> What Conſcience is, from the Notation.</head>
               <p>WHen the <hi>Names</hi> of things are ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant, &amp; expreſſiue, they are pettie <hi>Definitions,</hi> and giue ſome light to the point in hand. <hi>Conſcientia</hi> (ſaith <hi>S.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In Form. Hon. vit.</note> 
                  <hi>Bernard</hi>) ſoundeth as much as <hi>Cordis Scientia,</hi> becauſe it knowes it ſelfe, and many other things. <hi>Conſcientia</hi> (ſayth <hi>Aquinas</hi>) is <hi>Scien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Summa. Q. 79. Szeged.</note> 
                  <hi>cum alio, a knowledge with another:</hi> which <hi>combi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation</hi> hath either reference to the <hi>Soule</hi> reflecting vpon it ſelfe, or elſe to God, who is priuie to her inmoſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents. For though <hi>Angels,</hi>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:14830:14"/> and <hi>Men</hi> doe not know the <hi>Heart,</hi> but by <hi>Reuelation,</hi> or <hi>Ouerture;</hi> yet the moſt wiſe <hi>Creatour,</hi> who ſitteth in the <hi>Centre</hi> thereof, and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually<note place="margin">1. Sa. 16. 7.</note> maketh an vnblou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die <hi>diſſection,</hi> muſt needs bee acquainted with her moſt ſecret deſignes.</p>
               <p>If wee take it in the firſt ſenſe, it euinceth euidently, that in certaine caſes of doubt, the beſt appeale is to a mans owne <hi>Conſcience.</hi> For, <hi>What man knowes the</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 2. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>things of a Man,</hi> (ſayth S. PAVL) <hi>ſaue the Spirit of a Man, which is in him?</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the anſwere of Saint <hi>Auſten</hi> to <hi>Petilian,</hi> is excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent:<note place="margin">Contra lit. Pet. l. 3. c. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>Me Petilianus Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaeum eſſe dicit, loquens de
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:14830:14"/> aliena Conſcientia; hoc ego me non eſſe dico, loquens de mea conſcientia. Eligite cui creda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis. Petilian</hi> giues out that I am a <hi>Manichee,</hi> and this hee ſpeakes of anothers conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; I plainely affirme I am none of that <hi>Sect,</hi> and this I ſpeak from mine own <hi>Conſcience.</hi> Now chooſe ye which of vs <hi>Two</hi> yee will beleeue.</p>
               <p>If we take it in the latter ſenſe, as it hath relation to God, who notes our cloſeſt thoughts, it will teach vs to ſtamp vpon thoſe <hi>Cockatrice</hi> egges of our poyſonous i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maginations, before their hatching. It's an euerlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing reproch to <hi>Abſalon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Sam. 16. 22.</note> that he committed euill in
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:14830:15"/> the <hi>open</hi> ſight of the <hi>Sunne;</hi> and ſhall wee ſteame forth corrupt and noyſome co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitations in the face of that GOD, with whoſe glorious reſplendencie if wee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare the <hi>Sunne,</hi> it wil proue no better then a piece of <hi>Searing-candle?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But let vs paſſe on from the <hi>Name</hi> of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> to the very <hi>Life,</hi> and <hi>Nature</hi> of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> What Conſcience is, from the Definition.</head>
               <p>NOt to bury my ſelfe in the heape of others Definitions, I will ſelect one which ſeemes moſt
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:14830:15"/> kindely to expreſſe the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of <hi>Conſcience.</hi> It is this. <hi>Conſcience is a Part of the Practicall vnderſtanding, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termining of things done, and therevpon excuſing, or accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing.</hi> The ſubſtance of this <hi>Definition</hi> is found in thoſe<note place="margin">Rom. 2. 15.</note> words of the <hi>Apoſtle; Their Conſcience bearing witneſſe, and their thoughts (or Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonings) accuſing one another, or excuſing.</hi> By this <hi>clauſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Melanct. Il<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>yric. Grynaeus. Szeged.</note> (as by a <hi>Compaſſe</hi>) doe moſt <hi>Expoſitors</hi> ſhape their courſe, when they treat of <hi>Conſcience;</hi> concluding that it is a kinde of <hi>Practicall Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logiſme,</hi> whoſe <hi>Maior</hi> is <hi>The Law of</hi> GOD, and the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor,</hi> and <hi>Concluſion,</hi> the <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication</hi> of it, approuing
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:14830:16"/> what is good, and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the contrary. As thus:</p>
               <q>
                  <p>Euery diſobedient child is worthy of Puniſhment:</p>
                  <p>But I (ſaith <hi>Cham</hi>) am a diſobedient Child:</p>
                  <p>Therefore I am worthy of Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment.</p>
               </q>
               <p>If now (like good <hi>Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micks</hi>) we labour to extract the very <hi>Spirit</hi> of this <hi>Defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition,</hi> wee ſhall finde that it compriſeth the <hi>Eſſential<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> of <hi>Conſcience</hi> with the <hi>Soule,</hi> as beeing a <hi>facultie,</hi> or <hi>Part</hi> therof. Againe; it ſheds out the <hi>Subiects</hi> of <hi>Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> (that is, <hi>Men,</hi> and <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels</hi>) from all creatures that want the <hi>Diſcurſiue power:</hi> And therefore when wee finde in S. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> that
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:14830:16"/> the <hi>Hound</hi> being at default, makes a kind of <hi>Syllogiſme,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hexam. l. 6. c. 4.</note> (<hi>Aut in han<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> partem deflexit, aut in illam, aut certè in hunc anfractum ſe contulit: Sed nec in &amp;c.</hi>) Ergo &amp;c. wee muſt know that it is an <hi>Abuſiue</hi> ſpeech, as is euident by the context, where in full meaning hee aſcribes this warie caſting about of the <hi>Dogge,</hi> to the meere <hi>Sagacitie,</hi> and vigour of his ſenſe.</p>
               <p>Further, from this <hi>Defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition,</hi> doe naturally ſpring the <hi>Offices, Properties,</hi> and <hi>Kindes</hi> of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> with her whole <hi>furniture,</hi> and <hi>Appendices,</hi> which wee are to handle in due place. So that it is (in effect) the very
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:14830:17"/> 
                  <hi>Baſe,</hi> and <hi>Foundation</hi> of all the ſubſequent <hi>Diſcourſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IIII.</hi> Of the Offices of Conſcience: and firſt, that it is an Arbitratour.</head>
               <p>SVch is the <hi>Impatience,</hi> and ſurlineſſe of mans nature, that ſtruggling vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the weight of his affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, hee breathes out complaints againſt the <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice</hi> of GOD, as if the preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure exceeded the deſert. Thus IOB, (the holieſt man aliue) beeing ground to powder with the appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of his miſerie, cries<note place="margin">Iob. 14. 17. <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>atablus in Loc.</hi>
                  </note> out that GOD had <hi>ſealed</hi> vp his iniquities in a <hi>Bagge,</hi> and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:14830:17"/> added vnto his wickednes: as if hee would ſay (if hee durſt) that the Lord kept his ſinnes exactly, &amp; made them more then they were.</p>
               <p>In another place he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaines,<note place="margin">Iob 16. 12. 14. 21.</note> that <hi>God</hi> had taken him by the necke, and beat him, and runne vpon him like a <hi>Gyant,</hi> as if hee would ſue the Lord vpon an acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Batterie;</hi> for preſently<note place="margin">Iob 38. 39. 40.</note> after, he mumbles thus, <hi>Oh that a man might plead with God, as a Man doth with his Neighbour.</hi> But after the Lord vouchſafed to parle with him, and cald in <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> as an <hi>Vmpier,</hi> to take vp the matter betwixt them, then <hi>Iob</hi> that ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>while was ſo exorbitant (in
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:14830:18"/> an ouer-loue of himſelfe) bewailes his ſtate, and fals<note place="margin">Iob 42. 6.</note> to deprecation.</p>
               <p>Thus the <hi>Emperour Mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritius,</hi> what time his <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,</hi> and his moſt deare, and vertuous <hi>Wife</hi> were all cruelly ſlaine, one after an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, before his eyes, at the charge, and command of the Tyrant <hi>Phocas</hi> (himſelfe being immediately to act his part in the ſame <hi>Trage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die</hi>) his fleſh (no doubt) like a grudging <hi>Iſraelite,</hi> began to murmure againſt the Lord; but after ſome paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionate breathings, and pauſes (his <hi>Conſcience</hi> awar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding him <hi>Hell,</hi> if <hi>God</hi> ſhould haue beene extreme to marke what he had done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:14830:18"/> hee thus quietly and meekely concludeth, <hi>Iuſtus es, Domine, &amp; Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Functius Carion. Oſiander. Melanct. Loc. Com.</note> 
                  <hi>Iudicium tuum;</hi> Righ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teous art thou (O Lord) and iuſt is thy iudgement.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> That Conſcience is a Conuincer.</head>
               <p>WHen I conſider the force of <hi>Conſcience</hi> in the <hi>Conuiction</hi> of <hi>Errour,</hi> mee thinkes <hi>Shee</hi> is like the Martyr <hi>Steuen.</hi> For neither<note place="margin">Act. 5. 9. 10</note> 
                  <hi>Libertines,</hi> nor <hi>Cyrenians,</hi> nor they of <hi>Alexandria, Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licia, Aſia,</hi> no nor all the tranſcendent, and ſubli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated wits of the world, that will vndertake to cut
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:14830:19"/> 
                  <hi>Cummin-ſeede,</hi> with <hi>Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nine,</hi> are able to reſiſt the <hi>Wiſedome,</hi> and the <hi>Spirit,</hi> by which ſhee ſpeakes. For inſtance: The <hi>Diagoream,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cic. de Nat. Deor.</note> or <hi>Atheiſt,</hi> would gladly threap vpon his ſoule, that <hi>There is no</hi> GOD. <hi>Dixit in</hi> CORDE <hi>ſuo</hi> (ſaith Saint<note place="margin">Aug. in. Pſa. 14. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Auguſtine) qui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> hoc nemo au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit dicere, etiamſi auſus fuerit cogitare;</hi> Hee ſaid it in his <hi>Heart,</hi> becauſe, for ſhame, he durſt not vtter it with his lips. <hi>O Idoll!</hi> The Heauens<note place="margin">Pſal. 19. 1. Pſa. 104. 12</note> declare the <hi>glorie</hi> of GOD, and yet hee ſees them not: the <hi>Birds</hi> ſing Anthems of his praiſe, and yet he heares them not; the flowers dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe ſweet ſents into the <hi>Ayre,</hi> and yet he ſmels them
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:14830:19"/> not: in euery <hi>Vine,</hi> there is <hi>Water</hi> turned into <hi>Wine,</hi> and yet he taſtes it not: and though GOD may bee felt with the hand (as <hi>S. Paul</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 17. 27.</note> affirmeth) in euery crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, yet being ſtarke dead, he is voide of that laſt, and common ſence. And now comes <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens vp this <hi>Monſter</hi> in <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> and giues him a thump on the breſt, and beates it into him, maugre his heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bloud, that <hi>There is a</hi> GOD: and ſummons him to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare at the great <hi>Tribunall,</hi> for attempting to deface the <hi>Characters</hi> of the <hi>Deitie,</hi> ſo plainely, and deepely written with GODS owne hand in the heart of euery man.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:14830:20"/>
               <p>Another inſtance of the power of <hi>Conſcience</hi> is the Refutation and confuſion of thoſe deteſtable <hi>Hereticks</hi> (or rather more then <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks,</hi> as <hi>Irenaeus</hi> cals them) who charge the moſt Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous GOD, to be the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor</hi> of ſinne; and that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Indirectly,</hi> as <hi>Simon</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tertul. Iren. Aug.</note> 
                  <hi>Magus,</hi> the <hi>Cerdoniſts, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cioniſts, Manichees, Priſcilli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts,</hi> and others; or elſe <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly,</hi> as <hi>Florinus,</hi> and the <hi>Seleucians,</hi> with whom wee may ſhackle foote to foot, the damnable ſect of the <hi>Libertines,</hi> whoſe <hi>Ring-Leaders</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Caluin Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſus Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertinos. Bulling. Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſus A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabap. l. 2. c. 14.</note> were <hi>Coppin,</hi> and <hi>Quintin,</hi> two <hi>Coblers</hi> of <hi>Flanders.</hi> With theſe hide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Giants</hi> incounters <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:14830:20"/> and catching them by the throat, breathes fire and brimſtone in their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and in time of diſtreſſe, and horror, compels them to retract this fearfull blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemie.</p>
               <p>Another inſtance of the ſtrength of <hi>Conſcience</hi> is in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>futing thoſe ſlow-bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lied<note place="margin">Zanch. de Immort. Anim.</note> 
                  <hi>Cretians,</hi> who treading in the ſteps of the <hi>Sadduces,</hi> and <hi>Epicures,</hi> and ſome of the courſer ſort of <hi>Peripa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teticks,</hi> would haue the ſoule to bee vaparous, and mortall. For when once theſe <hi>Beaſts</hi> come to bee haled to the ſlaughter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe, and that they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue their end is approch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, then ſteps in <hi>Conſcience,</hi>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:14830:21"/> and ſtiffely pleades the ſoules <hi>Immortalitie,</hi> ſo that in the ſence of the truth thereof, they are forced to roare, and hang out the tongue.</p>
               <p>Another Inſtance of the efficacie of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> is in the <hi>Repulſe</hi> of the <hi>Roman-Catholicks</hi> both <hi>Hereſies,</hi> and <hi>Calumnies.</hi> And firſt, for their <hi>Hereſies,</hi> ſince the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of this Treatiſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids <hi>Polemical Diſcourſe</hi> (vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe obliquely, and by oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion) I will content my ſelfe with one Article, but yet of ſuch weight, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, as that it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines the very ſap, and life of Religion. It is the point of <hi>Iuſtification by Faith alone,</hi>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:14830:21"/> that is, <hi>by Chriſt alone</hi> (for it is not the <hi>Inſtrument,</hi> but the <hi>Obiect</hi> which wee ſtand vpon.) This ſound poſition the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> vtterly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>auow, and in ſtead thereof, they ſet to ſale their <hi>Linſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woolſie</hi> webbe, the <hi>warpe</hi> whereof is <hi>Workes,</hi> and the <hi>woofe, Faith;</hi> the long thrids mans <hi>Merite,</hi> and the ſhort inter-iected thrids, the Merit of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> But marke. When theſe iolly <hi>Sophisters</hi> are at their way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate, and that they lye pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and gaſping on their <hi>Pallet,</hi> then nothing but <hi>Chriſt, Christ,</hi> and then not a word of <hi>Workes,</hi> and <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit:</hi> ſuch difference is there betweene <hi>Schoole-diſputes</hi>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:14830:22"/> on a <hi>Cuſhion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> and the wrings of <hi>Conſcience</hi> on ones <hi>Death<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And here I cannot let paſſe the vnproſperous ſucceſſe of <hi>Cardinall Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine,</hi> their <hi>Pythagoras.</hi> For hauing gone about to prooue the concurrence of <hi>Faith,</hi> and <hi>Workes</hi> in the point of <hi>Iuſtification,</hi> and that at large, euen to ſacie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and ſurfet; at laſt, infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by the reuerberations and recoilements of his owne <hi>Conſcience, Penelope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like,</hi> he vntwiſts his labour, vnſaies all againe, and is driuen to turne Proteſtant whether he will or no.</p>
               <p>But that I may be cleere from the imputation of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurie,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:14830:22"/> I will ſet downe his words as they came from his owne <hi>pen,</hi> which (no doubt) like <hi>Pilats,</hi> was ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruled by the ſecret hand, and prouidence of GOD. They are theſe; <hi>Propter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certitudinem</hi>
                  <note place="margin">De Iuſtific. l. 5. c. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>propriae Iuſtitiae, &amp; periculum inanis gloriae, tutiſsimum eſt fiduciam</hi> TO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TAM <hi>in</hi> SOLA <hi>Dei miſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordia, &amp; benignitate repo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere:</hi> By reaſon of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaintie of a mans owne righteouſneſſe, and for feare of vaineglory, it is the ſafeſt way to repoſe our <hi>whole</hi> confidence in the <hi>On<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mercie,</hi> and goodneſſe of GOD.</p>
               <p>I confeſſe, that cloſe vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this <hi>Luther</hi>-like <hi>Apho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſme,</hi>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:14830:23"/> he ſettles himſelfe to the vnfolding of his owne meaning, but with ſuch perplexneſſe, and ſhifting, as that but for his olde friend <hi>Qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dammodo,</hi> (Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin-german to <hi>Non pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priè, Non abſolutè,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuch nice, and chea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>Aduerbs</hi>) hee might ſeeme to haue beene found within the compaſſe of a <hi>Spaniſh Inquiſition.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now, concerning the power of <hi>Conſcience</hi> in the repulſe of <hi>Calumnies,</hi> though it bee not alwayes apparant in regard of the ſtupified heart of the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſarie: yet in a diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion not wholly graceleſſe, it giues ſome glimpſe of an
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:14830:23"/> inward conuulſion. And here, let mee once againe produce Cardinall <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine:</hi> who attempting the ruine of <hi>Religion,</hi> by the diſgrace of her <hi>Profeſſours,</hi> moſt virulently writeth, that <hi>Caluin</hi> (a man of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular learning and ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie) <hi>was eaten to death with Wormes</hi> (like <hi>Antiochus, He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">De Notis Eccleſ. lib. 4. cap. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>Maximinus, Huneri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus</hi>) and that hee dyed <hi>blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheming and calling vpon the Deuill: Ne ipſe quidem Dae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Controuerſ. Secund. Quaeſt. Quint. c. 15</note> 
                  <hi>potuit malitioſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s loqui</hi> (ſayth good <hi>Whitaker</hi>) Not <hi>Belzebub</hi> himſelfe could haue ſpoken more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpightfully. Now to ſhew that he wrote this palpable lye againſt his own minde,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:14830:24"/> hee forthwith addeth, <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatur Hieronymus Bolſecus, Ierome Bolſeck</hi> ſayes thus, not I. For hee knew in his <hi>Conſcience,</hi> that this <hi>Bolſeck</hi> was an impure, and perfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious <hi>Apoſtata,</hi> the moſt notorious <hi>Stigmatick</hi> of the World, and the very <hi>Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cubus</hi> of the <hi>Deuill.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> That Conſcience is an Eſpiall.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>COnſcience is the Lords</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Numb. 13. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>Spye,</hi> diſpatched (like a <hi>Caleb,</hi> or <hi>Ioſhua</hi>) to view the ſtrength, and weakneſſe of euery man. It is <hi>Gods Pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> ſent out to make a Diſcouerie of the Coaſt,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:14830:24"/> and to returne aduertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. It is the keeper of that Poore Priſoner the<note place="margin">Non Caro, ſed Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tela Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, Carcer eſt. Aug. in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nar. <hi>Pſ. 142. 7. Ioſh. 7. 21.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Soule,</hi> whom it watches, &amp; followes at the heele, while it is in <hi>Durance,</hi> in the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible bodie. Shee ſaw <hi>Acha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> well enough, when he hid the Wedge of Gold in the earth. Shee lookt <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> in the face, and frowned vpon him, when hee ſhut the doore, in hope to haue ſinned (with <hi>Bathſheba</hi>) vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcerned.<note place="margin">2. Sa. 12. 12.</note> Shee beheld (with <hi>Ezekiel</hi>) what the<note place="margin">Ezek. 8. 12.</note> Ancients of the houſe of <hi>Iſrael</hi> did in the darke, when they offered vp Cloudes of <hi>Incenſe</hi> to their <hi>Idols,</hi> and then bleſt themſelues with this baſe deluſion, <hi>Tuſh,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:14830:25"/> The Lord ſees vs not, Hee hath forſaken the Earth.</hi> And as ſhee is an <hi>Eagle</hi> in the ſharpneſſe of her ſight; ſo can ſhee ouer-heare the ſof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt whiſperings, and <hi>Eliſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Kings 6. 8. 9.</note> know what is contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in the <hi>Aramites</hi> priua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt counſels.</p>
               <p>Since therfore each man, attended by his owne <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> is, in this, a kind of <hi>Scipio, Neuerleſſe alone, than when he is alone,</hi> let him ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer thinke to worke wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe vnſeene, vnleſſe hee can find meanes to run away from himſelfe. It is<note place="margin">Plato. Cic. Ambr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe. De Offic. l. 3 cap. 5.</note> not his <hi>Gyges Ring</hi> wil ſerue the turne.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:14830:25"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> That Conſcience is an Appeacher.</head>
               <p>SVch is the folly of an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regenerate man, as he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> preſumes, becauſe <hi>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcienc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> is an <hi>Inmate,</hi> that ſhee will ſtand by, and ſee, and heare, and ſay nothing. And be cauſe it is now <hi>Vacation,</hi> hee thinkes it will neuer bee <hi>Terme-time</hi> with <hi>Conſcience.</hi> But (to vſe the wordes o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Saint <hi>Ierome) Tranquillitas</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ad Helio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor.</note> 
                  <hi>iſta, Tempeſtas eſt; This Calme is but the Mother of a Storme;</hi> for ere long he ſhal eſpie a <hi>Weather-gawle in the Ayre.</hi> The Watch of his <hi>Clock</hi> now goes not, and the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:14830:26"/> Wheeles ſtand ſtill, being clam'd, and ruſted in their ioynts; but when by Gods hand the heauie Waights of <hi>Sinne</hi> ſhall bee hung vpon the Lines, (and that vvithout any counter poyze of <hi>mercy</hi>) then ſhall the <hi>Hammer</hi> ſtrike thicke, and indiſtinctly, I meane, his owne tongue ſhall blab thoſe foule enormities, which ſo long he hath ſmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered, and concealed in his boſome. He is now at eaſe, and vowes if he <hi>Feſſe,</hi> he will neuer <hi>Con;</hi> but alas (ſilly ſoule) when <hi>Sci,</hi> and <hi>Con</hi> (to ſing with him in his owne <hi>Cliffe</hi>) haue ſet him vpon the Racke, hee ſhall perforce ſpell, and put to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:14830:26"/> and that without any iocular inuerſion. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Satan comes, and with his <hi>Quill</hi> blowes <hi>Fig-duſt</hi> into his eyes, tell me then if hee ſtampe not, and cry not out againſt himſelfe.</p>
               <p>O that wee men would thus reaſon with our ſelues, when the bait of Pleaſure is caſt before vs! What? <hi>Shall</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 39. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>I doe this great wickedneſſe, and ſinne againſt God?</hi> Is there any thing ſo ſecret,<note place="margin">Mat<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 10. 26</note> that ſhall not be diſcloſed? If I commit it in the <hi>Wood,</hi> ſhall not a <hi>Bird</hi> of the <hi>Ayre</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſt. 10. 20.</note> carrie the voyce, and that which hath wings tell the matter? If I do it in the <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt,</hi> am I yet to learne that<note place="margin">Numb. 22. 28.</note> a <hi>Beaſt</hi> hath ſpoken? If in
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:14830:27"/> my <hi>Bed-chamber,</hi> ſhall not<note place="margin">Hab. 2. 11.</note> the <hi>Stone</hi> out of the Wall, and <hi>Beame</hi> out of the Tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber cry vengeance againſt me? But if all theſe faile, woe, and alas, I ſhall not be able to keepe mine owne counſell; but eyther I ſhall impart it to my familiar friend, who will proue but a riuen diſh; or elſe in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany I ſhall blurt it out at vnawares; or talke of it in my ſleepe: or vtter it on my Death-bed, to mine owne ſhame, and ſcandall of the <hi>Goſpell: Malum hoc, &amp; malum</hi>
                  <note place="margin">De Contrit. Cord. Auth. Inc.</note> 
                  <hi>hoc; ſed minus hoc; &amp; maius hoc.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:14830:27"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> That Conſcience is a Monitor.</head>
               <p>AFter <hi>Gregory</hi> had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen<note place="margin">Paſtoralis Curae, Quarta Pars.</note> 
                  <hi>ſixe and thirtie Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitions,</hi> concerning the ſeuerall eſtates of men, hee thus modeſtly concludeth: <hi>Pulchrum depinxi hominem, Pictor foedus;</hi> I haue por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traid a faire man, being my ſelfe but a <hi>Bungler</hi> at the <hi>Penſill.</hi> And (in truth) there is alwaies ſome imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in humane Aduertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. For eyther they proceed from the humour of <hi>Reuenge,</hi> and <hi>Vaineglorie,</hi> or elſe from flying reports, and ſuppoſals, or from ſelfe-guiltineſſe of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooued
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:14830:28"/> fault; or if they bee free from all theſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers, and aſperſions, yet can they not cenſure an <hi>Interior</hi> euill. But <hi>Conſcience</hi> being deputed a <hi>Moniſher</hi> from GOD, and looking in at the caſement of the <hi>Soule,</hi> is not eaſily corrupted by the former, nor deceiued in the laſt.</p>
               <p>And beſides this <hi>Inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuouſneſſe,</hi> and <hi>Certainty</hi> of her <hi>Items</hi> (ſo long as ſhee ſtands informed by the Word of God) there is found a <hi>Maieſty</hi> in the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of their giuing: for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Gods <hi>Vice-Roy, Shee</hi> prayes not, but inioynes, becauſe <hi>Requeſts,</hi> and <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunds</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bodin. De Rep. l. 3. c. 4.</note> are incompatible
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:14830:28"/> in a <hi>Prince,</hi> as derogating from <hi>Soueraigntie,</hi> &amp; <hi>Power:</hi> for <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and <hi>Kings</hi> intreat not. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſayth,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 5. 20</note> As though GOD did <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech</hi> you; hee cloſely im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyes, that the <hi>Edicts</hi> of <hi>God</hi> are <hi>Monitorie,</hi> and <hi>Iuſſorie,</hi> not <hi>Petitorie,</hi> and ſtooping. It is therefore a ſpeciall point of wiſedome, heed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to minde the <hi>Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>word</hi> of ones <hi>Conſcience:</hi> for, if in the prepenſion of ſome intended act, <hi>She</hi> ſhall deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cry eyther <hi>turpitude,</hi> or <hi>doubtfulneſſe,</hi> it is time to ſound the <hi>Retrait.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:14830:29"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> That Conſcience is a Shoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>COnſcience,</hi> by <hi>Origen,</hi> is<note place="margin">In Epiſt. ad Rom. 2. Velut Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dagogus ei quidam ſociatus. In Gen.</note> compared to a <hi>Schoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter,</hi> aſſociate to the <hi>Soule</hi> to direct, and tutour it; and by <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> to a <hi>ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Schoolemaſter;</hi> not that it is able to lead vs to ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in this obſcuritie, and corruption of naturall knowledge; but that it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formeth vs in many things, and is auaileable to make vs vnexcuſable for the <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pet. Mart. Loc. Com. <hi>Mat. 7. 12.</hi>
                  </note> of <hi>Conſcience</hi> is,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alteri non facere, quod nolis pati:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Not to doe that to another, which thou would'ſt not ſuffer thy ſelfe.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:14830:29"/>
               <p>And here wee muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, that (as <hi>Auſten</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aug. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſ. 1. ca. 18</note> wittily and diuinely no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth) wee bee carefull to a uoyd the <hi>Soleciſmes</hi> of <hi>Manners.</hi> For, if wee bee ſure of the <hi>Rod,</hi> or <hi>Ferule,</hi> if without an <hi>Aſpiration</hi> (contrarie to <hi>Grammatica<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Diſcipline</hi>) wee pronounce <hi>Ominem,</hi> for <hi>Hominem:</hi> then let vs not dreame of eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the <hi>Scourge</hi> of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> if we ſhall irregular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and incongruouſly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haue our ſelues, in the courſe, and paſſage of our liues.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:14830:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> That Conſcience is a Dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall Chaplaine.</head>
               <p>IT is a terrible ſaying of<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1. 26.</note> the Apoſtle, that <hi>Not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Mightie, not many No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble are called:</hi> one reaſon whereof amongſt the reſt, is their <hi>Impatience</hi> of <hi>Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation,</hi> for that (oft-times) they are of the nature of the <hi>Thiſtle,</hi> where they ſhould be like <hi>Clarie,</hi> which is ſoft in the hand, and hath a <hi>Downe,</hi> or <hi>Cotton</hi> vpon it. Hence it comes to paſſe, that hauing flattering <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets</hi> about them, (which put <hi>Honie</hi> into the <hi>Sacrifice,</hi> in ſtead of <hi>Salt</hi>) they dream of <hi>Peace,</hi> euen when the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:14830:30" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
                  <hi>Lord of Hoſts is vp on Armes againſt them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I know the <hi>Perſons</hi> of <hi>Kings</hi> are <hi>Sacred,</hi> and their <hi>Crownes,</hi> no <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> or <hi>Garlands,</hi> but conſiſting of <hi>Preeminence,</hi> &amp; <hi>Power:</hi> I like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe am not ignorant, that <hi>Miniſters</hi> of <hi>State,</hi> and <hi>Perſonages</hi> nobly deſcended, haue an extraordinarie ſtampe of <hi>Honour</hi> ſet vpon them: yet becauſe they are all the <hi>Sonnes</hi> of <hi>Adam,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolued in <hi>Sinne,</hi> and <hi>Wrath,</hi> aſwell as others, and haue greater occaſions of temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations then their <hi>Inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours,</hi> as ſayling both with <hi>Wind,</hi> &amp; <hi>Tyde</hi> againſt them; it is very requiſite that they ſometimes bee punctually
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:14830:31"/> dealt withall, prouided al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes that it be performed with great reuerence, and diſcretion.</p>
               <p>But becauſe <hi>degenerate</hi> and <hi>temporizing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> are ſo rife and common <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the Would and thoſe that are of a more t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>anke, and generous <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> doe ſometim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> paſſe by the ſinnes of <hi>Men</hi> in <hi>Aut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>itie,</hi> the Lord (in mercie) hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed <hi>Conſcience</hi> their <hi>Chaplaine</hi> in <hi>Ordinarie,</hi> who will not feare to reprooue them vnpartially, but like <hi>Nathan</hi> will tell them to their faces, one by one; <hi>Thou art the man.</hi> Of which plaine and gracious aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſement,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:14830:31"/> if they ſhall make good vſe, they are ſure to partake in the glorious <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledges</hi> of the <hi>Saints.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XI.</hi> That Conſcience is a Prog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nosticator.</head>
               <p>IT is but the vaine at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of a preſuming braine, to <hi>Calculate Natiui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ties,</hi> and to tell you (with a trice) whether your daies ſhall bee bleſſed, or vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperous. For whether the <hi>Starres</hi> doe <hi>ſignificare potiùs</hi>
                  <note place="margin">See Aug. de Ciu. Dei. 5. c. 1. 2. 3. &amp;c</note> 
                  <hi>quam facere,</hi> rather fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhew, than cauſe: or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Mars</hi> doe <hi>Homicidam facere,</hi> make a Man an <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micide,</hi> as the <hi>Mathematicks</hi>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:14830:32"/> determine; there was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer yet any that could ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly define, why in the life of <hi>Twinnes,</hi> there ſhould be ſuch diſparilitie in actions, euents, profeſsions, arts, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, and euen in death it ſelfe, being borne contigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly one after another (as <hi>Iacob,</hi> who caught <hi>Eſau</hi> by the heele) and being ſemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate in the ſame moment. For if the Anſwere of <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gidius</hi> concerning the ſwift whirling about of the <hi>Pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> wheele (ſo much ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauded by <hi>Mathematici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi>) be intertained, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced for current, it quite ouerthroweth the <hi>Geneth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liacall</hi> profeſsion: inaſmuch as in an incomprehenſible
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:14830:32"/> moment of time there is ſuch a mutation of all things, by reaſon of the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacitie of the heauen, that they become not onely di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, but contrarie: which made S. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> conclude, that this figment of the wheele was more fraile, and brittle, then the veſſels made by the rotation of it.</p>
               <p>Let this then be noted as a point of infallibilitie, that whatſoeuer is decreed in the great <hi>Senat</hi> of the <hi>Stars,</hi> is ouer-ruled by the power, and wiſedome of their moſt glorious <hi>Creator,</hi> who hath made them <hi>Attendants</hi> to man, to comfort him, and not <hi>Lords,</hi> to ſway him, and ſhape out his condition.</p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:14830:33"/>
               <p>If then you would know, whether you ſhall be hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py in the remainder of your life, or whether wretched, and full of diſcomfiture; the moſt compendiarie way to attaine the ſumme of your deſire, is to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound the <hi>Queſtion</hi> to your <hi>Conſcience,</hi> which wil quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſolue you in the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Eſayes</hi> aſſeueration:</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Surely it ſhall be well with the Iuſt: Woe be to the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, it ſhall be euill with him.<note place="margin">Iſaiah 3. 10, 11.</note>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>From whence you may ſafely, and certainely <hi>Prog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſticate,</hi> that ſince the bloud of <hi>Chriſt</hi> is precious vnto you, and that you loath and deteſt Sinne, as the very <hi>Bane,</hi> and <hi>Apollyon</hi>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:14830:33"/> of the world, your daies ſhal be good, and your conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion peaceable. But if at<note place="margin">Pſal. 37. 37</note> this preſent, you be frozen in your dregs, and reſolue to continue in your rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous courſes, preſuming that a <hi>Lord, Lord,</hi> will ſerue the turne at the cloſe of your life, (which is nothing elſe but <hi>Infidelis fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ucia, A faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe confidence,</hi> as S. <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi> cals it) then ſurely <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> (which is the <hi>Pulſe</hi> of the ſoule) will tell you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forehand, that your bud ſhall bee rottenneſſe, and your end wrapped vp in woe, and diſhonour.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:14830:34"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XII.</hi> That Conſcience is a Regiſter.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Conſcience</hi> is a <hi>Notarie</hi> that hath alwaies the <hi>Pen</hi> in hand, and keepes a <hi>Catalogue,</hi> or <hi>Diarie</hi> of our ſinnes. <hi>Shee</hi> ſets downe all our debts in her <hi>Booke of Account,</hi> euen an <hi>Hundred</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ferus in Math. 18.</note> 
                  <hi>Thouſand Talents; Magna ſumma, quam tamen omnes Deo debemus;</hi> A mightie ſumme, and yet wee owe (all of vs) as much to GOD. Shee omitteth no default through ſlownes of hand, for ſhee writes by <hi>Characte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie;</hi> neither ſtrikes ſhe out any through deceit, like the<note place="margin">Luk. 16. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>vniuſt Steward,</hi> that bade
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:14830:34"/> put downe <hi>fiftie</hi> in ſtead of an <hi>hundred;</hi> nor yet indures ſhee to ouer-reckon, for how can <hi>Conſcience</hi> bee ſo vnconſcionable? Nor can her letters be raced out, for they are written with a <hi>Pen</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ier. 17. 1.</note> of <hi>Iron,</hi> and with the <hi>claw</hi> of a <hi>Diamond.</hi> Which ought greatly to moue vs to an heedfull conſideration of our waies. For if the Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Martyr <hi>Latimer,</hi> took ſpeciall care to the placing of his words, in his <hi>Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">This He teſtifieth of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, in his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched at Stamford.</note> when hee heard the <hi>Pen</hi> walking in the chimnie behinde the cloth: how circumſpectly ought euery of vs to looke vnto our waies, and to guard our ſenſes, which are <hi>Ianuae Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptionis,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:14830:35"/> the Gates</hi> of <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In Pſ. 49.</note> (as S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> calls them) ſith <hi>Conſcience</hi> is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually <hi>Recording</hi> our acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, with the time when, the place where, and the maner how they were per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIII.</hi> That Conſcience is a Iudge.</head>
               <p>AFter that <hi>Conſcience</hi> hath purſued the poor ſinner, flowne him to the marke, attacht him, exa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mind him, and committed him: at laſt <hi>Shee</hi> comman deth the <hi>Priſoner</hi> to bee brought forth to the <hi>Barre.</hi> And ſitting on the <hi>Bench,</hi> in Robes of <hi>Maieſtie,</hi> betwixt
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:14830:35"/> 
                  <hi>Leo,</hi> and <hi>Libra</hi> (the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleme of <hi>Courage</hi> in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and <hi>Indifferencie</hi> in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termining) ſhee cauſeth the <hi>Booke</hi> of <hi>Moſes</hi> Law to bee ſpred before him, which forthwith begins to plead for the tranſgreſsion of her precepts, requiring for ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction the bloud of the Offender, for that hee hath wilfully broken them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for number few, for vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding plaine, for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie not contradictable.</p>
               <p>Hereat the wretched ſoule is agaſt, and being <hi>Selfe-condemned,</hi> confeſſeth<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Tit. 3. 11.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Guilty;</hi> when being pinni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ond, and looking for ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die execution, his heart would breake, but for the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:14830:36"/> hope of a mercifull <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> And thus much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Offices</hi> of <hi>Conſcience</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XII.</hi> Of the Properties of <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>ence, and first of and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>stification.</head>
               <p>IT followeth no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> we treat of the <hi>Pro</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> the firſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <note place="margin">Aquin 1. Quaeſt. 69. Art. 13.</note> of is <hi>Teſtification,</hi> that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Calling to Remembra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſuch a thing was done, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> done.</hi> To this purpoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> keth the <hi>Wiſe man</hi> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <note place="margin">Scit enim Conſcientia tua. I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r.</note> 
                  <hi>Houſholder; Oftentimes th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> heart,</hi> (that is, thy <hi>Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi>) knoweth, that thou likewise haſt curſed othe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> It was this <hi>Teſtifying</hi> Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:14830:36"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> forced the <hi>Patriarks</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 42. 21</note> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>ke backe to that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſin of ſelling their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>er <hi>Ioſeph</hi> into <hi>Egypt,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ey had committed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> twenty yeeres be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <note place="margin">Euiné Ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cubi, aut Aliquis? Confeſſ. l. x. c. 6. 7. Scitis ipſi lubricum Adolescen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae iter, in quo &amp; ego lapſus ſum &amp;c. Ad Chrom. Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginitatem in coelum fero, non quia habe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am, ſed quia magis mirer quod non habeo. Aduerſ. <hi>Iouin.</hi>
                  </note> it was this that made <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Auguſtine confeſſe,</hi> that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>ent his youth in vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Intemperancie,</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>ee was ſinfull in his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, yea when hee was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> either <hi>Any where,</hi> or <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>hing.</hi> It was this that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>S. Ierome</hi> to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ew of his greener yeeres, wherein he acknowledgeth he had a <hi>Slip,</hi> &amp; came ſhort of that <hi>Virginitie,</hi> which he ſo extolled in others. What <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hall I ſpeake of his <hi>Epiſtle <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> Euſtochium,</hi> wherein he
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:14830:37"/> feares not to make know <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> that though hee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in the vaſt, and ſolitary <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> derneſſe amongſt <hi>Scorpio</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> being ſcorched, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> like an <hi>Aethiopian;</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> though hee was rough a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſqualid with ſack-cloth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> lay vpon the bare ground <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and liu'd with ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and homely fare, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> thought it <hi>Luxurie</hi> to fee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <note place="margin">Putabam me Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis intereſſe delitijs. Saepe choris intereram Puellarum. Ad Euſto. De Cuſtod. Virgin.</note> on boild meate: yet for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> that, his mind was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> on the daintie ſights <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Rome,</hi> and ſtill hee thought hee was preſent there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Damſels.</hi> I ſpeake not this out of the forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe of dutie, as if I would diſcouer the naked<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe of the <hi>Fathers:</hi> But
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:14830:37"/> onely to ſhew, how this <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifying</hi> power wrought on them to recognize theirfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer courſes. After whoſe example, I beſeech thee (good <hi>Christian</hi>) ſeriouſly to examine thy daies mi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſpent: <hi>cum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Coram Deo, in</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bernard.</note> 
                  <hi>Lachrymis te maceraueris, precorte, vt memor ſismei.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XV.</hi> Of the ſecond Propertie of Conſcience, which is Ligation.</head>
               <p>IT is the <hi>Binding Power of</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aquin. 1. q. 69.</note> 
                  <hi>Conſcience,</hi> which iudgeth that <hi>a thing is to bee done, or not done: and therevpon ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inſtigateth the partie to vndertake it, or withdraweth
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:14830:38"/> him from attempting it.</hi> Hence is it that the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> laies downe this generall<note place="margin">Rom. 14. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>3. <hi>Conſcientia, reclamante, &amp; prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtante.</hi>
                  </note> rule, <hi>Whatſoeuer is not of Faith, is Sinne;</hi> that is, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer is done againſt <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> is offenſiue to GOD: (For, that <hi>Faith</hi> is there ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for a <hi>Perſwaſion</hi> of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> is the opinion of S. <hi>Ambroſe, Chryſoſtome, Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doret, Theophylact, Occumeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, Caluin,</hi> &amp; others.) From this ground (as it ſeemes) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſe that <hi>Axiom</hi> amongſt <hi>Diuines; Conſcientia, quam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uis erronea, ſemper ligat: Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, though erroneous, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies bindeth:</hi> with which concurreth that other, <hi>Quicquid fit contra Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Auguſt.</note> 
                  <hi>aedificat ad Gehennam,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:14830:38"/> Whatſoeuer is performed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Conſcience, helps a man on to hell-ward;</hi> the reaſon is, becauſe in ſo doing, hee hath ſinned <hi>formally</hi> againſt the Law, though not <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terially.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Heere then it muſt bee<note place="margin">Neceſſe eſt autem &amp; hoc ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iri, Conſcienti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am oportere regi verbo Dei, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanct. Loc. Com.</note> carefully remembred, that <hi>Conſcience</hi> bee guided, and gouerned by the <hi>Word of God,</hi> which alone is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per <hi>Binder</hi> thereof: For nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Humane Lawes,</hi> nor <hi>Oathes,</hi> nor <hi>Promiſes</hi> haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Coactiue</hi> power in the ſoule, but as they haue au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, and vertue there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:14830:39"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVI.</hi> Of the third, and fourth Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties of Conſcience, which are Excuſation, and Accu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſation.</head>
               <p>THe <hi>Conſcience</hi> iudging of ſome fact commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, doth <hi>Excuſe,</hi> and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, if it be good and war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable; but if it be found ſwaruing from the Law of GOD, there inſueth an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation, accompanied with the ſting of ſorrow, and remorſe. Thus <hi>Abime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lech</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 20. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5.</note> (King of <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rar</hi>) being reprooued of GOD in a dreame, for taking away the wife of <hi>Abraham,</hi> conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth preſently with his <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience:</hi> &amp; finding his <hi>minde
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:14830:39"/> vpright,</hi> and his <hi>hands inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent,</hi> he appealeth to GOD, and is cleered by him. On the contrarie, when <hi>Adam,</hi> againſt the expreſſe charge, and commaundement of GOD, had eaten of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden fruit his <hi>Conſcience</hi> ſmiting him, hee hid him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe among the Trees of the garden; which made the Lord call to him with an <hi>Adam, vbi es?</hi> Adam,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen. 3. 9.</hi> De Ciu. Dei l. 13. c. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>where art thou? Non vti<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ignorando quaerens, ſed incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pando admonens,</hi> ſaith <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine; Not as though God knew not where he was ſquat, but to check, and admoniſh him for his wilfull praevarica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> This of the <hi>Properties</hi> of <hi>Conſcience.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:14830:40"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVII.</hi> Of the kindes of Conſcience, which are Good, and Euill; and firſt, of the Good.</head>
               <p>NOw for the <hi>Kindes,</hi> (that I may declare my minde with popular fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilitie) <hi>Conſcience,</hi> is either <hi>Good,</hi> or <hi>Euill. Good Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is that, which being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned by the Word of</hi> GOD,<note place="margin">Epheſ, 1. 17, 18. 1. Ioh. 1. 7. H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>b. 9. 14. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Pet. 1. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>and purged by the Bloud of Chriſt from the Guilt, and Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of Sinne, and from dead workes to ſerue the liuing</hi> GOD, <hi>is cheared vp with ioy vnſpeakeable, and glorious.</hi> In this <hi>Deſcription</hi> are contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the <hi>Cauſes</hi> concurrent to the <hi>Nature,</hi> and <hi>being</hi> of
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:14830:40"/> 
                  <hi>Good Conſcience,</hi> which are <hi>Knowledge, Faith, Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, Peace;</hi> of each where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of wee are ſucceſsiuely to intreat.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVIII.</hi> That the knowledge of <hi>GODS</hi> Word, is neceſſary to the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Conſcience.</head>
               <p>TO the end the <hi>People</hi> of <hi>Iſrael</hi> might feare the Lord, &amp; walke in vpright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of <hi>Conſcience</hi> before him, he is euer calling vpon them to harken vnto his Law, which hee comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to be written vpon the <hi>Poſts</hi> of their houſe, and<note place="margin">Deut. 6. 7. 8. 9.</note> vpon their gates, and to be rehearſed (or whet) conti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nually
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:14830:41"/> to their children, at home, and abroad, when they goe to bed, and when they ryſe in the morning. And leſt any of them ſhuld exempt themſelues vnder colour of <hi>Sexe,</hi> or <hi>Degree,</hi> or <hi>Age,</hi> hee anticipates with a plain, and familiar diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, naming <hi>Men, Women,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 31. 11. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>Children, Stra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers.</hi> Thus the <hi>Prophets</hi> alſo in all matters of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> ſend ouer the <hi>People, To the Law,</hi> and <hi>To</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſai. 8. 20.</note> 
                  <hi>the Teſtimonie;</hi> and the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle Paul</hi> writing to the <hi>Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Col. 3. 16.</note> giueth charge that the <hi>Word of Christ dwell plente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly</hi> in them. Whereupon Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> (very ear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſtly vrging the practice<note place="margin">In Hom. 9. in Epiſt. ad Coloſſ.</note> of this dutie) ſpeaketh on
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:14830:41"/> this wiſe: <hi>Audite obſecro, Seculares OMNES! com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate vobis Biblia, Animae Pharmaca: hoc demum malo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum omnium Cauſa eſt, quòd Scripturae ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur: I beſeech you harken, All yee that bee Lay-men! in any wiſe get you Bibles, the only Phyſicke for the Soule; alas, this is the Cauſe of all miſchiefe, that men are ignorant of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now there are two eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al <hi>Reaſons</hi> of this <hi>Neceſsity</hi> of the <hi>Word,</hi> to the <hi>Goodneſſe of Conſcience.</hi> One is, becauſe it directeth the <hi>Vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,</hi> and <hi>pointeth</hi> it to the <hi>middle</hi> way, betweene the<note place="margin">Deut. 5. 32.</note> 
                  <hi>Right</hi> hand, and the <hi>Left,</hi> preſeruing, and ſtaying it in
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:14830:42"/> all doubts, and demurres, vpon warrant of the invio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable truth thereof.</p>
               <p>The other is, for that it is a <hi>Word</hi> of <hi>Power,</hi> working<note place="margin">Heb. 4. 12.</note> mightily vpon the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, eyther to the battering of the heart in pieces (in which regard it is compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red<note place="margin">Ier. 23. 29.</note> to a Hammer that brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the ſtone) or elſe to the refreſhing of it, when it is bruiſed (in which ſenſe it is likened to the <hi>dropping Ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny.</hi>)<note place="margin">Pſal. 19. 10</note> Therefore, when wee ſhall reade the thundering Sentences of the <hi>Fathers,</hi> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in their <hi>Apologies</hi> of the <hi>Christian Faith,</hi> or <hi>Exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> to the obedience ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, wee muſt not reſt in the applauſe of their <hi>Rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick,</hi>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:14830:42"/> but aſcribe the power to that Word, which made <hi>Foelix</hi> tremble; or rather to<note place="margin">Acts 24. 26.</note> the Lord, the <hi>Author</hi> of that <hi>Word.</hi> The like be affirmed of the incomparable ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the <hi>Bible,</hi> euery Leafe whereof is be-ſprint with <hi>Honie-dew.</hi> For where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as<note place="margin">Pſ. 119. 103</note> it is reported of Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> (by <hi>Paulinus</hi> that<note place="margin">Paulinus ad Auguſt.</note> wrote his life) that lying in his <hi>Cradle,</hi> the <hi>Bees</hi> were ſeen to flye in, and out, at his mouth; if he literally vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand it, I cannot eaſily concurre with him in opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion; but if hee meane it of his <hi>mellifluous tongue,</hi> I wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly imbrace his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, yet with this <hi>Corolla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,</hi> that <hi>Ambroſe</hi> had all
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:14830:43"/> his <hi>Ambroſia</hi> from <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And here we may take a iuſt eſtimate, and ſcantling of the <hi>Holineſſe</hi> of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n Biſhops:</hi> who haue ſhrin'd vp <hi>Ladie IGNO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RANCE</hi> for a Saint, haue painted her face, and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed her to ſpeake fierc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly out of the window to her <hi>Oppoſites,</hi> forgetting that ere long ſhe ſhal be thrown downe, and trampled vnder foot. O the innumerable ſoules that haue periſhed in <hi>Securitie,</hi> and <hi>Deſpaire,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe theſe <hi>Iehoiakims</hi> haue<note place="margin">Ier. 36. 23.</note> cut their <hi>Bibles</hi> in pieces with their <hi>Pen-kniues,</hi> and caſt them into the fire. O <hi>Conſcience!</hi> thou maiſt take
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:14830:43"/> it on thy death, that thou art murdred by <hi>Conſcience,</hi> euen by thoſe that vaunt themſelues for thine only Champions, and Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. O wicked <hi>Church,</hi> where <hi>Ignorance, Errour, Ambition,</hi> and <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pocriſie,</hi> are the <hi>foure Cardinall Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues,</hi> whereon the frame of <hi>Religion</hi> turneth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIX.</hi> That Faith is neceſſarie to the Goodneſſe of Conſcience.</head>
               <p>THE concluſion of S <hi>Paul,</hi> is very memora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble:<note place="margin">Rom. 5. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Being iuſtified by Faith, wee haue Peace toward God, through our</hi> LORD IESVS CHRIST. For, it being ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:14830:44"/> granted (vnleſſe by the Sacrilegious <hi>Pelagian</hi>) that the poyſon of <hi>Originall Sinne,</hi> tranſmitted from our firſt <hi>Parents,</hi> hath ſpred it ſelfe ouer all the powers of the ſoule; it muſt needs fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that <hi>Conſcience</hi> (beeing a principall part thereof) is corrupted and defiled. And becauſe the <hi>Guilt</hi> of ſinne, binding ouer vnto puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, is that ſharp-pointed ſting, that woundeth vnto Death; can wee euer find redreſſe, and ſuccour, but by looking vp to the <hi>Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Num. 21. 9</note> 
                  <hi>Serpent?</hi> Is there any remiſſion of ſinne, without bloud? Is there any bloud that is <hi>Expiatory,</hi> but<note place="margin">Ioh. 3. 14. Heb. 9 22.</note> 
                  <hi>Chriſts?</hi> Will the bloud of
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:14830:44"/> 
                  <hi>Bulls,</hi> and <hi>Goats</hi> aſſwage the pang of a tormented <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience?</hi> Will the ſending out to the <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Ekron</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 King. 1. 2.</note> helpe it? Will the precious heapes of the Gold of <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uilah</hi> releeue it? Will the comfortable <hi>Iulep,</hi> and <hi>Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiske</hi> reſtore it? Will the Perfumes of the <hi>Garden,</hi> the ſtraines of <hi>Muſicke,</hi> the charme of <hi>Oratorie,</hi> or the<note place="margin">Theſe Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies were of all other moſt pleaſant: See <hi>Ierome Ad Nepo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian.</hi>
                  </note> ſporting <hi>Scenes</hi> of <hi>Atella</hi> preuaile with it? Nay, can <hi>Delight</hi> her ſelfe delight it? Nay, can the <hi>Songs</hi> of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels</hi> recouer it? May not the <hi>Conſcience</hi> (in her agonie) iuſtly cry out to theſe, as <hi>Iob</hi> did to his friends, <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iob. 16. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Comforters are you all?</hi> For ſurely theſe poore
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:14830:45"/> and outward refreſhments, are no more auaileable for the curing of the <hi>Impoſtume</hi> of the ſoule, than a <hi>Plantin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leafe</hi> layd vnto the legge, for the remoouall of the <hi>Megrimme.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XX.</hi> That Repentance is neceſſary to the goodneſſe of Conſcience.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>REpentance</hi> is ſo neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the conſtituting of <hi>Good Conſcience,</hi> that till ſinne bee remooued, and newneſſe of life begunne, the <hi>Soule</hi> can neyther bee <hi>Purified,</hi> nor <hi>Pacified.</hi> Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is <hi>King</hi> SALOMONS<note place="margin">Pſal. 45. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>Spouſe</hi> intreted to <hi>forget her
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:14830:45"/> Fathers Houſe; Grande mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculum</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Ierome</hi>)<note place="margin">Ad Euſto. De Cuſt. Virg.</note> 
                  <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ter filiam cohortatur, ne me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minerit Patris ſai; A ſtrange miracle, the Father exhorts the Daughter, not to remem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber her Father.</hi> And leſt that moytie of <hi>Repentance</hi> might ſeeme ſufficient, it preſently followeth, that the <hi>Kings Daughter is all glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 45. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>within,</hi> that is<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> inriched &amp; beautified with alſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all graces. For when a man hath once attayned to the practice of holy <hi>Duties;</hi> his <hi>Conſcience,</hi> which before lookt ſterne vpon him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnes to ſmile, and amia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to conuerſe with him. Therefore the ſaying of Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> is excellent:
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:14830:46"/> 
                  <hi>Vis nunquam eſſe tristis? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>è</hi>
                  <note place="margin">De Interior. Domo. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ap. 45.</note> 
                  <hi>viue. Wilt thou neuer bee ſad? Then ſee thou liue well.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXI.</hi> That Peace is neceſſary to the goodneſſe of Conſcience.</head>
               <p>SO great a good is <hi>Peace</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tantum eſt Pacis bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, vt ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil ſine Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce ſit bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num. De Ciuit. Dei.</hi> Hob. 13. 20. Luke 2. 13. Ro. 10. 15. Luke 10. 6. Eph. 6. 15. Pſ. 122. 3. 1. Kings 4. 24.</note> (ſayth Saint <hi>Austine</hi>) that nothing is found to bee good without it. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is the Lord, the GOD of <hi>Peace;</hi> the <hi>Angels,</hi> Sing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of <hi>Peace;</hi> the <hi>Apoſtl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s, Me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers of Peace;</hi> the <hi>Elect,</hi> the <hi>Sonnes of Peace;</hi> the <hi>New Testament,</hi> the <hi>Goſpell of Peace; Ieruſalem, the Citie of Peace;</hi> and <hi>Salomon</hi> the <hi>King of Peace.</hi> Nay, not the Arch-Pyrats, <hi>Bargulus,</hi> and <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triatus,</hi>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:14830:46"/> but intertaine a kind of <hi>Peace;</hi> for they conſpire in the Plot, and iuſtly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide their vniuſtly gotten booties. Nay more, not the very <hi>Deuils</hi> themſelues, but can (certaine thouſands of them) co-habite in one bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die.<note place="margin">Mark. 5. 9.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Now the reaſon why all things are ſo deſirous of <hi>Peace,</hi> is the intendment <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> their owne preſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>; for it is the nature <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Peace,</hi> to vnite, and ſtrengthen, as it is of <hi>Warre,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o weaken, and diſſolue. Therefore the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> cal the one <hi>Shalom,</hi> from <hi>Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gritie,</hi> and the other <hi>Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chama,</hi> from <hi>Comeſtion.</hi> And wee ſee by experience, that
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:14830:47"/> rotten wood lies looſe, and moulders away, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it wanteth the <hi>Conium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiue</hi> vertue. As all other creatures, ſo likewiſe <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> aſpireth after <hi>Peace,</hi> as her <hi>Perfecter,</hi> and <hi>Preſeruer;</hi> and therefore can neuer be ſettled, and content, till ſhe finde ſinne remitted, and GOD reconciled.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXII.</hi> Of the Bleſſedneſſe of that man, whoſe Conſcience is quieted through the pardon of his ſinne.</head>
               <p>THE learned <hi>Heathen,</hi> finding by morall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct, that there was a <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſſe</hi>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:14830:47"/> attaineable in this life, ſpent themſelues (poor ſoules) in the inueſtigation of it, and that with ſuch variouſneſſe in their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions, that they haue left behind them (as a <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moriall</hi> of their weakneſſe) <hi>about two hundred, foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Varro. Aug. De Ciuit.</note> 
                  <hi>and eight Opinions.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong which, though that bee moſt ſpecious which faſtneth one ſhanke of the Compaſſe in <hi>Ciuill Vertue,</hi> while the other runs round in the practice of it; Yet, if it be brought to the <hi>Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance</hi> of the <hi>Sanctuarie,</hi> it will want the waight, and ſubſtance of true <hi>Happineſſe.</hi> For the only <hi>Felicitie</hi> that is found among the Sonnes
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:14830:48"/> of men, conſiſteth in the <hi>Remiſsion</hi> of <hi>Sinne,</hi> and <hi>Paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of Conſcience:</hi> of the firſt whereof the <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers</hi> knew nothing, and in ſtead of the latter, betooke themſelues to a carnall ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curitie, and ſenceleſneſſe.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Prophet Dauid</hi> in an holy extaſie, and infinite feeling of this comfort, breaketh forth into this <hi>Exclamation; Beati quorum</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 32. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>ſunt remiſſae iniquitates! Oh, Bleſſed they, whoſe iniquities are forgiuen; &amp; quorum tecta ſunt peccata, non in quibus non ſunt inuenta peccata,</hi> ſayth <hi>S. Auſtine; and whoſe</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In Enarrat. in Pſ. 32.</note> 
                  <hi>ſinnes are couered, not thoſe who neuer ſinned at all!</hi> For as the ſame Father noteth)
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:14830:48"/> 
                  <hi>Si texit peccata Deus, noluit aduertere; ſi noluit aduertere, noluit animaduertere; ſi noluit animaduertere, noluit punire; noluit agnoſcere, maluit ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſcere: If God once haue co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered our ſinnes, hee meanes not to looke on them; if he will not looke on them, hee will not minde them; if hee will not mind them, he will not puniſh them; no, hee will not preſſe them, hee will rather pardon them.</hi> Now when ſinne is remooued (whoſe nature is to ſeparate betwixt GOD,<note place="margin">Iſai. 59. 2.</note> and <hi>Man</hi>) the <hi>Conſcience</hi> is ſtilled in the view and ſence of <hi>Gods fauour,</hi> which is<note place="margin">Pſal. 63. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>ſweeter then life it ſelfe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="chapter">
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:14830:49"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXIII.</hi> Of the vnſpeakeable Comfort of a Good Conſcience.</head>
               <p>KIng <hi>Salomon</hi> decyphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring<note place="margin">Pro. 15. 15.</note> the comfort of a <hi>Good Conſcience,</hi> compares it to a <hi>continual feaſt.</hi> Where, if you aske, who are the <hi>Cookes</hi> and <hi>Butlers,</hi> you are anſwered from <hi>Luther,</hi> that they are the <hi>Angels.</hi> The <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 4. 7.</note> calleth it a <hi>Peace which paſſeth al vnderſtanding,</hi> car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying with it a delight ſo exquiſite, and peereleſſe, as is not poſsible for the reach of mortalitie to imagine. This it that <hi>hidden Manna,</hi> whereof that in the <hi>Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> was but a counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>type;
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:14830:49"/> this is that <hi>white ſtone,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reu. 2. 17.</note> which <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> giues, and in this ſtone is written a new name, which no man knoweth but hee that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueth it.</p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> beeing ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken<note place="margin">In Formula Hon. vit.</note> vp and deeply affected with the admiration of the Royalties, &amp; Indowments of a <hi>Good Conſcience,</hi> deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth it on this manner: <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientia Bona, eſt Titulus Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligionis, Templum Salomonis, Ager Benedictionis, Hortus Deliciarum, Gaudium An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelorum, Arca Foederis, The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaurus Regius, Aula Dei, Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitaculum Spiritus Sancti: A Good Conſcience</hi> (ſaith hee) is <hi>The Title of Religion, The Temple of Salomon, A Field
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:14830:50"/> of Bleſsing, A Garden of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, The Ioy of Angels, The Arke of the Couenant, The Kings Eſchequer, The Court of</hi> GOD, <hi>The Manſion of the Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let a man bee arayd in Robes of <hi>Eſtate,</hi> powdred with Pearle, and let him haue <hi>Caeſars Lawrell</hi> on his head; let him be Lord of as many Kingdomes, as the Diuell ſhewed our <hi>Sauiour</hi> from the Mountaine; let him raiſe his flight into the clouds and perke vpon the talleſt <hi>Cedar;</hi> let him keepe the key of <hi>Natures Cleſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> and inrich himſelf with her munificencie: let euery winde whiſtle him good newes, and euery Bird ſing
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:14830:50"/> Madrigals as hee goes: let him bee as proſperous as <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> as good as <hi>Traian,</hi> as learned as <hi>Antoninus;</hi> yet (alas) if hee haue not the comfort of a good <hi>Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> hee wants the chiefe flower of the Garland, and all his ioyes are but faint, &amp; imperfect If vpon Earth there bee an Heauen, it is <hi>Peace of Conſcience;</hi> oh, it is the Oyle that feedes, and maintaines the Lampe of life: it's the pure-red in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt bloud of the ſoule.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="chapter">
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:14830:51"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXIIII.</hi> That the Comfort of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is Inward, and Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent of the Creatures.</head>
               <p>THe Child of GOD is not vnlike the <hi>Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exo. <hi>Cap.</hi> 25. &amp; 26.</note> which beeing couered with the skins of <hi>Beaſts,</hi> was contemptible to looke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but had within, the <hi>Arke &amp; Cherubins.</hi> And when o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers truſt to <hi>Riches, Honour, Alliance,</hi> and other ſuch broken <hi>Reeds</hi> of <hi>Egypt,</hi> hee hath a certaine <hi>Autarchie</hi> within him, relying on none but <hi>El-Schaddai,</hi> who is<note place="margin">Gen. 17. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>God All-ſufficient</hi> in himſelf, of himſelfe, for himſelfe, and for all his creatures.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="chapter">
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:14830:51"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXV.</hi> That the Comfort of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is Noble, and Sincere.</head>
               <p>THe <hi>Comfort</hi> of a <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian</hi> ſpringeth not out of tranſitorie cauſes, but is of a right noble, &amp; heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly temper; framed, &amp; plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by GODS owne hand in his ſanctified ſoule, which makes him bold, and vnconquerable as a <hi>Lion,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 28. 1.</note> and keepes him in heart, and reſolution, againſt the outragiouſneſſe, and viru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies, of al Aduerſaries, of all creatures. For, his <hi>Birth</hi> being <hi>Royall,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> his <hi>Elder Brother</hi> (according to<note place="margin">Ioh. 20 17</note>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:14830:52"/> that of <hi>S. Bernard, Deus tuus factus eſt Frater tuus: Thy</hi>
                  <note place="margin">De Quad. Deb.</note> GOD, <hi>O man, is become thy Brother</hi>) the <hi>Angels</hi> guard him, the <hi>Saints</hi> reuerence him, the <hi>Diuels</hi> feare him, and the <hi>wicked</hi> croſſe the ſtreets when they ſpy him, as not able to looke vpon the ſober, and vndaunted Maieſtie that ſhineth in his face. Thus mercie imbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing<note place="margin">Pſ. 32. 10.</note> him on euery ſide, he lifts vp his head vnto the <hi>Heauens,</hi> looking for the<note place="margin">Tit. 2. 13.</note> bleſſed hope, and appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the glorie of the mightie GOD, and of his <hi>Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Beſides; the <hi>Comfort</hi> of <hi>Conſcience</hi> is ſound, and <hi>ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere,</hi> without <hi>mixture,</hi>
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:14830:52"/> and infection of attendant griefe, (vnleſſe in ſome ſharpe aſſault, and conflict) but is perfectly refined in the life to come, from all droſſe of ſorrow, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfiture. This, &amp; a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times more than this, is his bleſſed eſtate, that feeles in his ſoule, the <hi>Ioy of the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> The Lord, <hi>The Searcher of Hearts,</hi> knowes, that I vſe no <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perbole,</hi> or ouer-commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation: no, I ſpeake no more, then the <hi>Children of</hi> GOD finde daily in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, by ſweet experience.</p>
               <p>Now for the <hi>Delights</hi> of <hi>Vnregenerate</hi> men, oh how <hi>Baſe</hi> they be, and how <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded.</hi> And firſt for the
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:14830:53"/> 
                  <hi>Vileneſſe</hi> of <hi>Sinfull Pleaſure,</hi> it will the better bee diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered, if we ſhall vnmaske, and vn-muffle her painted face, &amp; ſophiſticated beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. And, to begin with him, who loues not to come behinde (I meane the <hi>Lofty,</hi> and <hi>Elated Spirit,</hi> that ſpends himſelfe, and his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate on vanity) what can be conceiued more ſordid, and diſhonourable, than to thinke to purchaſe the title of <hi>Generoſitie,</hi> by ſwearing deepe oathes (on no occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion) in the preſence of the liuing GOD, as if <hi>Hee</hi> were an <hi>Idoll</hi> of <hi>Wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d,</hi> or <hi>Stone,</hi> on whoſe ſhoulder the <hi>Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>birds</hi> ſit, and proyne them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and ſometimes
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:14830:53"/> pecke him in the face? And what more in-glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and degenerate, than like a ſilken <hi>Pompeian,</hi> to diſcourſe of warres, and ſwords, and helmets, and that with a ſhrug, and pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king out of the necke, and other ſuch eluiſh geſticula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as who would ſay, his fingers itcht till he came to hand-blowes; when all the world knowes him to bee ſoft, and feminine, much fitter to ſpin amongſt La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies with the laſt <hi>Aſſyrian Monarke,</hi> than to dare to meete <hi>Caeſar,</hi> (the <hi>Man of Men</hi>) in the field of <hi>Pharſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia?</hi> Yet do but intimate, in friendly manner, that this kinde of life is <hi>Sybaritiſh,</hi>
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:14830:54"/> abiect, and vnbeſeeming a <hi>Chriſtian;</hi> he will forthwith caſt vp his hayre back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and giuing it a ſhake, will ſternely tell you, that you are a fellow, a degree below <hi>Baſeneſſe</hi> it ſelfe. <hi>Quae quidem mihi, vox pecudis cſse videtur, non Hominis.</hi> I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, I am loth to bedabble my pen with <hi>Rhumes,</hi> and <hi>Diſtillations,</hi> much more, to taint it with the noyſome ſteames of <hi>Luxuriouſneſſe;</hi> yet leſt I become an acceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie to Intemperancie, and partake in the plagues of <hi>Vinking Prophets,</hi> I cannot but proſecute this ſubiect further. Is it not abſurd, that a man ſhould ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foole himſelfe, as to thinke
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:14830:54"/> to wring from others, an acknowledgement of his greatneſſe, by making a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainefull mouth, and caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out <hi>Smoke,</hi> which yet is but the commendation of a <hi>Chimney?</hi> And is it not more then ridiculous, that hee ſuppoſes you note not his <hi>magnanimouſneſſe,</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe he drinke till he tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in the floore? Doth not this rude, and brutiſh de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanour, rather become a <hi>Boore</hi> of <hi>Germanie,</hi> then a <hi>Gentleman</hi> of <hi>England?</hi> And what more groſſe, and ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominious, then to bow the knee to <hi>Bacchus,</hi> with a <hi>Paganiſh</hi> deuotion, and to be alwaies offring large ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice to the <hi>God Bel,</hi> nay to
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:14830:55"/> the <hi>God</hi> 
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Whoſe God is their <hi>Belly In Serm.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Bellie</hi> (I had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt<note place="margin">Phil. 3. 19.</note> ſaid) to the <hi>Goddeſſe Cloacina? O Augustine,</hi> thou ſaidſt true; <hi>Eſt blandus Doe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Ebrietas, dulce venenum, ſua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e peccatum, quam qui in ſe habet, ſe non habet; quam qui facit, non facit peccatum, ſed ipſe totus eſt peccatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: This ſame Drunkenneſſe is a flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Diuel, a ſweet Poiſon, a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful Sin, which whoſo hath in himſelfe, hath not himſelfe, and he that vſes it, is not ſinful in the Concrete, but ſinfulneſſe it ſelfe in the Abſtract.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Were the <hi>Prophet Amos</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Amos 4. 1.</note> aliue, though he were a <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate</hi> of <hi>Samaria</hi> that were thus licentious, hee would call him <hi>Kow</hi> of <hi>Baſhan,</hi> as one that at once, had put of
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:14830:55"/> both his <hi>Nature</hi> and his <hi>Sexe.</hi> I know that <hi>Lyra</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds thoſe <hi>Kine</hi> of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhan</hi> of the <hi>Popiſh Ladies</hi> of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that ranne gadding to their <hi>Calues</hi> at <hi>Dan,</hi> and <hi>Bethel,</hi> and there kiſt them, and lickt them, and at their parting fild the ayre with <hi>Lowing,</hi> like the <hi>Kine</hi> that went with the <hi>Cart</hi> to <hi>Beth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhemeſh;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Sam. 6. 12.</note> but I rather follow S. <hi>Ierome,</hi> and others, who meane it of the <hi>Gallants</hi> of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now as the pleaſure of the ſenſuall man is baſe, and courſe-grained; ſo is it euer mingled with ſome vnpleaſant ſenſe of euill, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that of <hi>Salomon, Euen in the midſt of laughter</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 14. 13.</note>
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:14830:56"/> 
                  <hi>the heart is ſorrowfull.</hi> Thus <hi>Haman</hi> (the <hi>Agagite</hi>) ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing<note place="margin">Eſter 5. 13.</note> the glory of riches, children, promotion, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of the <hi>Prince;</hi> eſtee<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>meth them nothing, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>Mordecai</hi> the <hi>Iewe</hi> would not riſe vp in the gate, and doe him obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXVI.</hi> That the Comfort of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is Immutable, and Durable.</head>
               <p>SVch is the <hi>Inſtabilitie</hi> of human affayres, and the calamitie whereto all men are ſubiect, that as the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Ieremie</hi> complaineth,<note place="margin">Lam. 3. 5.</note> they that did feed delicate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:14830:56"/> are deſolate in the ſtreets, and they that were brought vp in Scarlet, imbrace the dunghill. <hi>Sampſon</hi> that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible <hi>Nazarite,</hi> and <hi>Type</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that ſlew a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand <hi>Philiſtines</hi> with a <hi>Iaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bone,</hi> bare away the <hi>Gates</hi> of <hi>Azzah</hi> on his backe, and<note place="margin">Iudges 16. 21. <hi>Pet. Mart.</hi>
                  </note> brake cords as thrids, when they feele the fire, had his eyes digd out of his head with a <hi>Bodkin,</hi> ſo that teares o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bloud ranne trickling downe his cheekes. <hi>Zede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah,</hi> King of <hi>Iudah,</hi> in the<note place="margin">2. King. 25.</note> very prime and ſtrength of his daies, had his <hi>Sonnes</hi> ſlaine before his face; after which woefull ſpectacle, his owne eyes were put out, and hee bound in
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:14830:57"/> chaines, and carried cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue to <hi>Babel.</hi> Proud <hi>Nabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadnezzar,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dan. 4. 27, 28, 30.</note> that walking in his Royall Palace, ſpake thus in a brauerie, <hi>Is not this Great Babel, that I haue built for the houſe of the Kingdome, by the might of my power, and for the honour of my Maieſty?</hi> Euen while the word was in his mouth, was told by a voice that came downe from Heauen, <hi>O King,</hi> Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buchad-nezzar, <hi>to thee bee it ſpoken, thy Kingdome is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from thee.</hi> The very ſame houre was this thing fulfilled vpon him, and he was driuen from men, and did eate graſſe as the <hi>Oxen,</hi> and his body was wet with the dew of heauen, till his
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:14830:57"/> haires were growne as <hi>Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gles</hi> feathers, and his nayles like <hi>Birds</hi> clawes.</p>
               <p>Renowned <hi>Xerxes,</hi> that<note place="margin">Iuſtin. l. 2.</note> ouer-ſpred the <hi>Seas</hi> with <hi>Ships,</hi> and paſſed ouer into <hi>Greece</hi> with ſuch an huge <hi>Armie</hi> as emptied the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, and made the Earth to tremble before him, was inforced to come ſtealing backe in a poore <hi>Fiſhers</hi> boate, without ſo much as a <hi>Page</hi> to attend him. <hi>Vale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian,</hi> an aged, wiſe, and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant <hi>Emperour</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> was made the <hi>Foote-ſtoole</hi> of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>por,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Carion. l. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Perſia,</hi> and after all kinde of diſgrace, and vaſſallage, was flay'd quick fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the head vnto the feete.</p>
               <p>What ſhould I ſpeake of
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:14830:58"/> 
                  <hi>Baiazet</hi> the <hi>Turke,</hi> (the<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Munſter</hi> in his <hi>Coſmog.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Scourge</hi> of <hi>Greece,</hi> and <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour</hi> of <hi>Chriſtendome,</hi>) was he not led about by <hi>Tamer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lane,</hi> the <hi>Tartar,</hi> in an <hi>Iron-Cage,</hi> as a <hi>Monſter</hi> to bee gazed on, and died hee not of the ſullen, like a <hi>Vermin</hi> in a <hi>Trap?</hi> Was not the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorious <hi>Emperour, Henry</hi> the <hi>Fourth,</hi> who had fought<note place="margin">Oſiand.</note> 52. pitcht fields, (at leaſt) compelled to make ſuite in his old age, for a poore <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bend,</hi> in the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Spyra?</hi> And was not <hi>Belliſarius,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Carion.</note> (ſometime the onely man for proweſſe and honour) driuen to that hard exigent, that hauing his eyes put out, &amp; being led in a ſtring to beg by the highway ſide,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:14830:58"/> he cried out to the <hi>Paſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, Date obolum Belliſario, For Gods ſake beſtowe one Halfe-penny on</hi> Belliſarius?</p>
               <p>Thus the beautie of all Earthly excellencie, is but as a fading flower, and as<note place="margin">Iſaiah 28. 4.</note> the haſtie fruit before the Summer; but the <hi>Comfo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ts of Grace</hi> know no end, no ſtint. Temptations may obſcure their verdour, but cannot hurt the inward ſubſtance; ſome Leaues may fall, and ſome fruit may fade, but the ſeed, and roote ſhall ſtill remaine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyre.<note place="margin">De Ciuit. Dei l. 1. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>Nec prodi poſsunt, nec perdi,</hi> ſaith, S. <hi>Auſtine, They can neither bee betrayd, nor loſt:</hi> but when friends, and health, and life forſake vs,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:14830:59"/> they will ſticke vnto the <hi>Soule,</hi> and accompany her to <hi>Heauen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXVII.</hi> That Peace of Conſcience is the beſt Muſicke.</head>
               <p>SO great is the force, and operation of <hi>Muſicke,</hi> (which handleth meaſures as they are in ſounds) that it doth not onely moue the ſenſe, by the ſweetneſſe of the tune, and delight the reaſon by a skilfull compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of numbers, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portions; but alſo allay the turbulencie of paſsion, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to vertue, and make the <hi>Rockes,</hi> and <hi>Solit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>des</hi> to anſwere it. The <hi>Author</hi> of
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:14830:59"/> this <hi>Science,</hi> is GOD him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, who ſtirred vp <hi>Iubal</hi> to<note place="margin">Gen. 4. 21.</note> inuent it, and afterward o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Proficients</hi> to perfit it, and that for the ſolace of man, who being of all viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble creatures the onely ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, was therefore deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uedly the onely miſerable.</p>
               <p>By the ſweet warble of<note place="margin">God vſed his Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick as a meanes. 1. Sam. 16. 23. 2. Kin. 3. 15</note> his <hi>Harpe</hi> (whereto, no doubt, he ſang ſacred Dit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties) did <hi>Dauid</hi> put to flight the <hi>Euil Spirit</hi> of <hi>Saul. Elize<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> when he was to <hi>Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie</hi> before the Kings of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah,</hi> and <hi>Samaria,</hi> cals for a <hi>Muſician.</hi> The <hi>Lydian</hi> and<note place="margin">Bodin. De Repl. l. 4. c. 2</note> 
                  <hi>Ionique Muſicke,</hi> haue diſar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med wild, and ſauage Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of their teeth, and clawes, &amp; made them quiet
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:14830:60"/> and tractable. The <hi>Dorian</hi> harmonie, hath been held ſo graue, and pleaſant, that in the <hi>Primitiue Church,</hi> the <hi>Pſalmes,</hi> and <hi>Hymnes</hi> were ſung only in that tune. We ſhall finde in <hi>Iob,</hi> that the<note place="margin">Iob 39. 28.</note> ſterne ſound of the <hi>Trumpet</hi> (which is a <hi>kinde</hi> of <hi>Phrygi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Muſicke</hi>) doth cauſe the <hi>Horſe</hi> to cry, <hi>Ha, Ha,</hi> in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the battell.</p>
               <p>Thus the ſeuerall ſorts of true <hi>Muſick,</hi> haue wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily their due praiſe, both from their <hi>Author,</hi> and <hi>Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects.</hi> But yet there is one <hi>Harmony</hi> remaining, (which is very <hi>Still,</hi> and vnper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued of the <hi>Eare</hi>) where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the <hi>Soule</hi> is rapt, and captiuated, and which for
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:14830:60"/> ſweetneſſe ſurmounts them all. It is <hi>Peace</hi> of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> that is, <hi>Peace</hi> with GOD, <hi>Peace with Ones ſelfe, Peace with Angels, Peace with all Creatures.</hi> It was this <hi>Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick,</hi> (though ſomewhat im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect) that brought to Land the <hi>Prophet Ionah,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ionah 2. 4. 6. 7. 10.</note> that <hi>Chriſtian Arion</hi> (as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naeus</hi> cals him) and that not on the backe of a <hi>Dolphin,</hi> but in the belly of a <hi>Whale.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXVIII.</hi> That Peace of Conſcience is the beſt Phyſick.</head>
               <p>DIſeaſes (ſaith <hi>Origen</hi>)<note place="margin">Super Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit. Hom. 8.</note> are either cured by the <hi>Iuice</hi> of <hi>Hearbs,</hi> or <hi>Liquors</hi> of <hi>Trees,</hi> or <hi>Veines</hi> of <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals,</hi>
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:14830:61"/> or by the <hi>Bodies</hi> of <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing Creatures:</hi> all which doe either euacuate ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluities, or reſtore the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret decaies of Nature. But yet no <hi>drugge,</hi> nor precious <hi>Confection,</hi> may once com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare with <hi>Peace of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> it being one of <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons Aphoriſmes,</hi> that <hi>A ſound Heart is the life of the</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 14. 30.</note> 
                  <hi>fleſh.</hi> Doth not <hi>Experience</hi> declare, that this <hi>Inward Ioy</hi> inlargeth the heart, diffu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the ſpirits, cheereth the countenance, openeth the pores, cleanſeth the bloud, fatteth the bones, ſtrengthneth the ſynowes, maintaineth the natiue heate, and moyſture, and ſpinnes out the thrid of
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:14830:61"/> Mans life at length?</p>
               <p>How many, (alas) to the end they may purchaſe health, and hearts-eaſe, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult with the <hi>Phyſician,</hi> ſhake off the yoke of <hi>callings,</hi> and <hi>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion,</hi> are haunted with <hi>Rymesters, Ieſters, Panto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mimes,</hi> lay the reines on the necke, and giue their ſoules the vtmoſt of their deſire, and yet are pale, and leane, and ill-liking, neuer laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but faintly; neuer ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, but angerly; fretting themſelues away, and haſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to the graue, becauſe they want the <hi>Cordiall</hi> of a <hi>Good Conſcience?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="chapter">
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:14830:62"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXIX.</hi> That Peace of Conſcience is an Inestimable <hi>IEWELL.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE moſt precious <hi>Gemmes</hi> of mightie <hi>Monarches,</hi> which with their luſtre dazell the eyes of their admirers, are no whit ſo glorious as <hi>Peace</hi> of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> the <hi>End,</hi> and <hi>Crowne</hi> of all GODS <hi>Graces.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rollock in Theſſ.</note> For, if wee looke into their matter, it is but an earthie and watrie vapour: and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a certain date of yeeres, they grow ſick, and weake in operation, like a dead<note place="margin">Zanch. De Terr. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teor.</note> 
                  <hi>Pepper-corne,</hi> which hath loſt the heate, and byteth not the <hi>Tongue.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:14830:62"/>
               <p>But this <hi>Iewell</hi> wee ſpeake of, is of a moſt noble, and Diuine nature, not ſubiect to decay, but capable of <hi>Eternitie.</hi> This is the true <hi>Diamond,</hi> that flings beams of comfort vpon the <hi>Soule,</hi> enliuing and quickning it, to the cheerefull perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of all <hi>Religious Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</hi> This is the true <hi>Rubie,</hi> that carries in her face the <hi>Colour of Vertue;</hi> a ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all<note place="margin">Ruhor Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutis Color. <hi>2. Ioh. 1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Ornament</hi> for an <hi>Elect</hi> LADIE. This is the true <hi>Smaragd,</hi> ſo faire, and beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous to looke vpon, yet withall ſo <hi>Chaſte,</hi> that it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dures not the heat of <hi>Luſt,</hi> but will <hi>Cracke</hi> at ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignitie. This is the true <hi>Ia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>per,</hi> of colour greene, and
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:14830:63"/> ſprinkled with many drops of bloud, euen of the bloud of the vnſpotted <hi>Lamb.</hi> This is the true <hi>Sardius,</hi> which draweth <hi>Wood</hi> vnto it, (as the <hi>Adamant</hi> doth <hi>Yron</hi>) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing able to worke vpon the dulleſt nature. This is the true <hi>Chryſolite,</hi> of <hi>Golden</hi> hue, but cold in nature, allaying the heate of the <hi>Soules</hi> tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting <hi>Feuer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Oh that our haughtie <hi>Daughters</hi> of <hi>Sion,</hi> would adorne themſelues with this ineſtimable IEWELL, and not ſuffer the <hi>Soule</hi> to lye neglected, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorne, while the <hi>Bodie</hi> is cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly pranckt, and trickt vp! <hi>Dominam ancillari, &amp;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Medit. c. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>ancillam dominari, magna a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>buſio
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:14830:63"/> eſt,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Bernard;</hi> It's a foule in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 line">
                     <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 line">
                     <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 line">
                     <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of Saint <hi>Cyprian</hi> who is very earneſt<note place="margin">De Diſcip. &amp; Hab. Virg.</note> and copious in the reproofe of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXX.</hi> That a Good Conſcience com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forteth in Infamie.</head>
               <p>THE ſpeech of <hi>Iob,</hi> is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie<note place="margin">Iob. 31. 35 36.</note> memorable: <hi>Though mine Aduerſary ſhould write a Booke againſt mee, would I not take it vpon my Shoulder, and bind it as a CROWNE vnto mee?</hi> His meaning is, that in the vprightneſſe of
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:14830:64"/> his <hi>Conſcience,</hi> hee would make himſelfe <hi>Garlands</hi> of the reports of <hi>Sycophants. Fideliter in conſpectu Dei di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cont. Lit. Petil. li. 3. c. 2 &amp; 6.</note> (ſayth Saint <hi>Auguſtine) nihil eorum quibus</hi> Petilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus <hi>tempus vitae me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, poſtea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam in Chriſto baptizatus ſum, criminatus eſt, mihi con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcius ſum; id<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> non ſolum contriſtari non debere, verum etiam gaudere, &amp; exultare: I ſpeake it ſolemnely in the ſight of God, that I am not guiltie of any of thoſe actions, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with</hi> Petilian <hi>chargeth mee, ſince the time I was baptized in the name of Chriſt, and therefore haue I no cauſe to bee ſad, but rather to reioyce, and exult.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What though <hi>Tertullus</hi>
                  <pb n="107" facs="tcp:14830:64"/> (very eloquently) doe call Saint <hi>Paul</hi> a <hi>Peſtilent Fellow,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 24. 5. 6.</note> and charge him with <hi>Sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Hereſie, Sacriledge,</hi> ſo long as hee is able to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere him point, by point, and to cleere himſelfe of<note place="margin">Caluin. in Epiſt.</note> the calumnies? <hi>O bona Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientia, quantum polles, ac va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les! O innocent Conſcience, of how great force, and effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacie art thou!</hi> For if the Lord ſpeake peace vnto my Soule, the Tongue that's as hot as coles of <hi>Iuniper,</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not<note place="margin">Pſal. 120 4.</note> hurt mee; but if I bee guiltie, and conuiected in my ſelfe, what auailes an v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſal acclamation of my goodneſſe, but to my fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther plague, for my pallia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted hypocriſie?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="chapter">
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:14830:65"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXI.</hi> That a Good Conſcience com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forteth in Pouertie.</head>
               <p>THE <hi>Moraliſt</hi> did well<note place="margin">Eth. 3. 6.</note> to place <hi>Pouertie</hi> in the ranke of things <hi>Terrible;</hi> for, beſides the nips, and pinches it giues, which ſhrinke vp the heart, like a piece of <hi>Northerne Cloth;</hi> not <hi>Vertue</hi> herſelfe, but ſhal paſſe vnſaluted, if She goe in ill clothes. Howbeit the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> hauing the <hi>Legacy of Peace</hi> bequeathed him by<note place="margin">Ioh. 14. 27.</note> his <hi>Sauiour</hi> (in whoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon<note place="margin">2. Cor. 8. 9.</note> alſo <hi>Pouertie</hi> is ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied) contenteth himſelfe with the sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing of Saint <hi>Ie</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ad Heliod.</note> 
                  <hi>rome; Affatim Diues eſt, qui
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:14830:65"/> cum Chriſto Pauper eſt: Hee is abundantly Rich, that is Poore with Chriſt.</hi> Thus <hi>Iacob</hi> can ſleepe on a Pillow<note place="margin">Gen. 28. 11 Dan. 1. 15.</note> of Stone: <hi>Daniel</hi> is content with <hi>Pulſe,</hi> and <hi>Water;</hi> and the <hi>Diſciples</hi> are glad of<note place="margin">Mat. 12. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Eares</hi> of <hi>Corne</hi> on the <hi>Beſt</hi> Day of the <hi>Seuen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXII.</hi> That a Good Conſcience com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>forteth in Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</head>
               <p>WHen <hi>Len<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ulus</hi> (the<note place="margin">Saluſt. Con. Cat.</note> 
                  <hi>Conſpiratour</hi>) was carryed to Priſon, and put in the <hi>Dungeon</hi> calld <hi>Tullia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num</hi> (a roome ouer-head v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lted with a ſtone-arch, and exceeding darke, and
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:14830:66"/> vnſauourie) oh, with what horror was hee ſurprized, hauing no friend to flye to but his <hi>Conſcience,</hi> which (like his <hi>Executioner</hi>) was readie to ſtrangle him! But when <hi>Paul,</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> are ſore beaten with Rods, are caſt into the <hi>Inner Priſon,</hi> &amp; ſet faſt in the <hi>Stockes,</hi> they cheerefully <hi>ſing</hi> at <hi>Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night; Tantum intereſt, non</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aug. De Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit, Dei. lib. 1. cap. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>Qualia, ſed Qualis quiſque pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiatur: Such difference is there, not betweene the Sufferings, but the Sufferers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe holy men had <hi>Peace of Conſcience,</hi> which (as Saint <hi>Auſtine</hi> deſcribes it) is, <hi>The Garden of Eden: A Golden Bed of Reſt:</hi> and the <hi>Mercie-ſeate of the Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ru bins.</hi>
                  <pb n="111" facs="tcp:14830:66"/> For they were thus ſhamefully intreated for <hi>Chriſts</hi> ſake, whoſe ſacred<note place="margin">Mat. 27. 2.</note> hands had beene bound with cords for the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chace of their libertie. <hi>O</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bern. De Paſſion. Dom. c. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Rex Regum, &amp; Domine Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minantium, quid tibi, &amp; Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culis! O King of Kings, and Lord of Lords, alas, what haue Bonds to doe with thee!</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXIII.</hi> That a Good Conſcience com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forteth in Sickneſſe.</head>
               <p>THE comfort that <hi>Aha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ziah</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. King. 1. 2.</note> hath, when hee is caſt vpon his bed of ſicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, is <hi>Baal-zebub,</hi> the <hi>God of Ekron.</hi> When <hi>Aſa</hi> is<note place="margin">2. Chron. 16. 12.</note> troubled with the Gowt,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:14830:67"/> his only hope is the <hi>Ph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n.</hi> But when <hi>Hezeki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h</hi> is<note place="margin">Iſai. 38. 3.</note> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eere vnto death, hee hath recourſe to <hi>Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ence,</hi> for ſuccour: <hi>I beſecch thee, Lord, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>emember now, how I haue walked before thee in truth, and with a perfect heart, and haue done that which is Good</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bonum. Conſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uum. Congregal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uum. Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catiuum.</note> 
                  <hi>in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſight:</hi> Hee meanes it of all kinds of <hi>Goodneſſe,</hi> whether it be <hi>Preſeruing,</hi> or <hi>Vniting,</hi> or <hi>Communicating:</hi> which yet he ſpeakes not in a vaine confidence of <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> but in a cheerefull teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of his <hi>Faith.</hi> Not vnlike to this, is the beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour of GODS Children; in their languiſhments: for thus they reſolue from the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> PAVL; <hi>Whether</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 14. 8</note>
                  <pb n="113" facs="tcp:14830:67"/> 
                  <hi>wee liue, wee liue vnto the Lord: or, whether we die, we die vnto the Lord: whether we liue therefore, or die, wee are the Lords.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXIIII.</hi> That a good Conſcience com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forteth at the time of Death.</head>
               <p>THere are <hi>foure</hi> things that make <hi>Death</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midable; The <hi>Parting with the World<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> the <hi>bitter Pangs of it:</hi> the <hi>Horror of the Graue:</hi> &amp; the <hi>Conſideration of Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment following.</hi> Againſt all theſe doth <hi>Good Conſcience</hi> arme the <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> and inable him to incounter them, either ioyntly, or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidedly.
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:14830:68"/> And firſt, for <hi>Parting with the World,</hi> he hath his witneſſe within himſelfe, that ſince the time of his effectuall cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, hee neuer ſet his heart vpon it; ſo the abſence can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bee very grieuous, where the poſſeſſion was but faintly taken. As for the <hi>Pangs</hi> that clap to the heart in <hi>Death,</hi> I confeſſe (with Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) that<note place="margin">Tam mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſta eſt Mors, vt nulla expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cari locu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione poſſit. De Ciuit. l. 13. c. 11.</note> they are ſo ſharpe, as that no tongue is able to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe them: but yet this is his comfort, that hath a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate Conſcience,</hi> that the <hi>Lord</hi> in mercie will either mitigate the paine, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion the patience, or els cauſe him to triumph in <hi>S.
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:14830:68"/> Hieromes</hi> words, (which he<note place="margin">Ad Helio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor.</note> borrowed from the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Hoſea) O mors, quae fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hoſ. 13. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>diuidis, &amp; amore ſociatos, crudelis, ac dura diſſocias, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoraſti, &amp; Deuorata es! O Death, that art wont to part owne-brothers, and (inexora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble as thou art) doeſt ſeparate thoſe friends whom affection hath made one, thou haſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured, but art now deuoured thy ſelfe!</hi> Now for the <hi>Graue,</hi> it is true, that (as <hi>Iob</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes<note place="margin">Iob. 10. 22.</note> it) it is a <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd</hi> of <hi>Darkeneſſe,</hi> and <hi>Confuſion,</hi> but yet <hi>Good Conſcience</hi> (that ſuckes comfort out of <hi>Gall,</hi> and <hi>Worme-wood</hi>) i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not in this caſe deſtitute For, can <hi>Darkeneſſe</hi> ſtrike terrour, when the bodie is
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:14830:69"/> aſleepe? Can <hi>ſtinch</hi> annoy,<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 4. 13.</note> when the ſences are bound vp? Can the <hi>Worme</hi> affright, which is my <hi>Mother,</hi> and<note place="margin">Iob. 17. 14.</note> my <hi>Siſter?</hi> Can <hi>Scalpes,</hi> and <hi>Shin bones</hi> terrifie, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maze me, ſith He that ſhal, one day, ſeuer the <hi>Sheepe</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 25. 32</note> from the <hi>Goats,</hi> doth now preſently diſtinguiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>Bone</hi> and <hi>Bone</hi> in the <hi>Charnel-houſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And hath not my <hi>Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn. 19. 40. 41.</note> taken poſſeſſion of the <hi>Graue,</hi> with his owne bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed bodie, which was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>balmed with ſweet <hi>odours;</hi> and made it of a rotten <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bine,</hi> a delightfull <hi>Bed of</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſai. 57. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Downe?</hi> And for the <hi>Day of Iudgement,</hi> ſhal I not lift vp my head to thinke of it,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:14830:69"/> ſince it is the day of my <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 21. 28 1. Cor. 15. 14. &amp;c.</note> Take away the comfort of the <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> and take away the <hi>Staffe</hi> of <hi>Chriſtianity;</hi> for then, my <hi>Faith</hi> is vaine, and my zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous indeuour of <hi>holineſſe</hi> is vaine, and the <hi>teares</hi> vaine that I haue ſhed for my ſins, and the <hi>prayers</hi> vaine that I haue made for their forgiueneſſe, and thoſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable <hi>ioyes</hi> are vaine, which ſo oft I haue wiſht, which ſo long I haue lon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ged for, and the <hi>Sacraments</hi> (the ſeales of my ſaluation) are vaine, and the <hi>Booke</hi> of <hi>Bookes</hi> (the <hi>Holy Bible</hi>) is vaine, and woe is mee that euer I was borne, for the Pagan is happier than I,
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:14830:70"/> and the Epicure is happier than I, and the foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>footed Beaſt that eateth hay, is happier than I.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXV.</hi> That a good Conſcience com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forteth at the Day of Iudgement.</head>
               <p>NOw, if the contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation of the day of <hi>Iudgement</hi> approching, doe bring with it ſuch a waight of conſolation: oh, what vnſpeakeable gladneſſe of heart will the true <hi>Profeſſor</hi> bee poſſeſſed of, when hee ſhall actually appeare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his <hi>Redeemer!</hi> O the ſweete muſicke of <hi>Come yee</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 23. 34.</note> 
                  <hi>Bleſſed!</hi> and, O the thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-clap
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:14830:70"/> of <hi>Goe yee Curſed.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">41. Ad Heliod. Veniet, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niet illa dies, &amp;c.</note>
               </p>
               <p>To this very purpoſe S. <hi>Ierome</hi> ſpeaketh notably: The day will come, yes, it will ſurely come, when this corruptible, and mortall, ſhall put on incorrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and immortalitie: and then, bleſſed bee that ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, whom the Lord finds waking. The <hi>Earth</hi> with her inhabitants, ſhall trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at the ſound of the <hi>Trumpet,</hi> but thou, good <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> ſhalt reioice. The <hi>World</hi> ſhall mourne, and roare, and knock the breſt: the hearts of mighty <hi>Kings</hi> ſhall be ſeene to beat, and throb through their ſides; the wanton <hi>Miſtreſſe</hi> ſhall bee brought forth with her
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:14830:71"/> 
                  <hi>Bratts,</hi> and the <hi>Iouial Yonker,</hi> with his <hi>Plume,</hi> and <hi>Buskin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like</hi> eloquence. Then foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh <hi>Plato,</hi> and his Schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, muſt anſwere for their <hi>Community,</hi> and profound <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> ſhall not haue one poore <hi>Argument</hi> to helpe himſelfe withall. But thou, (now forlorne, and deſpiſed) <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> ſhalt then exult, and trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phantly ſay, <hi>Loe,</hi> this my <hi>Iudge,</hi> is the <hi>Childe</hi> that cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed when he was ſwadled in the Manger: this is <hi>He,</hi> that (in contempt) was called the <hi>Carpenters Sonne;</hi> this is <hi>Hee,</hi> that in his infancie did flie from man, being <hi>God,</hi> into <hi>Egypt.</hi> This is <hi>Hee,</hi> that was clad in <hi>Purple,</hi> was
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:14830:71"/> wounded with the <hi>Crowne of Thornes,</hi> was held a <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurer,</hi> a <hi>Samaritan,</hi> and <hi>One</hi> poſſeſſed of a <hi>Deuill.</hi> O <hi>Iew,</hi> behold the hands which thou nailedſt! O <hi>Romane,</hi> looke vpon the ſide which thou diggedſt! come neere, and ſee whether it bee the ſelfe ſame bodie, or no, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ye gaue out, that his <hi>Diſciples</hi> had cloſely ſtolne him away by night. Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto S. <hi>Ierome.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXVI.</hi> A complaint that Good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience is ſo little ſet by.</head>
               <p>NOt-with-ſtanding all that hath been ſpoken
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:14830:72"/> concerning the incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <hi>Treaſure</hi> of a <hi>Good Conſcience,</hi> what man (alas) makes any account of it? The <hi>Ambitious</hi> is hot in the purſuit of <hi>Honour,</hi> but makes not <hi>Conſcience</hi> pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie to his intent; ſo neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting the one, hee falls ſhort of the other; for, <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria virtutem, quaſi vmbra ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitur</hi> (ſaith <hi>S. Ierome) &amp;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ad Euſtoch. Virg.</note> 
                  <hi>appetitores ſui deſerens, appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tit contemptores: It is the nature of Glory to follow ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue as her ſhadow, and to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake her followers, while ſhee follow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s her contemners.</hi> But would he conſult with the <hi>Booke</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and take in his<note place="margin">1 Sam. 2. 30.</note> way, <hi>Honorantes me Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>;</hi> hee ſhould finde, that
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:14830:72"/> 
                  <hi>Conſcience</hi> were the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendiary way to true <hi>glory;</hi> which the very <hi>Heathen</hi> ſhadowed (as is noted by S. <hi>Auſtine</hi>) when they built<note place="margin">Aug. De Ciu. l. 5. c. 12</note> the <hi>Temples</hi> of <hi>Vertue,</hi> and <hi>Honour,</hi> ſo cloſe together, that none could paſſe vnto the laſt, but through the <hi>former.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Great Ill</hi> man (ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing diſcharged <hi>Conſcience</hi> for comming vpon his ground) ſacrilegiouſly takes away the <hi>Tythes,</hi> and<note place="margin">Leu. 27. 30</note> 
                  <hi>Offrings,</hi> which <hi>Scripture</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoucheth to bee a part of the <hi>Lords Crowne,</hi> and anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent <hi>Demaynes:</hi> and beeing fleſhed with the reuenewes of the <hi>Church,</hi> runnes with open mouth vpon the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons,</hi>
                  <pb n="124" facs="tcp:14830:73"/> and deuoures whole <hi>Townes,</hi> and <hi>Countries</hi> be fore him; in hope, at length, to bee Lord of as much ground, as a <hi>Kyte</hi> can well flye ouer in a day. <hi>O Rauen!</hi> For hee builds his neſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, and dips his bill in poore mens bloud, vp to the eyes. Hee hath got the aduantage of the <hi>Hill,</hi> that his deadly <hi>Pile</hi> might ſtrike downe all before it; which being caſt counter-mont, or in a plaine leuill, could not be ſo dangerous. Which S. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> conſidering,<note place="margin">This ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi> is often ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timer.</hi>
                  </note> concludeth thus ſeuerely againſt the whole <hi>Ranke</hi> of them; <hi>Miror ſi aliquis Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorum potest ſaluari; I won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der if any of theſe Great men
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:14830:73"/> can be ſaued;</hi> where (yet) he doth not import an <hi>Impoſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie,</hi> but a <hi>Difficultie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Vſurer,</hi> and his <hi>Broker</hi> vnmercifully faſten their gryping talons vpon the boſome of the decayed <hi>Borrower:</hi> tell them of <hi>Good Conſcience,</hi> they terme you <hi>Pragmaticall,</hi> and with full mouth talke of their <hi>Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands,</hi> as if they were able to ſpit <hi>ſhillings</hi> in the face of any one that durſt op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe them.</p>
               <p>The ſubtle <hi>Lawyer</hi> that pleades in ill cauſes, ſels ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, takes fees with both hands, and like an ill <hi>Surge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> keepes the wound of his <hi>Client</hi> greene, eſteemes of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> as the <hi>Rich-man</hi>
                  <pb n="126" facs="tcp:14830:74"/> in S. <hi>Iames</hi> of his poore-ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parrel'd<note place="margin">Iam. 2. 3. Sit thou here <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> my Foote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoole.</note> 
                  <hi>Gueſt,</hi> that is, hee makes her his <hi>Foote-ſtooles Foote-ſtoole.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The deceitfull <hi>Trades<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> that keepes a <hi>weight,</hi> and a <hi>weight,</hi> becauſe hee hath an heart, and an heart, holds <hi>Conſcience</hi> an vtter e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie to his thrift; and be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cauſe he meaneth to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonably rich, he can well be content to be vnmeaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably ſinfull.</p>
               <p>The bold fac't <hi>Stage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>player,</hi> that trades in poyſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning all ſorts, and ages, with verſes reezd in the ſmoke of luſt, and blaſphemous <hi>Scripture-ieſts,</hi> broke in the very face of GOD, is worthily caſt out (as the
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:14830:74"/> Bane of <hi>Conſcience</hi>) to the vtmoſt welt of the skirt of the <hi>Suburbs.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXVII.</hi> That Gods deareſt Children are often troubled in Conſcience.</head>
               <p>IT is the manner of the vnreclaimed perſon, to bleſſe himſelfe in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit of his light-hearted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: and to wonder that the ſtaid, and mortified <hi>Chriſtian</hi> can bee ſo ſad, and ſo vnſociable. But (alas) hee muſt vnderſtand, that <hi>Sapiens miſer, plus miſer, quàm Ruſticus miſer; The wiſe man in his affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, is more paſsionate then the vnlearned; for hee knowes
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:14830:75"/> how to exaggerate the cauſes of his griefe, whereof the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cannot skil.</hi> And though no outward croſſe lye on him, yet is hee ſo ſenſible, and apprehenſiue of his ſinne, that the continuation of his <hi>Pilgrimage,</hi> is but a viciſsitude of <hi>Ioy</hi> &amp; <hi>Sorrow.</hi> He is euer ſighing out this <hi>Prayer</hi> with S. <hi>Bernard; Eri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe</hi>
                  <note place="margin">De Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior. Domo. 31.</note> 
                  <hi>me, Domine, ab Homine malo, ideſt, à Meipſo: Deliuer me, O Lord, from the Vngodly Man, that is, from mine own ſelfe.</hi> And caſting back his eyes on the ſeuerall paſſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges of his life, hee findes it to be <hi>Peccat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m,</hi> or <hi>Sterili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas;</hi> either <hi>Sinne,</hi> or <hi>Barren<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe;</hi> ſo his concluſion is this, after all debatements,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:14830:75"/> 
                  <hi>Nullum inuenio peccatum, à</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bern. de In<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Do. 33.</note> 
                  <hi>quo non ſim aliquo modo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinatus: I finde no ſin, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, in ſome ſort, I haue not beene defiled.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This, this was it, that made DAVID water his<note place="margin">Pſa. 6. 6.</note> couch with his teares; made him faſt, and go bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foote,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 15. 30.</note> and put ſack-cloth on his loynes, as if hee had beene at the brim of <hi>Deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payre,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 77. 7.</note> as in truth, hee was. And ſo was <hi>Iob,</hi> when the<note place="margin">Iob 6. 4.</note> Lord ſet him vp as a <hi>Butt</hi> to ſhoote at, and ſent poiſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Arrowes ſinging into his boſome. So that it is not a matter of diſlike to ſee a brother <hi>Afflicted in minde,</hi> but rather of reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing; foraſmuch as <hi>Trouble
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:14830:76"/> of Conſcience</hi> is a neceſſarie part of <hi>Repentance,</hi> without which there is no hope of <hi>Saluation.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXVIII.</hi> Of ſundry Comforts againſt exceſsiue griefe for Sinne; and first, of the Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Inſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>teneſſe of Gods Mercie.</head>
               <p>IT is a worthy obſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion<note place="margin">Super Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tica. Serm. 38.</note> of S. <hi>Bernard,</hi> that <hi>The Ignorance of God, bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth foorth Deſpaire.</hi> For when the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> is in his <hi>Agonie,</hi> his owne carnall reaſon will aſſault him on this manner: <hi>Quid facis? Et vitam iſtam vis perdere, &amp; futura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? What now? Wilt thou
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:14830:76"/> loſe this life<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; the other too? Nequaquam pro tot, &amp; tantis peccatis, nec ſite excories, ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficies ſatisfacere; Thou ſhalt neuer be able to ſatisfie for thy ſinnes (ſo many are they, and ſo enormous) no not if thou ſhou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> flay thy ſelfe.</hi> Which ſharpe temptation muſt be thus reſiſted: <hi>Graue eſt vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug. in</hi> Pſal. 51.</note> 
                  <hi>quod habeo, ſed ad Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potentem confugio: de meo tam Lethali vulnere deſperarem, niſi tantum Medicum reperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem: My wound</hi> (I confeſſe) <hi>is deepe and dangerous, but I flye for cure to one that is Omnipotent: I ſhould vtterly Deſpayre, but that I haue found ſo incomparable a Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician.</hi> For though my ſins<note place="margin">Pſal. 40. 12.</note> haue taken ſuch hold on
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:14830:77"/> me, that I am not able to looke vp, and that they be more in number then the hayres of my head, ſo that my heart faileth mee to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count them: yet are they not <hi>Infinite,</hi> as is <hi>Gods Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie.</hi> And therefore if <hi>Satan</hi> ſhall whiſper in mine eare, that my ſinnes are greater than can be forgiuen, I will anſwere him out of S. <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard, Mentiris, Latro, quia maior eſt Pietas Dei, quàm quaeuis iniquitas: Thou lieſt, thou theefe, for the goodneſſe of God is greater than my wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe either is, or can be.</hi> The <hi>Lord</hi> deſcribing him ſelfe, for the comfort of his choſen, repeateth his <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 34. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>eight,</hi> or <hi>nine</hi> times to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether:
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:14830:77"/> is <hi>Hee</hi> ſo <hi>Rich</hi> in<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Grace,</hi> and ſhall I bee ſo poore in <hi>Faith?</hi> Is it not his <hi>Mercie</hi> that is <hi>Communis Peccantium Portus? The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Harbour of all (Penitent) Sinners?</hi> For it is not the <hi>Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> nor his <hi>Power,</hi> nor <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> that keepes the broken heart from dying a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, but his <hi>Mercie:</hi> which al men find (by experience) to bee the ſweeteſt proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of his <hi>Nature.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> in a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine<note place="margin">De Euang. Sept. Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num.</note> 
                  <hi>Sermon,</hi> makes men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a <hi>Seuen-fold Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie,</hi> which (hee ſayth) each Childe of <hi>God</hi> may find in himſelfe.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Firſt,</hi> is a <hi>Preuenting</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">1.</note> 
                  <hi>Mercie,</hi> by which the <hi>Lord</hi>
                  <pb n="134" facs="tcp:14830:78"/> preſerues his <hi>Elect</hi> from fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling into groſſe euils; <hi>Fateor, &amp; fatebor,</hi> (ſayth hee) <hi>niſi quia Dominus adiuuit me paulò minùs cecidiſſet in omne peccatum anima mea: I doe, and will ingenuouſly confeſſe, that vnleſſe the Lord had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued me by grace, my Soule had gone neere to haue laſht into all ſinne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Second,</hi> is a <hi>Forbea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">2.</note> 
                  <hi>Mercie,</hi> whereby the <hi>Lord</hi> waiteth for the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion of a <hi>Sinner.</hi> In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard whereof the ſame <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour</hi> writeth thus: <hi>Ego pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cabam, &amp; tu diſsimulabas; non contin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bam a ſceleribus, &amp; tu à verberibus abstinehas: I ſinned, O Lord, and thou ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medſt not to regard it: I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:14830:78"/> not my ſelfe from wickedneſſe, but thou abſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedst from ſcourging mee for the ſame.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Third,</hi> is an <hi>Altering,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">3.</note> or <hi>Changing Mercie,</hi> which makes a man ſettled in the reſolution of holineſſe, where before hee was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane, and looſe in his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiour.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Fourth,</hi> is an <hi>Imbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">4.</note> 
                  <hi>Mercy,</hi> whereby GOD aſſureth the <hi>Conuert</hi> of his <hi>Fauour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Fifth,</hi> is a <hi>Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">5.</note> 
                  <hi>Mercie,</hi> which ſtrengthneth, and vphol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the <hi>Righteous</hi> in his goodneſſe.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Sixth,</hi> is a <hi>Mercie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">6.</note> that ſets him in the hope,
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:14830:79"/> and expectation of <hi>Glorie.</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">7.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Seuenth,</hi> is a <hi>Crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Mercie,</hi> where is <hi>Liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,</hi> and <hi>Seyſin,</hi> and full poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of the Kingdome of Heauen.</p>
               <p>Thus the <hi>Lord</hi> hath <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen Mercies,</hi> nay, <hi>Seuentie times Seuen Mercies,</hi> euen an innumerable <hi>multitude</hi> of compaſſions, for the poore diſtreſſed ſinner, that gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth vnder the burden of his tranſgreſſions. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if I <hi>Pray,</hi> this ſhall be<note place="margin">Luk. 18. 13.</note> my <hi>Petition, O</hi> GOD, <hi>be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull vnto me a Sinner;</hi> and if I giue <hi>thankes,</hi> this ſhall be<note place="margin">Pſal. 136.</note> the <hi>foot</hi> of my Song, <hi>For his mercie indureth for euer; for his mercie indureth for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="chapter">
               <pb n="137" facs="tcp:14830:79"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXIX.</hi> Of the Second Comfort in trouble of Conſcience, which is the Meditation of the bloud of Chriſt.</head>
               <p>NExt, when my <hi>Soule</hi> is heauie vnto <hi>Death,</hi> I muſt haue recourſe to the <hi>Bloud</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> whoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertie<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 1. 7.</note> is to <hi>cleanſe</hi> from <hi>Sin,</hi> and to make an <hi>atonement</hi> betweene GOD and <hi>Man.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Col. 1. 20.</note> And for my further in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of comfort, I muſt call to minde the ſeuerall <hi>Effuſions</hi> thereof, as they are recorded in <hi>Scripture.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>firſt</hi> bloud he ſhed,<note place="margin">Luk. 2. 21.</note> was at his <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> when hee was but <hi>Eight</hi>
                  <pb n="138" facs="tcp:14830:80"/> dayes old, which Saint <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi>
                  <note place="margin">De Paſſion. Do m. c. 36.</note> cals, <hi>Maturum Marty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium; A Timely Martyrdome.</hi> To which end hee further addeth; <hi>Vix natus eſt Coeli Gloria, Coeli Diuitiae, Coeli De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciae, dulcis</hi> IESVS, <hi>&amp; ecce<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>recenti ortui Crucis dolor co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulatur: Scarce was ſweete</hi> IESVS <hi>come into the World, who was the Glorie, the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, the Delight of Heauen, but he vnderwent the painful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Croſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Second</hi> effuſion of<note place="margin">Bern. De Paſſion. Dom.</note> bloud, was in his <hi>Agonie,</hi> wherof S. <hi>Bernard</hi> ſpeaketh thus; <hi>Ecce quàm Rubicun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus, &amp; quàm totus Rubicun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus: Behold, how Red, and how all-ouer Red He is:</hi> for Saint<note place="margin">Luk. 22. 44.</note> 
                  <hi>Luke</hi> affirmeth that his <hi>ſweat</hi>
                  <pb n="139" facs="tcp:14830:80"/> was like droppes of <hi>bloud</hi> trickling downe to the ground.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Third</hi> effuſion of<note place="margin">Iohn 19. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>bloud,</hi> was at his <hi>whipping; O cum quanta quantitate, pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas illum ſanctiſsimum ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinem, è conſciſſo corpore, &amp; flagellato, diſtillaſſe in terram! Oh, in what abundance, thinke yee, did that moſt Sacred bloud of his, powre downe from his torne, and ſcourged bodie, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vnto the ground!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Fourth</hi> effuſion of<note place="margin">Iohn 19. 2.</note> bloud, was when the <hi>Crown of Thornes</hi> was deſpightfully clapt vpon his head: <hi>Nec hic puto defuiſſe Riuos San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinis,</hi> ſayth Saint <hi>Bernard; Nor can I thinke, that at this time, there wanted Riuers of Bloud.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="140" facs="tcp:14830:81"/>
               <p>The <hi>Fifth</hi> effuſion of<note place="margin">Ioh. 19. 18.</note> 
                  <hi>Bloud,</hi> was vpon the <hi>Croſſe,</hi> where his hands, and feete, and ſide were pierced; <hi>Quis vnquam tam grauia, tam pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denda p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſus fuit? Who was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer thus cruelly, and thus ſhamefully handled? Conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dunt</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bern. De Paſſione.</note> 
                  <hi>Paſsio, &amp; Charitas; illa, vt plus ardeat: iſta, vt plus rubeat: His Paſsion, and Loue doe ſtri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e together: that, that it may bee hotter: this, that it may bee redder. O ſua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me vniuerſorum Domine, &amp; Saluator, Bone</hi> IESV, <hi>quales tibi condignas gratiarum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre potero actiones! O bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed</hi> IESV, <hi>the moſt graciou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Lord, and Sauiour of all thy Choſen, How can I render thee ſufficient thankes! for thy
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:14830:81"/> Garment is dipt in Bloud, and</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reuel. 19. 13. Iſai. 53. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>the chaſtiſement of my Peace hath beene vpon thee from the beginning of thy dayes, vnto thy death, yea and after thy Death.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XL.</hi> Of the Third Comfort in trouble of Conſcience, which is, the Conſideration of the Indefiniteneſſe of <hi>GODS</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes.</head>
               <p>WHEN <hi>Satan</hi> (that <hi>Murtherer</hi> from<note place="margin">Ioh. 8. 44.</note> the <hi>beginning</hi>) ſhall lay the <hi>Razor</hi> cloſe vnto my throate, and ſhall labour to threape mee downe, that though there were an <hi>Ocean</hi>
                  <pb n="142" facs="tcp:14830:82"/> of <hi>Chriſts Bloud,</hi> yet not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut drop belonged vnto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to then ſtands it me in han<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitch my thoughts vp<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> At the <hi>Vniuerſalitie</hi> of Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>-<hi>Promiſes,</hi> where-from Ic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s, not exempt my ſelfe, wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, out iniurie to GOD, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> preiudice to mine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Soule. For, ſith the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> proclaimes a <hi>Generall Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on</hi> in the <hi>Prophet, Ho, Eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie one that thirſteth, come ye</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſai. 55. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>to the Waters:</hi> and that our <hi>Sauiour</hi> inuiteth <hi>All</hi> that ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Wearie,</hi> and <hi>Heauie-laden;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 11. 28.</note> to come vnto him; why ſhould I be ſo curſedly vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gratefull, as to except my ſelfe, aboue all other, and wilfully refuſe the gracious offer of my ſaluation? Nay,
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:14830:82"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſhould I not rather <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> thus with S. PAVL;<note place="margin">1. Tim. 1. 15</note> 
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>riſt Ieſus came into the World, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>nners:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>erefore he came to ſaue ME, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> of Sinners.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XLI.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Fourth Comfort in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rouble of Conſcience, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>hich is the Conſideration <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> moſt grieuous Sinners, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> that haue beene pardoned vpon their Repentance.</head>
               <p>SVCH is the ſubtletie of the <hi>Spirituall Aduerſarie,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>at in the practicall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe before the commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of ſome crime, hee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanteth the Sinner with the ſpell of <hi>Mercie;</hi> but when he hath once intang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him in his Net, hee
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:14830:83"/> ſhewes him nothing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the ſanctions of the <hi>La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> bring him to vtter aba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment, and confuſion. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> which time I muſt reme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber thoſe mightie Sinn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> that haue beene forgiue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vpon their ſerious humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation. And thus I muſt reaſon. Am I worſe the DAVID, that went in, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <note place="margin">2. Sam. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>Bathſheba,</hi> and imbrued his handes in the bloud of <hi>V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riah?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Kings 21 2. Chron. 33.</note> Am I worſe then <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſes;</hi> Idolatrous, Murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, Notorious <hi>Manaſſes?</hi> Am I worſe then <hi>Peter,</hi> that<note place="margin">Mat. 26. 74</note> curſt, and band, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwore his Sauiour? Am I worſe then <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 8. 2.</note> that was poſſeſt of <hi>Seuen Deuils?</hi> Am I worſe then
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:14830:83"/> the <hi>Iewes,</hi> that ſcourg'd and<note place="margin">Acts 2. 36. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>7. 41.</note> ſpit vpon, and reuiled, and crucified the <hi>Lord</hi> of <hi>Life<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Since theſe haue obtained pardon vpon <hi>Repentance,</hi> what ſhould barre <hi>MEE</hi> from it, vpon the ſame con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition? O, but my <hi>Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe</hi> is like the <hi>morning dew;</hi> for my <hi>Conſcience</hi> tels mee, that I haue had many fearefull <hi>Relapſes.</hi> To this I anſwere from <hi>Chryſoſtome;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In Pſal. 51. Contra No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uat.</note> 
                  <hi>Peccaſti? Poenitere: Millies peccaſti? Millies Poenitere; Millies Poenitet? Adhuc e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam Poenitere: Haſt thou ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned? Repent; Haſt thou a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times ſinned? Why then, a thouſand times Repent. Haſt thou Repented a thouſand times, I ſay, Deſpayre not, but
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:14830:84"/> ſtill betake thy ſelfe to Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I dare affirme it, (and <hi>Scripture</hi> will beare me out)<note place="margin">Some of the Scribes and Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and others.</note> that thoſe damned Wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches that committed that vnpardonable ſinne againſt the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> might haue bin forgiuen, if they could but haue <hi>Repented.</hi> For we muſt not thinke, that that <hi>Hell-blacke</hi> ſinne is in it ſelfe <hi>irremiſsible:</hi> but for that it is his nature that fals into it, to abhorre all motions vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to grace and goodneſſe. Then, bleſſed GOD, create in mee a <hi>New</hi> heart, and giue mee the ſingular gift of <hi>Regeneration.</hi> I craue not <hi>Riches,</hi> nor <hi>Honour,</hi> nor <hi>Long life;</hi> but <hi>Repentance,
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:14830:84"/> Repentance,</hi> is the thing I ſue for. O, <hi>Lord,</hi> vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe it mee, for <hi>Ieſus</hi> ſake, vpon my bare knees I aske it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XLII.</hi> Of the Fifth Comfort in trouble of Conſcience, which is the Conſideration of Gods fatherly Chaſtiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments accompanying it.</head>
               <p>IN my importable preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, and afflictions, when, that I feared is come vpon mee: when I am be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reft of Wife, Children, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, Health, Libertie, Maintenance; this makes my Cup of Gall, and Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to runne ouer, that my
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:14830:85"/> 
                  <hi>Conſcience</hi> informes mee of my life, either openly led in prophaneſſe, or vailed ouer with an hypocriticall precizeneſſe: and beſides, <hi>Satan</hi> inſulteth in my miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and like <hi>Shemei</hi> rayles, and throwes ſtones at mee, as if I were the <hi>Monſter</hi> of the World. But as expert <hi>Phyſicians</hi> fetch from the <hi>Scorpion</hi> an helpe againſt her poyſon: ſo muſt I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract from the Matter of my woe, a <hi>Preſeruatiue</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it. And thus I muſt hearten vp my ſelfe: It is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſo, O, LORD, Whom<note place="margin">Heb. 12. 8.</note> thou loueſt, thou chaſtneſt, and ſcourgeſt euery Sonne that thou receiueſt. If I bee without correction (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:14830:85"/> al are partakers) then am I a <hi>Baſtard,</hi> and not a <hi>Sonne.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hieron. ad Caſtrut.</note> 
                  <hi>Quid inter Reges,</hi> Ioſia <hi>ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctius? Aegyptio mucrone in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terſectus eſt; Quid</hi> PAVLO <hi>ſublimius?</hi> Neronianum <hi>gladium cruentauit: What King was euer holier than</hi> Ic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah? <hi>Yet was hee ſlaine by the Sword of Aegypt; Who more heroical, than</hi> Paul? <hi>yet died he by the blade of</hi> NERO. <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na ira eſt, quando peccantibus non iraſcitur Deus:</hi> GOD <hi>is</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>thorowly angry with Sinners, when hee ſeemes not to be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry at all.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="43" type="chapter">
               <pb n="150" facs="tcp:14830:86"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XLIII.</hi> Of the ſixth Comfort in trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of Conſcience, which is Mourning for ſinne.</head>
               <p>IF, when my <hi>Conſcience</hi> is vpon the <hi>Racke,</hi> and that I call my ſaluation into doubt, I can lament my ſinnes and rebellions, with brackiſh teares, or ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes equiualent: I haue iuſt cauſe of conſolation. For <hi>firſt</hi> it is certaine, that <hi>Iudging</hi> my ſelfe, I ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11. 31.</note> be <hi>Iudged</hi> of the <hi>Lord. Againe,</hi> it is an <hi>Axiome</hi> in <hi>Scripture,</hi> that, <hi>They that ſow</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſa. 126. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>in teares, ſhall reape in ioy. Thirdly,</hi> I find, that the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieſt men were the greateſt
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:14830:86"/> 
                  <hi>weepers;</hi> as <hi>Dauid</hi> (for one)<note place="margin">Oculus ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uti à Tineis Corroſus eſt. Vatab. in Pſ. 6. 7.</note> whoſe eye was <hi>worm-eaten</hi> with <hi>blubbering.</hi> To the which conſenteth <hi>S. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine,</hi> when he ſaith, <hi>Quantò</hi>
                  <note place="margin">De Ciu. Dei l. 20. c. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>quiſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> eſt ſanctior, tant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> eſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ius fletus vberior: The ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier a man is, the more plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full is he in weeping. Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> the tears that flow from a contrite heart, are accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of <hi>God,</hi> as <hi>ſecret prayers:</hi> therefore ſaith <hi>S. Ambroſe, Lachrymae, tacitae quodammo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Serm. 46.</note> 
                  <hi>ſunt preces: Teares (in ſome ſort) are cloſe ſupplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Fiftly,</hi> the <hi>teares</hi> of a penſiue ſinner reioyce the bleſſed <hi>Saints</hi> of <hi>Heauen:</hi> to this end ſaith <hi>Bernard, La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chrymae</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Super Cant. Ser. 68.</note> 
                  <hi>Peccatorum, Deliciae Angelorum: The teares of
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:14830:87"/> S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nners, are the delights of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Sixtly</hi> the merry ſports of <hi>The<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ters,</hi> come very farre ſhort of the comfort that goes with <hi>teares,</hi> for ſo ſaith <hi>S. Auguſtine, Dulciores ſunt</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In Pſ. 128.</note> 
                  <hi>lach<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ymae o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>antiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, quàm gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ia Theatrorum: More ſweet are the t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ars of them that pray, than the pleaſures of Stage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playes. Seuenthly,</hi> it is a ſigne that he is reſpected of <hi>God,</hi> whoſe heart by grace is diſſolued into <hi>teares. Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis Peccator</hi> (ſaith <hi>S. Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi>)<note place="margin">De modo Benè viu. Ser. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>tunc ſe cognoſcit viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tari à Domino, quando com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pungitur adlachrymas: Then doth the ſinner perſwade him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe that hee is viſited</hi> (in mercie) <hi>of the Lord, when his griefe for ſinne ſhewes it ſelfe
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:14830:87"/> in teares. Eightly,</hi> if <hi>teares</hi> (as the ſame <hi>Author</hi> teſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth) bee miraculouſly tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into <hi>Wine,</hi> which iſſue foorth in the feruour of<note place="margin">In Epiphan. Dom. Ser. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Charitie</hi> to our <hi>neighbour;</hi> then much more thoſe, which the Sacred fire of <hi>Gods Spirit</hi> hath diſtilled from true <hi>remorſe</hi> for ſinne: whereof if we drinke til we ſcarce know where we are, it is but <hi>Sobria quaedam E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brietas; A certaine ſober kind of Dizzineſſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="44" type="chapter">
               <pb n="154" facs="tcp:14830:88"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XLIIII.</hi> Of the Seuenth Comfort in trouble of Conſcience, which is Prayer.</head>
               <p>AS our bleſſed <hi>Sauiour,</hi> in the dayes of his fleſh, did offer vp prayers, and ſupplications vnto his <hi>Father,</hi> with ſtrong crying,<note place="margin">Heb. 5. 7.</note> and teares, and was alſo heard in that which he fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: ſo is euery <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> in the terrour and conſterna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his minde, to inuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate <hi>Gods</hi> Name with all <hi>Faith,</hi> and <hi>Zealouſneſſe.</hi> For, ſince <hi>Prayer</hi> is of ſuch a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailing nature, that it pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth the heauens, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunes the <hi>Lord</hi> for ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour,
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:14830:88"/> not ſuffering him to reſt, vntill hee haue mercie on the <hi>Suppliant:</hi> how can<note place="margin">Iſa. 62. 7.</note> he want comfort, that is ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulous in the vſe of it? The <hi>Prophet Dauid</hi> was often wounded grieuouſly in <hi>Conſcience:</hi> and in all his <hi>Agonies,</hi> hee<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſtill hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to <hi>God</hi> by <hi>Prayer.</hi> And this is very obſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that his <hi>Petitions</hi> in that caſe, howſoeuer they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginne in <hi>griefe,</hi> yet they end<note place="margin">Pſal. 6. 1.</note> in <hi>ioy. O Lord, rebuke mee not in thine anger!</hi> an heauie entrance: yet thus he exul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in the cloze, <hi>Away from</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">8.</note> 
                  <hi>me<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> all ye workers of iniquity; for the Lord hath heard the voyce of my weeping.</hi> So, when he powreth out this
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:14830:89"/> complaint, <hi>My God, my God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſ. 22. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>why haſt thou forſaken mee?</hi> what can bee imagined more ſad, and rufull? yet in the concluſion, where hee<note place="margin">23, 44.</note> calls vpon the faithfull to congratulate <hi>Gods</hi> great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of him, doth not the gladneſſe more then coun teruaile the ſorrow? In like manner, when he crieth out as for life, and death, <hi>Sau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> me, O Lord, for the waters are</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſ. 69. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>entred euen to my ſoule;</hi> what beginning can bee more paſſionate? yet if wee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend to the latter part, it will not much differ from a <hi>Song</hi> of <hi>Triumph?</hi> It were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o hard matter to quote ſundrie other places to this purpoſe: but theſe may
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:14830:89"/> ſuffice, as a direction to the reſt.</p>
               <p>Now the ground of our<note place="margin">Pſ. 50. 15.</note> hope in the <hi>Inuocation</hi> of <hi>Gods</hi> name, is both a <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement,</hi> and a <hi>Promiſe: Call vpon mee in the day of trouble, and I will deliuer thee.</hi> O the vnſpeakable ſolace of <hi>Gods children,</hi> that are not onely inuited, but charged, to call vpon their heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Father,</hi> in all their neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities, with a moſt gracious aſſurance to bee heard, when they ſhall aske, nay, <hi>before</hi> they aske! O the<note place="margin">Iſa. 65. 24. Rom. 8. 15.</note> glorious priuiledge of <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall Ado<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tion,</hi> which is a lawfull <hi>Act,</hi> not imitating, but tranſcending nature; found out of <hi>God,</hi> not for
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:14830:90"/> the comfort of a <hi>Father</hi> that wanteth <hi>Children,</hi> but for the comfort of <hi>Children</hi> that want a <hi>Father.</hi> It is this that makes vs crie <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba, Father!</hi> It is this that makes vs ſay, <hi>Shibboleth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iudg. 12. 6.</note> not <hi>Sibboleth:</hi> it is this that makes vs renew our ſtrength, and lift vp our wings, as the <hi>Eagles.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 40. 31.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Say, ye that are the Sons of the liuing <hi>God,</hi> ye that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone can ſpeake the <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage</hi> of <hi>Canaan,</hi> if euer yee made an holy and feruent prayer, and felt not an hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly reioycing after it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And ſay, if ye finde it not true in experience, that much prayer, much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ort; little prayer, little
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:14830:90"/> comfort; no prayer, no comfort. O, it muſt needs<note place="margin">De Inter. Dom. 6. 48.</note> bee ſo. For, as <hi>S. Bernard</hi> well ſayth, <hi>Quando oramus, Spiritum ſanctum ad nos vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camus: As oft as we pray, wee call the Holy Ghoſt vnto vs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But here it muſt bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred, that in the anxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etie and perplexedneſſe of our ſoules, wee frame our petitions, (for their mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tents) according to the patterne of the <hi>Lords Prayer,</hi> concluding alſo (v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually) therewith our own ſupplications. For (as <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian</hi>
                  <note place="margin">De Orat. Dom.</note> noteth) <hi>Quantò effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ùs impetramus, quod peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus in Chriſti Nomine, ſi pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us ipſius Ora<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>? How much ſooner ſhall we obtaine
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:14830:91"/> what wee deſire in Chriſts Name, if withall we requeſt it in his owne words?</hi> For it is to bee beleeued, that no <hi>Saint,</hi> nor <hi>Angel</hi> is able to match that <hi>Platforme</hi> of <hi>Prayer;</hi> whether we regard the <hi>Authority</hi> of it, or the <hi>Breuitie,</hi> or the <hi>Perfection,</hi> or the <hi>Method,</hi> or the <hi>Effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacie,</hi> or the <hi>Neceſsity.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="45" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XLV.</hi> Of the Eighth Comfort in trouble of Conſcience, which is the Reading of Scripture.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>EXcept thy Law had beene</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 119. 92.</note> 
                  <hi>my deligh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> ſaith <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uid to the Lord) I ſhould haue periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ouble:</hi> (where by
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:14830:91"/> 
                  <hi>Law</hi> is meant, not the <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Caluin. Vatab. Molier. in <hi>Pſal. 19.</hi>
                  </note> onely, but the whole <hi>Couenant</hi> of <hi>God.) S. Paul</hi> calleth the <hi>Scripture</hi> (eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally the <hi>New Teſtament</hi>) the <hi>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rd</hi> of <hi>Life;</hi> becauſe as it is<note place="margin">Phil. 2. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>Verbu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Domini, the Word of the Lord;</hi> ſo it containeth nothing (in effect) but <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bum Dominu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, The Word, The Lord.</hi> Now where <hi>Chriſt</hi> is the <hi>Subiect-matter,</hi> there muſt needs bee cauſe of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilation.</hi> Certainely, as the <hi>Lord</hi> is the <hi>God of all Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Cor. 1. 3.</note> ſo the <hi>Bible</hi> is the <hi>Booke of all comfort;</hi> which if wee perceiue not, the fault is in our pallate, according to that of <hi>S. Auguſtine, Mel amarum Febrienti: Not hony</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>In</hi> Pſal. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>it ſelfe, but is bitter to the Aguiſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="162" facs="tcp:14830:92"/>
               <p>I confeſſe, the <hi>Bookes</hi> of <hi>Heathen Writers,</hi> doe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe comfort in calamitie, but (alas) they performe it not: but are like a <hi>Brooke</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iob 6. 17.</note> that ſwels in winter, when there is no neede of it, and is drie in Summer, when the <hi>Paſſenger</hi> fainteth, and panteth for heate. For be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ignorant both of <hi>Sinne,</hi> the wound, and of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>Remedie,</hi> the ſuccour they afford, muſt needs bee weariſh. No: if wee will haue good <hi>Gold,</hi> wee muſt go to <hi>Ophyr:</hi> if good <hi>Balme,</hi> to <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lead:</hi> if good <hi>Wine,</hi> to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> at the wedding of <hi>Cana:</hi> and, if good tidings, to the <hi>Booke of God.</hi> For, to make a voyage, when the
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:14830:92"/> minde is deadded, to <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile Authors</hi> for refection (eſpecially to their merrie <hi>Poets</hi>) is little better than<note place="margin">1. Kin. 10. 22.</note> trauelling to <hi>Tharſhiſh</hi> for <hi>Apes,</hi> and <hi>Peacocks.</hi> I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale to all the <hi>Seruants</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and chiefely to the old experienced <hi>Souldiers</hi> of <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt,</hi> if euer they were eaſ'd of the <hi>Sting,</hi> and <hi>tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour</hi> of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> by any writing vnder heauen, but the <hi>Bible;</hi> or by ſome <hi>Booke,</hi> that hath borrowed all the ſweetneſſe it hath thence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from. And more, let them ſay, if at any time they ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted to this <hi>Fountaine of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing waters</hi> (taking with them their <hi>Pitcher,</hi> that is, true <hi>Faith</hi>) and came not
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:14830:93"/> backe with wonderfull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhment.</p>
               <p>There is a rare, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> recorded by S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> of <hi>Himſelfe,</hi> in<note place="margin">Lib. 8. c. 12.</note> his <hi>Confeſsions.</hi> His words are theſe: Recalling to minde, and aggrauating my miſerie: there aroſe a great ſtorme, which brought foorth a pealing ſhowre of teares. Wherevpon I went aſide from my friend <hi>Alipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> that I might more freely giue my ſelfe to weeping. And laying me downe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a certaine <hi>Figge-tree,</hi> mine eyes guſht out with riuers of waters; and thus I bemoned my ſelfe to <hi>God; O Lord,</hi> how long? how long wilt thou bee angry
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:14830:93"/> with me? For euer? I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee, remember not my former wickednes. For I perceiu'd, that ſtill I was hopled in it, and therefore I tooke vp this miſerable complaint; <hi>Quam diu, Quam diu, Cras, &amp; Cras? Quare non modo? Quare non hac hora, finis turpitudinis meae?</hi> How long, how long ſhall I put off my <hi>Repentance,</hi> with <hi>To Morrow, To Morrow?</hi> Why turne I not <hi>Now, this preſent houre,</hi> from the filthineſſe of my life? At which words (deliuered with bitter mourning) mee thought I heard a voice thus ſinging from the next houſe: <hi>Tolle, Lege: Tolle, Lege: Take vp and Read; Take vp, and Read.</hi>
                  <pb n="166" facs="tcp:14830:94"/> Then changing my coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, and pondering the matter carefully, and adui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly, I returned to <hi>Alipius,</hi> where I had left my <hi>Booke</hi> of the <hi>Epiſtles</hi> of S. <hi>Paul;</hi> I ſnatcht it vp, and opened it, and read to my ſelfe this place, which firſt preſented it ſelfe to mine eyes: <hi>Not</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 13. 13. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>in Gluttonie, and Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, neither in chambering, and wantonneſſe, nor in ſtrife, and enuying. But put ye on the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and take no thought for the fleſh, to fulfill the luſts of it. Nec vltra volui Legere, nec opus erat:</hi> Nor would I reade any further, nor needed I: for ſo ſoone as I came to the end of this clauſe, my minde was ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:14830:94"/> &amp; al doubts diſlodged.</p>
               <p>If here it bee demanded what parts of <hi>Scripture</hi> are fitteſt to bee read for the ſtay of <hi>Conſcience:</hi> I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, that for the <hi>Old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament,</hi> the <hi>Prophet Iſaiah,</hi> in the iudgement of Saint <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> who counſelled<note place="margin">Aug. Confeſ. l. 9. c. 5.</note> S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> propounding the ſame queſtion, to bee conuerſant in <hi>him,</hi> aboue others: no doubt, becauſe he wrote ſo cleerely of the <hi>Meſsiah</hi> to come, as if hee had beene already incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate. But <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> and<note place="margin">Prolog. in lib. Pſal. Ad Ruſt. Mon.</note> 
                  <hi>Baſil, &amp; Auguſtine, &amp; Ierome,</hi> and <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> and almoſt al the <hi>New Writers,</hi> ſtand ſo deeply affected to the <hi>Book of Pſalmes,</hi> that they hold it
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:14830:95"/> the <hi>Store-houſe of all good learning,</hi> the <hi>Diuine M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtris</hi> both of <hi>Faith,</hi> and <hi>Vertue,</hi> and the perfect <hi>Anatomie of the Soule.</hi> And therefore their aduice is<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that as <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> the <hi>Great,</hi> was woont to put the works of <hi>Homer,</hi> in the moſt precious <hi>Casket</hi> of King <hi>Darius,</hi> which glit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered all-ouer with gold, and gemmes; ſo, that euery <hi>Chriſtian</hi> (eſpecially thoſe that are burdened in <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi>) would locke vp the <hi>Booke of Pſalmes</hi> in <hi>the Cabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net</hi> of their hearts, as a moſt incomparable <hi>Treaſure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now for the <hi>New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> (which is more glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous than the <hi>Old,</hi> as <hi>S. Paul</hi> proueth) I am of <hi>Zanchies</hi>
                  <note place="margin">De Natur. Dei. c. 3.</note>
                  <pb n="169" facs="tcp:14830:95"/> opinion, that thoſe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines are moſt excellent, which our <hi>Sauiour Chriſt</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered with his owne mouth; as his <hi>Sermon</hi> vpon<note place="margin">Mat. 5. Luke 4. Iohn 17.</note> the <hi>Mount,</hi> at <hi>Nazaret,</hi> at <hi>Capernaum,</hi> and thoſe hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly <hi>Prayers,</hi> which hee made a little before, and at his <hi>Death.</hi> Where it muſt be cautiouſly remembred, that though in the <hi>Sermons</hi> of our <hi>Sauiour,</hi> there be found ſome ſentences of terrour and deiection: yet (as <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Vpon the <hi>Galatians.</hi>
                  </note> noteth) they properly belong not to his office of <hi>Mediator-ſhip,</hi> and were on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bent againſt the viperous generation of the <hi>Phariſes,</hi> and others of that ſtraine.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="46" type="chapter">
               <pb n="170" facs="tcp:14830:96"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XLVI.</hi> Of the Ninth Comfort in trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of Conſcience, which is Singing of Pſalmes.</head>
               <p>THere are ſundry Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,<note place="margin" type="runSum">1.</note> why the <hi>Lord</hi> would haue the chiefe points of <hi>Religion</hi> included in <hi>Numbers,</hi> by the ſweet <hi>Singer</hi> of <hi>Iſrael. One</hi> is, that they might be tranſmitted pure, and without depraua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to poſteritie: for they runne ſo eeuenly, and ſo harmonically vpon feete, that if there want but a word, or ſyllable, the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour is deprehended.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> it is done for the<note place="margin" type="runSum">2.</note>
                  <pb n="171" facs="tcp:14830:96"/> helpe of memorie; for <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinnitie</hi> of <hi>Numbers</hi> is ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner learn'd, and longer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd, then <hi>Proſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> (as <hi>Athanaſius</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">3.</note> obſerues) it putteth vs in minde of the harmonie of our actions.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> it ſerueth for the<note place="margin" type="runSum">4.</note> comfort of the <hi>Godly,</hi> who are often more cheared by <hi>Pſalmoaie,</hi> than by <hi>Prayer.</hi> In this laſt reſpect <hi>S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> thus deſcribeth a<note place="margin">Prolog. in lib. Pſal.</note> 
                  <hi>Pſalme: Pſalmus, Tranquilli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas animarum eſt, &amp; Signifer Pacis: A Pſalme is the Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillitie of Soules, and the Standerd-bearer of Peace.</hi> With the which agreeth that of <hi>S. Ambroſe; Pſalmus</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Praefat. in Pſal.</note> 
                  <hi>eſt vox Eccleſiae, &amp; clamor Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunditatis:
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:14830:97"/> A Pſalme is the voice of the Church, and the Noyſe of Reioycing.</hi> And truely it is verified in the experience of the <hi>Saints,</hi> that deuout <hi>Singing</hi> of <hi>Pſalmes,</hi> cauſeth teares (of ioy) to ſtand in the eyes (if yet wee may call them teares, and not rather the <hi>Dew of Heauen,</hi> with Saint<note place="margin">De Scala Clauſtrali.</note> 
                  <hi>Bernard.</hi>) To this purpoſe, ſaith <hi>S. Austine, Pſalmus, eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prolog. in lib. Pſal.</note> 
                  <hi>ex corde Lapideo, Lachry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas mouet: A Pſalme f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth teares from a flintie heart.</hi> Nay, he ſticketh not to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, that the <hi>Singing of Pſalmes and Hymnes</hi> vnto the <hi>Lord,</hi> with a grace in our hearts, doth inuite the <hi>Angels</hi> of <hi>Heauen</hi> to beare
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:14830:97"/> vs companie, and doth put to flight the very <hi>Deuils.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then <hi>Sing</hi> yee merrily vnto the <hi>Lord,</hi> O yee ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants of his, that wraſtle (many times) with <hi>Death,</hi> and <hi>Deſpayre:</hi> for well it becommeth you to bee thankefull, ſith you are the <hi>Timbrels</hi> of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt.</hi> For it is not the <hi>Beaſt</hi> that can <hi>Sing,</hi> nor yet the <hi>Birds</hi> that are of great ſize: but the <hi>Little Lark,</hi> the <hi>Little Nightingale,</hi> the <hi>Little Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net,</hi> I meane, the poore deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſed ones: and they, not on the ground, but vpon the trees, or in the ayre. For the beſt-men, if they once begin to minde the <hi>Earth,</hi> forget their <hi>Singing.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="174" facs="tcp:14830:98"/>
               <p>Now, if it bee obiected from <hi>S. Iames,</hi> that merrie<note place="margin">Iam. 5. 13.</note> times are fitteſt for <hi>Singing of Pſalmes:</hi> I anſwere, firſt, that the ſorrowes, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladies of the <hi>Saints</hi> haue euer their inter mixture of ioy; &amp; then, that the ſpeech is not ſo to be reſtrained to proſperitie, but that it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth it ſelfe alſo to caſes of extremitie. To this end Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> bringeth in<note place="margin">
                     <hi>In</hi> Pſal. 50.</note> 
                  <hi>God,</hi> rebuking thoſe that ſung not praiſes to him in their Diſtreſſe, in theſe words: <hi>Quando parco, cantas; quando Caſtigo, murmuras: quaſi quando parco, ſim Deus tuus, &amp; quando non parco<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> non ſim Deus tuus. Ego, quos amo, arguo, &amp; caſtigo. When
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:14830:98"/> I ſpare thee, thou ſingeſt; when I afflict thee, thou murmureſt; as if when I let thee alone, I were thy God, and were not thy God, when I corrected thee. No, know, that whom I loue, I</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reu. 3. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>rebuke, and chaſten.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="47" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XLVII.</hi> Of the Tenth Comfort in trouble of Conſcience, which is the Teſtimonie of the M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter.</head>
               <p>IN the time of ſome gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous ſickneſſe, or calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, when the <hi>Conſcience</hi> of the <hi>Beleeuer</hi> is waked vp, and the paines of <hi>Hel</hi> begin to take hold on him; oh, how hard it is to perſwade him of his <hi>Adoption!</hi> For,
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:14830:99"/> the <hi>Deuill</hi> obtruding the multitude of his ſinnes, the hainouſneſſe of their ranke, the holineſſe of the Law, the iuſtice of GOD, and the horror of damnation; and he iudging of himſelfe by feeling, not by <hi>Faith,</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times breaks forth into fearefull words of impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and diſtruſt. In which combate, if the godly <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister,</hi> to whom are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted<note place="margin">Mat. 16. 19. Ioh. 20. 23.</note> 
                  <hi>The Keyes of Heauen,</hi> ſhall perceiue by his thirſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after the bloud of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> by his zealous praier for increaſe of grace, by his humble ſubmiſsion vnder the hand of GOD, and by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther comfortable effects, and ouertures, that his
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:14830:99"/> name is writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the Book of life; and therevpon ſhall acquit him (in Chriſt) from the malediction of the Law; there is certainely of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered him great matter of reioycing.</p>
               <p>For, if when I ſhal thinke (becauſe I haue a great drought vpon mee) that I am entred into a <hi>Dropſie,</hi> and am like ere long to be bigge of the diſeaſe, and to bee brought to bed of <hi>Death;</hi> there ſhall come vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me an expert, and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienced Phyſician, who af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter due pauſe, and aduiſed conſideration, ſhall confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently aſſure me, that there is no ſuch matter, becauſe my liuer is not obſtruct, my
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:14830:100"/> Stomacke ſwells not, my Ankle pitts not, my Vrine is not wateriſh, nor my Fleſh ſpungie, nor my Complexion ſallow, nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Symptome</hi> of ſuch euill can bee diſcerned; ſhall I not take heart, and gather vp my ſpirits, and bluſh to thinke that I was ſo timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, and conceited? And euen ſo ſhould it fare with me in my inward languiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, when the Spirituall <hi>Phyſician</hi> imparts the like effectuall incouragements.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="48" type="chapter">
               <pb n="179" facs="tcp:14830:100"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XLVIII.</hi> Of the Eleuenth Comfort in trouble of Conſcience, which is, Conference with the Godly.</head>
               <p>IT is no ſmall bleſſing, when a man that is hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in <hi>Spirit,</hi> may repaire for eaſe to <hi>Chriſtian</hi> friends to whome is giuen the tongue of the learned, to know how to miniſter a<note place="margin">Iſa. 50. 4.</note> word in time to him. For, <hi>firſt,</hi> it is a <hi>Rule</hi> in <hi>Diuinity,</hi> and in <hi>Experience,</hi> that <hi>Two</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccl. 4. 9.</note> are better than <hi>One:</hi> and that <hi>A three-fold Cord is not</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">12.</note> 
                  <hi>eaſily broken. Secondly,</hi> it is the <hi>Promiſe</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that where two or three are ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered<note place="margin">Mat. 18. 20</note>
                  <pb n="180" facs="tcp:14830:101"/> together in his Name, there will hee bee preſent by his <hi>Holy Spirit,</hi> as he was corporally with his <hi>Diſciples,</hi> when they went<note place="margin">Luc. 24. 15.</note> to <hi>Emaus. Thirdly, Godly Conference is</hi> a ſpeciall part of the <hi>Communion of Saints. Fourthly,</hi> the viciſſitude of graue Diſcourſes, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſed collation of <hi>Euangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call</hi> contexts, exhilerateth the minde, and lifteth it vp aboue it ſelfe. <hi>Fiftly,</hi> the inter-view of each others holineſſe, puts on the dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly-diſpoſed partie, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acuates him to goodneſſe. <hi>Sixtly,</hi> the force of mutuall incouragement, ſtrikes fire into the affections, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flames them with zealouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:14830:101"/> and deuotion. <hi>Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> the prayers that are ioyntly made, with vnited hearts, and pure hands lift vp, aſcend as <hi>Incenſe</hi> before the <hi>Lord,</hi> and much availe in the behalfe of the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfited. But if in the fright, and appallment of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> we ſhall reſort to pleaſant companions, who with rotten mirth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake (as they phraſe it) to driue away the <hi>Qualme</hi> from our ſtomacke: the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent will prooue, that it is but cold water in a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Ague,</hi> which aſſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth the heate for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, but afterwards redou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth it, and indangereth the bodie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="49" type="chapter">
               <pb n="182" facs="tcp:14830:102"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XLIX.</hi> Of the Twelfth Comfort in trouble of Conſcience, which is Painful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in our Calling.</head>
               <p>AMongſt other effectual meanes againſt droo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, and vexation of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, the <hi>Diligence</hi> in our par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Calling, is not to be forgotten. For as it remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the occaſion of euill: ſo beateth it backe the temptation to <hi>Deſpaire.</hi> Therefore thoſe men are marueilouſly deceiued, who liuing in diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ent, by continuing in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ome groſſe ſinne, doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquiſh
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:14830:102"/> all d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aling in the world, and betake them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to a Sedentarie life, perſwading the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues they ſhall reſt them in retyred<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, as in the centre of their hopes. For, through want of due motion and ſtirrage, the ruſt, and canker of ſelfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiltineſſe, will eate into their moſt ſolid, and beſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compacted parts, and, in tract of time, conſume them to nothing.</p>
               <p>Let vs therefore ſhunne <hi>Idleneſſe,</hi> as the <hi>Moth of the Soule,</hi> which frets it in pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces without making any noyſe: and let vs beare in minde the counſel of Saint <hi>Ierome: Facito aliquid oper is,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ad Ruſtic. Mon.</note> 
                  <hi>vt te ſemper Diabolus inue
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:14830:103"/> occupatum: Bee doing ſomething, that the Deuil may alwayes find thee buſied.</hi> And let vs goe (as <hi>Salomon</hi> adui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth<note place="margin">Pro. 6. 6.</note> vs) to be ſchooled of the <hi>Piſmires;</hi> for they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtirre themſelues with toile incredible, and (as <hi>Ierome</hi> reports of them) are witti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly<note place="margin">In vit. Mal. Mon.</note> laborious: ſome bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring burdens bigger then themſelues: ſome nipping ſeeds in their mouthes, as with pincers: ſome carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing moulds to ſtop the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-wayes: ſome cutting Corne in the middle, that it growe not: ſome run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to helpe them that lie ſtrugling vnder their load: and others officiouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueighing out the bodies of
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:14830:103"/> the dead, for feare of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noyance.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="50" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. L.</hi> Of the Thirteenth comfort in trouble of Conſcience, which is, The Trueth of Gods Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes.</head>
               <p>ANother <hi>Anchor-hold,</hi> for the <hi>Soule</hi> to ſtay her <hi>ſelfe,</hi> in the ſurges of temptation, is the infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Truth of Gods Promiſes.</hi> For <hi>God</hi> is not as man, that<note place="margin">Num. 23. 19.</note> he ſhould lye, neither as the ſonne of man, that he he ſhould repent: hath <hi>He</hi> ſaid, and ſhal <hi>He</hi> not doe it? Hath <hi>Hee</hi> ſpoken, and ſhall <hi>He</hi> not accompliſh it? Is he not <hi>true</hi> in him ſelfe, in his words, and in his works? Is
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:14830:104"/> not his <hi>Truth</hi> ſincere with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out imperfection? firſt, without dependance? eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall without ſucceſſion? immutable without varia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? Is not his <hi>Word</hi> the<note place="margin">Ioh. 17 17.</note> 
                  <hi>Trueth</hi> by an excellencie? and ſhall it not remaine in violate, when the conſtant<note place="margin">Mat. 5. 18.</note> frame of heauen and earth ſhall be ſhaken, and diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued? And hath not the<note place="margin">Ier. 31. 34.</note> Lord made a <hi>Couenant</hi> with the <hi>Beleeuer,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed it by hand-writing,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11. 25.</note> and ſeales, that he will for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue his iniquity, &amp; remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber his ſin no more? Then why doe I liſten to the deadly Knell of Satan, as if I were a <hi>fire-brand of Hell,</hi> without all hope of life,
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:14830:104"/> and ſaluation: and not ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther crie with teares, as the <hi>Man</hi> did in S. <hi>Marke, Lord,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mark. 9. 24</note> 
                  <hi>I beleeue, helpe my vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="51" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. LI.</hi> Of the Fourteenth Comfort, which is the Iuſtice of God.</head>
               <p>AS out of the <hi>Eater</hi> came<note place="margin">Iudg. 14. 14</note> meate, and out of the <hi>Strong</hi> came ſweeteneſſe: ſo may there matter of conſolation, bee fetched from the proprietie of <hi>Gods Iuſtice.</hi> For, <hi>firſt,</hi> it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer executed againſt the nocent, without ſome mix<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture of mercie; inſomuch that the <hi>Deuils</hi> themſelues are not altogether puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:14830:105"/> ſo ſeuerely as they<note place="margin">See <hi>Hier. Zanch. de Nat. Dei. c. 5.</hi>
                  </note> deſerue. <hi>Secondly,</hi> it being againſt the nature of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice,</hi> that a <hi>Debt</hi> ſhould be twice payd, by the <hi>Surety</hi> once, and againe by the <hi>Principall:</hi> why ſhould I feare the attachment of my perſon, ſith my <hi>Bonds</hi> long<note place="margin">Col. 2. 14.</note> ſince were canceld at <hi>Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotha,</hi> and nayld to the <hi>Croſſe</hi> of my <hi>Redeemer?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="52" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. LII.</hi> That all the forenamed Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts are vneffectual, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Preſence of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt.</head>
               <p>BVt in vaine doth <hi>Paul</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 3. 6.</note> plant, and <hi>Apollos</hi> wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, vnleſſe the <hi>Lord</hi> do giue
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:14830:105"/> increaſe. It is not bread, but the <hi>Staffe</hi> of bread that nouriſheth. It is the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> that is the <hi>Comforter,</hi> euen the <hi>Spirit of Trueth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 14. 16, 17.</note> whom the world ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, becauſe it ſeeth him not, neither knoweth him: but the <hi>Children of God</hi> knowe him; for <hi>Hee</hi> dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in them with an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable ioy, which goes a degree beyond <hi>Peace of</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 14. 17. <hi>De Scala Clauſt.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Conſcience. Inexperti talia non intelligunt</hi> (ſaith <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard) niſi ea expreſsiùs legant in libro Experientiae, quos ipſa doceat Vnctio: Vnexpert men cannot skil of theſe things, nor any but thoſe that expreſly reade them in the Book of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, beeing inſtructed
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:14830:106"/> therein by the Vnction of the Spirit. Hanc autem gratiam cui vult, &amp; quando vult, Sponſus tribuit; non quaſi iure Haereditario poſsidetur: Now the Bridegroome</hi> (CHRIST IESVS) <hi>conferres this grace vpon whom he will, and when hee will: for no man can chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge it as an Heritage.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſignes (ſayth Saint <hi>Bernard</hi>) that declare the<note place="margin">De Scala Clauſt.</note> preſence of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> are chiefely two: <hi>Suſpiria, &amp; Lachrymae: Sighes, and Teares. O, Domine</hi> IESV! <hi>ſi adeò ſunt dulces iſtae lachrymae, quae ex memoria, &amp; deſiderio tui excitantur; quàm dulce erit gaudium, quod ex mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſta Tui Viſione capietur? Lord</hi> IESV! <hi>if the teares, that</hi>
                  <pb n="191" facs="tcp:14830:106"/> 
                  <hi>are ſhed in the remembrance, and deſire of Thee, bee ſo ſweete, and delightfull; how vnſpeakeable will that ioy bee, that ſhall bee conceiued in the manifeſt Viſion of Thee? Si adeò dulce eſt flere prote; quàm dulce erit gaudere de te? If there be ſuch pleaſure in wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping for thee, Oh, what com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort will there be, in reioycing in thee?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="53" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. LIII.</hi> An Exhortation to the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>GOD,</hi> that they ſtriue againſt their Dum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſhneſſe, and that they be Cheerefull in the Lord.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>REioyce</hi> in the <hi>Lord,</hi> O<note place="margin">Pſal. 33. 1.</note> ye <hi>Righteous;</hi> for it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:14830:107"/> well the <hi>Iuſt</hi> to be <hi>thankefull. Reioyce</hi> in the<note place="margin">Phil. 4. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Lord,</hi> alway, againe, I ſay, <hi>Reioyce. Sing</hi> ye merrily vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to<note place="margin">Pſal. 81. 1.</note> GOD your <hi>Strength,</hi> make a cheereful noyſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the GOD of <hi>Iacob.</hi> O <hi>Sing</hi> Prayſes, ſing Prayſes vnto your GOD; O ſing Prayſes, ſing Prayſes vnto your <hi>King.</hi> O giue thankes<note place="margin">Pſal 47. 6.</note> vnto the LORD, for hee is Gracious, and his Mercie indureth for euer. O giue thankes vnto the GOD of all GODS, for his Mercie indureth for euer. O thanke<note place="margin">Pſal. 136. 1. 2. 3.</note> the LORD of all LORDS; for his Mercie indureth for euer. Yea, let the <hi>Dumbe</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſai. 35. 6.</note> man <hi>Sing,</hi> and the <hi>Lame</hi> man leape as an <hi>Hart.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="193" facs="tcp:14830:107"/>
               <p>Hearten vp your ſelues<note place="margin">Pſal. 42. 5.</note> with the <hi>Prophet</hi> DAVIDS <hi>Apoſtrophe:</hi> Why art thou ſo heauie, O my Soule; and why art thou ſo diſquieted within me? O put thy truſt in GOD. Feare not, thou woorme <hi>Iacob,</hi> for thy <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſai. 41. 14.</note> the <hi>Holy One of Iſrael</hi> will help thee. Why ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt thou ſay, The LORD<note place="margin">Iſai. 49. 14.</note> hath forſaken mee, and my LORD hath forgotten me? Can a Woman forget her Childe, and not haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion on the ſonne of her Wombe? Though they ſhould forget, yet will not the LORD forget thee. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, he hath ingrauen thee vpon the palmes of his hands, thy Walls are euer
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:14830:108"/> in his ſight. For a moment,<note place="margin">Iſai. 54. 8.</note> in his anger, hath he hid his face from thee, for a little ſeaſon: but with euerlaſting Mercie will hee haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion on thee. Who ſhall lay any thing to thy charge? It is GOD that iuſtifieth<note place="margin">Rom. 8. 33. 34. &amp;c.</note> thee. Who ſhal condemne? It is CHRIST which is dead, yea rather, which is riſen againe, who is alſo at the right hand of GOD, and maketh requeſt for thee. Who ſhall ſeparate thee from the loue of CHRIST? Shall tribulation, or an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh, or perſecution, or fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, or nakedneſſe, or pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ril, or ſword? No, thou maiſt perſwade thy ſelfe, that neyther death, nor life,
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:14830:108"/> nor <hi>Angels,</hi> nor <hi>Principali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> nor powers, nor things preſent, nor things to come, nor height, nor depth, nor any other creature, ſhall be able to ſeparate thee from the loue of GOD, which is in <hi>Christ Ieſus</hi> thy <hi>Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Conſider that the <hi>Godly</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>th.</hi> 7. 11.</note> man is a <hi>Bleſſed</hi> man, and therefore hath his name of <hi>Reioycing.</hi> Conſider the ſaying of <hi>Athanaſius</hi> (which is cited by Saint <hi>Bernard</hi>)<note place="margin">De modo Bene Viu. Ser. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>Homo triſtis ſemper malitia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, &amp; contriſtat Spiritum Sanctum, ſibi à Deo donatum: A man that is cuſtomably ſad, and dumpiſh, is alwayes ham<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mering ſome miſchiefe, and grieueth the Holy Spirit, which the Lord hath giuen
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:14830:109"/> him.</hi> Conſider that a <hi>ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 17. 22.</note> minde dryeth vp the bones, and riueleth the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, which is a part of the <hi>Image</hi> of GOD. Conſider, that it diſableth a man to the performance of the Workes of his Calling. Conſider, that it is excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding liable to temptations, and is vſually barren in the very diſpoſition to doe good. Conſider, that <hi>Liſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſneſſe,</hi> and <hi>Vnthankeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> are neuer ſeuered, but goe hand in hand together. Conſider, that it is the <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> of <hi>Doubtfulneſſe.</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider,<note place="margin">Bern. De Mod. Bene Viu. Ser. 11</note> that <hi>Melancholy</hi> is a <hi>Black humour,</hi> and the <hi>Seate</hi> of the <hi>Deuill,</hi> if it bee not well lookt to. Conſider,
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:14830:109"/> that immoderate <hi>Sorrow</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Cor. 7. 10</note> cauſeth Death, and is the Fore-runner of <hi>Deſpaire.</hi> Conſider, it argues a defect of Wiſedome, ſith the wrath of GOD belongs<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5. 6.</note> not to the <hi>Elect,</hi> but to the Children of Diſobedi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nce Conſider, that as in the <hi>Laughing</hi> of the wicked, the<note place="margin">Pro. 14. 13.</note> heart is ſorrowfull, and the end of that Mirth is Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uineſſe: ſo in the ſorrow of the <hi>Godly,</hi> the heart ſhould bee lightned, becauſe the end of that Heauineſſe is Mirth. Conſider, that it prouokes the Lord to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, when one ſerues him not with <hi>Ioyfulneſſe,</hi> and<note place="margin">Deu. 28. 47</note> with a <hi>Good</hi> heart.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="54" type="chapter">
               <pb n="198" facs="tcp:14830:110"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. LIIII.</hi> A ſhort Prayer for Comfort in trouble of Conſcience.</head>
               <p>MOſt mightie, and moſt glorious GOD, the brightneſſe of whoſe coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance the very <hi>Angels</hi> are not able to behold, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whoſe wrath none is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſtand: how dare I vile, and miſerable Sinner, once offer to ſpeake vnto thee by <hi>Prayer,</hi> who am guiltie in my ſelfe, of ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny treacheries, and rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions; wherby I haue made my ſelfe liable to euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting vengeance? But, <hi>Lord,</hi> it is thine infinite good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and tender compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:14830:110"/> in <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> that thus imboldneth mee. For, though I bee <hi>Hell,</hi> yet thou art <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>auen.</hi> And ſtill thou moſt kindly offereſt thy ſelfe vnto mee in thy <hi>Word,</hi> and <hi>Sacraments,</hi> and ſmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt my ſtony heart with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morſe, that ſo I may bee conuerted, and liue. Yea, Gracious <hi>Lord,</hi> thou ſeeſt at this preſent, that I lye blee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in wardly before thee, and that my ſinnes purſue me vnto Death. My belly trembleth, my lips ſhake, and rottenneſſe entreth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my bones, for feare of thy Iudgements. For, O <hi>Lord,</hi> I confeſſe from the bottome of my heart, that, in mine owne feeling, I am
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:14830:111"/> the moſt notorious Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that euer beg'd mercie at thy hand, or that euer was ſaued.</p>
               <p>For <hi>Chriſt</hi> his ſake, haue mercie vpon me and ſpeake Peace vnto my Soule. O thou that killeſt, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt aliue, bringeſt downe to the Graue, and rayſeſt vp againe; forgiue mee my manifold, &amp; crying ſins, &amp; reſtore the ioyes that I was wont to find in thee. O bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Father,</hi> look vpon me in thy <hi>Beloued:</hi> O <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> one drop, one drop of thy bloud to comfort mee: O <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> inſpire mee with the ſweet motions of grace, and giue me a Certificate of mine Election, and Saluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:14830:111"/> Good <hi>Father,</hi> forſake not the worke of thine own hands; but glorifie thy name, in vouchſafing pitie to me poore wretch, who in all humilitie doe craue it further, in the name, and words of my <hi>Sauiour,</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Our Father, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="55" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. LV.</hi> Of <hi>Euill</hi> Conſcience: and firſt of the Large one.</head>
               <p>HAuing thus copiouſly diſcourſed of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of <hi>Good Conſcience,</hi> and of <hi>Trouble of Minde,</hi> which (being ſanctified) is in the way to it: it now remaineth that wee treat of <hi>Euill Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> which hath ſundrie
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:14830:112"/> kindes, or diſtinctions; the <hi>firſt</hi> whereof is called <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientia Dilatata; A large</hi> or <hi>Cheuerill Conſcience;</hi> becauſe it ſticketh not at any ſinne, vnleſſe it be notorious, and capitall. Thus many will ſweare deepe and fearefull oathes, which yet wil pauſe in a caſe of <hi>Periurie;</hi> will di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt <hi>Fornication,</hi> but ſhrinke at <hi>Inceſt;</hi> will make no bones of <hi>Vſury, Brokage,</hi> and ſuch drie murder; yet will ſit downe, and demurre, ere they bathe their hands in bloud.</p>
               <p>This <hi>Conſcience</hi> is that, which is tearmed <hi>Sleepie,</hi> or <hi>Benummed;</hi> for that it lies ſtill, and couches cloſe, till the time of <hi>Sickneſſe, Death,</hi>
                  <pb n="203" facs="tcp:14830:112"/> or other extremitie; and then (like a wilde <hi>Beaſt</hi>) it ſtarts vp with fierie eyes, &amp; is ready to pluck out the throate of the ſoule. Now the cauſes of this <hi>Securitie,</hi> are <hi>Ignorance, Paſſion, Harts<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, Imployment;</hi> which ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther lull the <hi>Conſcience</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleepe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> or elſe crie downe her voice with clamours, as the <hi>Drummes</hi> in the ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to <hi>Moloch,</hi> were wont to drowne the ſhriekes of the <hi>Infants.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="56" type="chapter">
               <pb n="204" facs="tcp:14830:113"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. LVI.</hi> Of the Second kinde of Euill Conſcience, which is Nice, or Spiced.</head>
               <p>AGaine; there is a <hi>Byrd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ey'd Conſcience,</hi> which ſtarteth backe at the leaſt occaſion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and maketh more <hi>Commandements</hi> that <hi>Ten.</hi> Againſt this cauſeleſſe ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puloſitie, is bent that ſage aduice of <hi>Salomon, Bee not</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſt. 7. 18.</note> 
                  <hi>thou Iuſt Ouer-much:</hi> which ſpeech may ſeeme ſtrange at the firſt ſight, becauſe <hi>Iustitia quantò maior, tantò</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dionyſ. Carthuſ.</note> 
                  <hi>melior; The greater Iuſtice is, the more commendable it is.</hi> But we muſt conſider, that albeit <hi>Iuſtice</hi> (in it ſelfe) be a
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:14830:113"/> vertue, where in there is no <hi>Exceſſe, directly;</hi> becauſe the <hi>Augmentation</hi> is the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pletion</hi> of it: yet in the <hi>Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes,</hi> and <hi>Acts</hi> thereof, <hi>ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluitie</hi> may be found. So that (no doubt) it is diſpleaſing to GOD, that a man ſhould maceratehimſelf, by watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, faſtings, and immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate labour, refuſing lawful meates, &amp; refections, which ſerue for the ſuſtentation of life, and furtherance of his calling: howſoeuer, in a certaine ſtrictneſſe, and moroſitie, hee perſwade himſelfe that this <hi>Auſtere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> pleaſeth him. But we neede not preſſe this point too farre, in this <hi>Intemperate Age,</hi> which is rather pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:14830:114"/> to ſurfet, than abrid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged of Neceſſaries.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="57" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. LVII.</hi> Of the Third kinde of Euil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Conſcience, which is the Peruerſe one.</head>
               <p>ANother kinde of <hi>Euill Conſcience,</hi> is the <hi>Way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> one; whoſe propertie is to ſtraine out a <hi>Gnat,</hi> and ſwallow a <hi>Camell.</hi> This<note place="margin">Mat. 23. 24.</note> was the <hi>Conſcience</hi> of the <hi>Phariſes,</hi> who cried out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt<note place="margin">Mat. 12. 2.</note> the poore hungry <hi>Diſciples</hi> for plucking a few eares of Corne on the <hi>Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath;</hi> but could bawke their owne ſinnes, which were ſo palpable, and ſhamefull, that they deſerued to bee
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:14830:114"/> hooted at. In like ſort, they tythed <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nt, Anniſe,</hi> and<note place="margin">Mat<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 23. 23.</note> 
                  <hi>Cummin:</hi> but left the weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier matters of the <hi>Law,</hi> as <hi>Iudgement, Mercie,</hi> and <hi>Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delitie.</hi> Not that it was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proueable to regard the ſmalleſt documents of the Law: but for that they committed a <hi>three-fold</hi> er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour. <hi>Firſt,</hi> in the neglecting of greater duties: <hi>Secondly,</hi> in placing their hope in theſe little ones: and <hi>Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> in their ſuperſtitious co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation of them. Of the <hi>Succeſſors</hi> of theſe <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſes,</hi> complained <hi>Dionyſius</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In Mat. 23. 23.</note> 
                  <hi>Carthuſianus</hi> in his time. <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les (proh dolor</hi>) ſaith he, <hi>iam penè innumerabiles<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſunt in Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia Chriſti, Paſtores, &amp;
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:14830:115"/> Praelati: qui Decimas, &amp; cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tera quae ad eorum commodum pertinent, cum omni diligentia exigunt, &amp; non dantes incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pant durè, non tam diuino, quàm priuato amore inducti: ſi verò ſubditi peccent in De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, vel ſe inuicem laedant, nil curant, vel parùm: There are at this day (I ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eake it with griefe of heart) an innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable</hi>
                  <note place="margin">This is meant of the Romiſh Phariſes.</note> 
                  <hi>ſort of Paſtors, and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates in the Church (of Chriſt) who demand their Tithes, and other profits, with all diligence and ſtrictneſſe, and take them vp roundly, that denie them; not led ſo much hereto by any loue to</hi> God <hi>as out of deſire to benefit themſelues: but if they perceiue that the people ſinne immediately againſt</hi> GOD,
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:14830:115"/> 
                  <hi>or elſe oppreſse and wrong one another, they reſpect that, little or nothing at all.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="58" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. LVIII.</hi> Of the Fourth kinde of Euill Conſcience, which is the Cauterized.</head>
               <p>THere is a <hi>Conſcience</hi> worſe then all the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, which S. <hi>Paul</hi> calleth<note place="margin">1. Tim. 4. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Seared;</hi> becauſe it is bereft of life, and ſenſe, and moti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on; as an arme, or leg, that is cut off from the bodie, and burnt with an hot iron. This kinde of <hi>Conſcience</hi> is found in none, but obſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nate <hi>Heretickes,</hi> and hainous <hi>Malefactors;</hi> ſuch, as in <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> are ſaid to be Vines of <hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> to be<note place="margin">Deut 32. 32.</note> fat, and groſſe, and laden
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:14830:116"/> with fatneſſe, to adde drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe<note place="margin">Deut. 32. 15. Deut. 29. 19. 1 Kin. 21. Iſaiah 5 18 Zeph. 1. 12. Ier. 3. 3. zach. 7. 12.</note> to thirſt, to ſell themſelues to worke wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſe, to draw ſinne with Cart-ropes, to be frozen in their dregs, to haue Harlots fore-heads, and hearts of <hi>Adamant.</hi> Theſe are they that are ſaid (by the <hi>Schoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi>) to be <hi>Habituati in malo; Accuſtomed to doe Euill;</hi> and being <hi>Black-moores,</hi> will not<note place="margin">Ier. 13. 23.</note> change their hue, though you waſh them with Sope, and Nitre.</p>
               <p>This hard, and irrelent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing<note place="margin">De Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat. l. 1. Quid eſt Cor Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum? Quod ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metipſum non exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret, &amp;c.</note> heart is thus deſcribed by Saint <hi>Bernard:</hi> An hard heart is that which feares not it ſelfe, becauſe it feeles not it ſelfe: It is that which is not rent with compuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:14830:116"/> nor ſoftned with pietie, nor moued with prayers: which yeeldeth not to threats, and growes tough with ſcourges: vnthankfull for benefits, vnfaithfull in counſels, in iudgements cruell, in vileneſſe impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent; vnfearefull of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, vncourteous to the gentle, vnreuerent in <hi>Gods</hi> worſhip: vnmindfull of things paſt, negligent of things preſent, improui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of things to come. And that I may winde vp all in one word, <hi>Ipſum est, quod nec Deum timet, nec hominem reueretur; It is that which feareth neither</hi> GOD, <hi>nor man;</hi> like the <hi>Vnrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke: 8. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Iudge</hi> decyphered in the <hi>Goſpell.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="59" type="chapter">
               <pb n="212" facs="tcp:14830:117"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. LIX.</hi> Of the Steps, and Degrees, that lead to this Searedneſſe of Conſcience.</head>
               <p>THere are (ſaith <hi>Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi>)<note place="margin">In Paſto. Cura.</note> 
                  <hi>three</hi> principall <hi>Staires,</hi> that deſcend to the chambers of Death: <hi>Sug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion, Delectation,</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent;</hi> the firſt is effected by <hi>Satan,</hi> the ſecond by the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> and the third by the <hi>Soule. Suggeſtione peccatum agnoſcimus, Delectatione vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cimur, Conſenſu ligamur: By Suggeſtion, we take notice of ſinne, by Delight wee are vanquiſhed, by Conſent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thralled.</hi> S. <hi>Augustine</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times<note place="margin">Confeſ. 8. 5.</note> makes this <hi>Gradation:
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:14830:117"/> Will, Peruerſe Deſire, Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tom. 10. Hom. 27.</note> 
                  <hi>Neceſsitie:</hi> and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times this; <hi>Suggeſtion, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectation, Conſent, Perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tration.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">De Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcien.</note> Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth <hi>ſeuen Deſcents</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Hell; Importabile, Graue, Leue, Inſenſibile, Delectabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le, Deſiderabile, Defenſibile:</hi> In effect thus much: Firſt, Sinne is <hi>Intolerable,</hi> then <hi>Heauie,</hi> then <hi>Light,</hi> then <hi>Paſt feeling,</hi> then <hi>Delightfull,</hi> then <hi>Deſireable,</hi> then <hi>Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiable.</hi> From all theſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and ſome other of the like nature, wee may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue <hi>Eight</hi> ſeueral <hi>Degrees,</hi> which I reckon thus in their order.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Firſt</hi> is the <hi>Suggeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">1.</note> to ſinne, againſt which
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:14830:118"/> we muſt arme our ſelues with watchfulneſſe, and <hi>Gouernement of the Senſes.</hi> For there were <hi>two</hi> things that vndid DAVID; <hi>Oti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, &amp; Oculus: Idleneſſe,</hi> and his <hi>Eye.</hi> And here we muſt remember, that <hi>Suggesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bern. De Conſcien.</note> without <hi>Ingeſtion,</hi> (that is, A temptation offered, without yeelding to it) is not <hi>Vulnus,</hi> but <hi>Corona;</hi> no <hi>Wound,</hi> but a <hi>Garland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Second Degree,</hi> is<note place="margin" type="runSum">2.</note> 
                  <hi>Cogitation,</hi> which is <hi>Ad pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catum diſpoſitiuè,</hi> in the way to Sinne, if it bee not preuented. For (as Saint<note place="margin">Ad Paul &amp; Euſtoch.</note> 
                  <hi>Ierome</hi> writeth) the <hi>Deuill,</hi> when he meanes to take vp his lodging, is woont to ſend a Thought before, to
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:14830:118"/> trie whether hee ſhall bee welcome, or no. So that a wicked thought (as the ſame <hi>Father</hi> noteth,) is, <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mogenita Diaboli; Satans El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt Daughter.</hi> Now the <hi>Thoughts</hi> of <hi>Man,</hi> (as S. <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi>
                  <note place="margin">De Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en.</note> diſtinguiſheth them) are either <hi>Burdenous,</hi> ſuch as thruſt themſelues vpon the minde vnavoidably: or <hi>Affectuous,</hi> belonging to the pleaſure of the bodie: or <hi>Obſcene,</hi> as being in the nature of vncleane dregs: or <hi>Idle,</hi> as the imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Birds,</hi> flying in the <hi>Ayre:</hi> or <hi>Curious,</hi> tending to the exploration of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets: or <hi>Suſpicious,</hi> incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to ſiniſter interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: or laſtly, <hi>Diſtentorie,</hi>
                  <pb n="216" facs="tcp:14830:119"/> when the reaſon is ſtretcht <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o the contemplation of farre-diſtant Regions, or to the ſpeculation of cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, or elſe to worldly ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotiations.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Third Degree</hi> is <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">3.</note> whereby an euill thought receiued, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ained in the minde, inuei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gleth the will, and laies a bait for it. And this <hi>tickling</hi> of the affection, (if it bee dwelt vpon) is a <hi>Mortall Sinne,</hi> euen by the verdict of the <hi>Schoole-men</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues:<note place="margin">Pet. Lomb. l. 2. Diſt. 24.</note> which muſt ſtirre vp euery one to be circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect in this caſe; to which end tendeth that <hi>Hiſtorie,</hi> which Saint <hi>Ierome</hi> records in the life of <hi>Paulus,</hi> concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:14830:119"/> a godly yongman, a <hi>Souldier</hi> of <hi>Decius;</hi> who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the commandement of the <hi>Tyrant,</hi> laide vpon a fine <hi>Downe-bed,</hi> and tyed downe hand and foot with ſilken Towels, was moſt dangerouſly inticed by the kiſſes, and imbracements of a beautifull Harlot; and being not able to breake a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from her (as <hi>Ioſeph</hi> did<note place="margin">Gen. 39. 12</note> from his wanton Miſtreſſe) to check himſelfe in the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of pleaſure, he bit off his tongue, and ſpit it in her face.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Fourth Degree,</hi> is<note place="margin" type="runSum">4.</note> 
                  <hi>Conſent,</hi> or <hi>Reſolution</hi> to venter vpon the <hi>Action</hi> And here the <hi>Diuell</hi> (that <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Darkneſſe</hi>) bindes
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:14830:120"/> a Napkin cloſe to the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners eye, leſt he behold the danger enſuing; and ſets a <hi>Skriene</hi> betwixt him and <hi>Hell-fire,</hi> that hee may not feele the leaſt heat of it. Of this <hi>Determination</hi> to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſinne, S. <hi>Bernard</hi> thus<note place="margin">De Jnter. Dom. c. 19.</note> writeth: <hi>Solus Conſenſus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>os nos facit, etiamſi aliquid impediat, ne opera ſubſequan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur: Conſent alone makes vs guilty before God, though the fact intended be neuer accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſht.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>fift Degree</hi> is <hi>Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">5.</note> which may be called the <hi>Birth of ſinne.</hi> For now<note place="margin">Iam. 1. 15. Pſ. 7. 14.</note> the <hi>Brat</hi> lies wralling in the lap, which before was ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent,<note place="margin">In Serm. de vilic. Iniq.</note> and concealed. <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet &amp; opus vocem ſitam,</hi> ſaith
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:14830:120"/> 
                  <hi>Bernard: Euery euill worke hath a kind of voice,</hi> whether it be done <hi>Contra Natura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, aut Contra Legem, aut Contra Conſuetudinem: Againſt Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, Law, or</hi> (warrantable) <hi>Cuſtome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Sixth Degree</hi> is <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">6.</note> in euill: which hath brought the profane to ſuch an haunt, <hi>Vt iam, non modò placeat peccatum, ſed &amp; aſsidue placeat: That he doth not now only delight in ſinne, but doth nothing elſe but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in it.</hi> Thus <hi>Conſuetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do vertitur in Naturam: The Habit is growne to a Neceſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. Hic Peccator foetet, Hic</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bernard.</note> 
                  <hi>Quatriduanus est: This Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſtinketh, and rotteth like Lazarus,</hi> when hee had<note place="margin">Ioh. 11. 39.</note>
                  <pb n="220" facs="tcp:14830:121"/> beene dead <hi>foure</hi> dayes.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Seuenth Degree</hi> is<note place="margin" type="runSum">7.</note> the <hi>Defence of Sin,</hi> which is fearefull to thinke vpon. At this paſſe were the <hi>Iewes,</hi> who being reproo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued from the Lord, for their groſſe <hi>Idolatry,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned this anſwere, <hi>Wee haue loued Strangers, and</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ier. 2. 25.</note> 
                  <hi>them</hi> WIL <hi>we follow.</hi> Thus the <hi>Blaſphemer</hi> alledgeth <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph,</hi> to excuſe his <hi>ſwearing;</hi> the <hi>Drunkard, Noah;</hi> the <hi>Adulterer, Da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>id;</hi> the <hi>Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſour, Zachee:</hi> but theſe wicked men (as <hi>Gregorie</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Paſtor. Cur. 3. pars.</note> well aduiſeth) are to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed, <hi>Vt eis perditio priuata ſufficiat: That they would hold it ſufficient to bee caſt awayes themſelues,</hi> and
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:14830:121"/> not by their lewd &amp; licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious ſpeeches, to drawe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers with them into the ſame damnation.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Eighth,</hi> and laſt <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree,</hi>
                  <note place="margin" type="runSum">8.</note> is the <hi>Boaſting of Sinne,</hi> to the which when a man is come, he is in the gall of<note place="margin">Act. 8. 23.</note> bitterneſſe, and in the bond of iniquitie. The triall of<note place="margin">Iſa. 3. 9.</note> his countenance witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth againſt him; hee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clures his ſinne, as <hi>Sodome,</hi> he hides it not: woe be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to<note place="margin">Ier. 6. 15.</note> his ſoule, for he hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded euil vnto himſelfe. Is hee a ſhamed when hee<note place="margin">Ier. 8. 12.</note> hath committed euill? No, he is not aſhamed, neither can he haue any ſhame, but turneth vnto his race, euen<note place="margin">Ier. 8. 6.</note> as the <hi>Horſe</hi> that ruſheth
<pb n="222" facs="tcp:14830:122"/> into the battaile. Thus the Tyrant <hi>Boaſteth,</hi> that he<note place="margin">Pſa. 52. 1.</note> can doe euill; like <hi>Lamech,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. 4. 23. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ab.</hi>
                  </note> (the firſt <hi>Bigamist</hi>) who <hi>Vaunted</hi> to his wiues, that he would ſlay a man in his wound, and a yong man in his heate. And thus the vngracious <hi>Old</hi> man, whoſe thoughts are green, though his head be gray, delights to bragge of his <hi>Sabbath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dancings,</hi> and other vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of his youth; forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting that ſuch abuſing of the whole body with foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh geſticulations, and profanation of the <hi>Lords Day,</hi> may truely bee defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to bee <hi>Circulus, cuius Centrum Diabolus: A Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, whoſe Centre is the Deuil.</hi>
                  <pb n="223" facs="tcp:14830:122"/> I will end this point with that worthie ſentence of Saint <hi>Bernard: Nihil equè</hi>
                  <note place="margin">De Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en.</note> 
                  <hi>exaſperat illius tremendi Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicis Maieſtatem, quàm pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>care, &amp; ſecurè peccare, &amp; de vitijs, quaſi de virtutibus glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riari: There is nothing in the world, that prouoketh ſo much to anger the Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie of the moſt dreadful Iudge, as firſt, to ſinne, and then, to ſin ſecurely, &amp; at laſt to glory in the perpetration of it, as if wee had performed ſome no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table exploit.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="60" type="chapter">
               <pb n="224" facs="tcp:14830:123"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. LX.</hi> Of the fearefull Eſtate of thoſe that haue Searedneſſe of Conſcience.</head>
               <p>TO the end the <hi>Obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, &amp; Obdurate,</hi> may be brought to the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the dreadful dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, where with he is inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roned (like the <hi>Hoſte</hi> of the<note place="margin">2. Kin. 6. 20</note> 
                  <hi>Aramites</hi> in the midſt of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maria</hi>) I will ſtand a little, to deſcribe the wofulneſſe, and forlorneneſſe of his eſtate.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt</hi> then, the Man that<note place="margin">Deut. 28. Leu. 26.</note> hath his <hi>Conſcience ſeared,</hi> is liable to all the plagues that are vnder heauen: to hunger, to thirſt, to naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:14830:123"/> to Famine, to Warre, to Baniſhment, to Shame, to Beggerie, to Contempt, to Impriſonment, to the Peſtilence, to the Phrenſie, and to the Botch of <hi>Egypt,</hi> to Abridgement of Life by a ſudden, and ignominious Death; at what time his Soule is like to goe to <hi>Hell,</hi> while his Bodie is deuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of the Fowles of the <hi>Ayre;</hi> or at the beſt, lyes rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting like a <hi>Carrion</hi> in the earth, til the Day of <hi>Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> the <hi>Scripture</hi> brands him for a <hi>Curſed</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. King. 9. 34.</note> Man; than which, what can be imagined more terrible? For as the ſweeteſt word in all the World, is, <hi>Come ye,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 25. 34. 41.</note>
                  <pb n="226" facs="tcp:14830:124"/> BLESSED: ſo the very bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of the Violl of GODS wrath, is, <hi>Goe, yee</hi> CVRSED.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> he doth enough to bring a plague vpon his Poſteritie, to the <hi>third</hi> and<note place="margin">Exod. 20. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>fourth</hi> Generation: for oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the Curſe is intayled to the Children of irreli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Parents, the rather, becauſe they vſually tread in the by-wayes of their <hi>Progenitors.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> the <hi>Sinner</hi> that hath made a league with <hi>Hell,</hi> and with <hi>Death,</hi> is transformed into a <hi>Beaſt,</hi> and hath loſt the name, and nature of a <hi>Man;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the Dialect of <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 10. 9. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſal. 22. 12. Luk. 13. 32. Mat. 3. 7.</note> hee is a <hi>Lion,</hi> a <hi>Bull,</hi> a <hi>Fox,</hi> a <hi>Viper,</hi> and (at the
<pb n="227" facs="tcp:14830:124"/> beſt) a <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned<note place="margin">Dan. 4. 30.</note> out to graſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fiftly,</hi> the Word of GOD, which is as <hi>Fire,</hi> and as the<note place="margin">Ier. 23. 29.</note> 
                  <hi>Hammer</hi> that breaketh the ſtone; which hath beene a powerful inſtrument of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation to thouſand thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſoules that haue heard it, (as we read of <hi>Three</hi> thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand<note place="margin">Acts 2. 41.</note> that it wanne to the <hi>Church</hi> at one time) cannot preuaile with the flagitious liuer; but the more Sermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s he reſorts to, the worſe hee is; like a raw, and vnbaked Bricke, which the more it is waſhed, the fouler it is.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sixtly,</hi> the <hi>Sacrament</hi> is altogether ineffectuall to him, though it bee the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duit of Grace,</hi> and the <hi>Lauer
<pb n="228" facs="tcp:14830:125"/> of the Soule.</hi> Thus <hi>Iudas</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing the <hi>Bread</hi> of the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> at the bleſſed hand of our <hi>Sauiour,</hi> and yet retayning a <hi>Trayterous</hi> diſpoſition, receiued the<note place="margin">Ioh. 13. 27.</note> Sop, but withall gaue the <hi>Deuill</hi> the full poſſeſſion of himſelfe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Seuenthly,</hi> (which is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to make one quake to thinke of it) our <hi>Sauiour</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 17. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath left it in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe words, that hee will not <hi>Pray</hi> for him. <hi>Ieremie Muſt</hi> not: <hi>Chriſt Will</hi> not.<note place="margin">Ier. 7. 16.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eightly,</hi> when in his affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction he prayes, &amp; howles vpon his Bed, hee doth no better than cut off a <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gges</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 66. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>necke,</hi> or offer <hi>Swines-bloud,</hi> or bleſſe an <hi>Idoll.</hi> Inſomuch
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:14830:125"/> that the action of <hi>Prayer,</hi> which in the <hi>Elect</hi> is a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular grace, (as being the principal fruit of <hi>Faith,</hi> and<note place="margin">Bez. Conf. c. 4. Art. 16.</note> the moſt honourable ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice that can be tendred to GOD) is, in him, vnfruitfull, and abominable.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lastly,</hi> this <hi>Hardneſſe of</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 7. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Heart,</hi> and high degree of <hi>Spirituall deſertion,</hi> is <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raohs</hi> puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that is, the <hi>Plague of Plagues,</hi> &amp; the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Maſter-pocke,</hi> that eateth out the eye of the <hi>Soule.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="61" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. LXI.</hi> Of the Fift kind of Euill Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, which is the Deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate one.</head>
               <p>THe laſt, and worſt kind of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> is the
<pb n="230" facs="tcp:14830:126"/> 
                  <hi>Deſperate:</hi> the horror wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of but to ſhadow, (for who is able to expreſſe it at life?) were enough to ſplit the heart of a <hi>Chriſtian.</hi> For, <hi>Firſt,</hi> it is an <hi>Inward</hi> pang, a <hi>Secret</hi> torment, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uulſion; which by ſo much the more is into lerable, by how much the leſſe it is ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of vent. For the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked is like the raging of the<note place="margin">Iſai. 57. 20.</note> Sea, whoſe waters caſt vp m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re and dirt; being not only toſſed with Stormes and Counter-blaſts from without, but moſt of all troubled with it owne reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>procall motion. Thus the huge, and maſſiue bodie of the <hi>Earth,</hi> is ſhaken with vapors from within, where
<pb n="231" facs="tcp:14830:126"/> the moſt boyſterous winds that aſſault her vpper-face, cannot ſtirre her.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> he is a <hi>Fugitiue,</hi> and is runne away from GOD, who (as Saint <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In Pſal. 139</note> ſpeaketh) is not only an <hi>Inquiſitour,</hi> but an <hi>Inue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtigatour:</hi> doth not only in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of him but traces him ſtep by ſtep, and will finde him out, though hee hide himſelfe in the top of <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mel:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Amos 9. 3.</note> nay, though hee lay cloſe in the bottome of the <hi>Sea,</hi> yet thence would hee command the <hi>Serpent,</hi> and he ſhould bite him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> the LORD hath<note place="margin">Deut. 28. 28, 67.</note> ſmitten him with <hi>Madneſſe,</hi> (as hee threatned in the Law) ſo that hee knowes
<pb n="232" facs="tcp:14830:127"/> not what to doe, nor where to reſt; nor how to paſſe the time: but when it is morning, hee wiſheth it were night; and when it is night, he wiſheth it were morning; and cannot ſleep ſweetly, but ſtarts out of his Bed, and is readie to kill himſelfe, like the <hi>Keeper</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 16. 27</note> of the <hi>Priſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> at <hi>Philippi.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> hee is a <hi>Malefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor,</hi> condemned, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudged to <hi>Death;</hi> expecting hourely his deſerued <hi>Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution;</hi> and therefore liueth in continuall feare, and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment: for, <hi>Timor ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicamentum</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Id eſt, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicium. De Fug.</note> 
                  <hi>habet,</hi> ſayth TERTVLLIAN: <hi>Feare hath euer puniſhment annexed to it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fiftly,</hi> he is like the man,
<pb n="233" facs="tcp:14830:127"/> 
                  <hi>Poſſeſſed of the Deuill,</hi> who<note place="margin">Mark. 5. 3.</note> had his abiding in the <hi>Graues:</hi> for the moſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant proſpects are to him but <hi>Golgothaes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Laſtly,</hi> there is a <hi>Worme</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed this by the Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle or Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that fed vpon the heart of <hi>Prome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theus, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crob. l. 1. in Som Scip.</hi>
                  </note> which lyes gnawing, and grabling continually at his heart, which ſhall neuer die, neuer leaue tugging, no not when hee hath lien thouſand thouſand yeeres in Hell. For the certaintie whereof, it hath pleaſed the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> to repeat it <hi>three</hi> ſeuerall times, within the compaſſe of <hi>fiue</hi> Verſes, in theſe wordes; <hi>Where the</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mark. 9. 44. 46, 48.</note> 
                  <hi>Worme dyeth not, and the fire neuer goeth out</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="62" type="chapter">
               <pb n="234" facs="tcp:14830:128"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. LXII.</hi> That it is exceeding dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous for a man in horrour of Conſcience, to kill himſelfe.</head>
               <p>AFter the <hi>Arch-enemie</hi> of <hi>Mankinde</hi> (the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill</hi>) hath inſnared a man many yeeres together, in ſenſualitie, and worldli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and trailed him along with the vaine conceit of <hi>Mercie:</hi> at laſt hee preſents himſelfe in a ghaſtly ſhape, with kniues and halters in his hand; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually vrging him to become his owne <hi>Deaths-man,</hi> that ſo he may bee rid of his preſent an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh. Againſt which blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die
<pb n="235" facs="tcp:14830:128"/> temptation, the <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> is moſt carefully to arme himſelf with the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the danger that will accrew. For if <hi>Cleombrotus</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aug. De Ciu. Dei, l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> did ill to kill himſelfe, that hee might bee poſſeſſed of thoſe ioyes of Heauen, which his <hi>Maſter Plato</hi> ſo excellently had deſcribed: and if <hi>Cato</hi> haue got him an euerlaſting reproch (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the truely wiſe) by diſpatching himſelfe in a diſdaine to yeeld to <hi>Caeſar</hi> (a man of incomparable valour, and clemencie:) and if <hi>Lucretia,</hi> (chaſte, and <hi>innocent Lucretia,</hi>) haue wronged her name, by the wilfull abridgement of her life, in a falſe ſuppoſall of
<pb n="236" facs="tcp:14830:129"/> diſhonour: and, if the beſt commendation that they got, was, that they did it<note place="margin">Aug. De Ciu. Dei. l. 1. c. 22.</note> 
                  <hi>Magnè,</hi> but not <hi>Benè:</hi> how ſhall they eſcape the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of GOD, who in the bright ſunne-ſhine of the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> doe moſt cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bereaue themſelues of the great bleſſing of this preſent life, which <hi>God</hi> hath allotted them for their comfort, and <hi>Repentance?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hath not the <hi>Lord</hi> ſaid, <hi>Thou ſhalt not kill,</hi> without adding the word <hi>Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour</hi> (as <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> well<note place="margin">De Ciu. Dei l. 1.</note> noteth) that thou migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt take heede of admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the leaſt thought of deſtroying thy ſelfe? A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 17. 23.</note> are not <hi>Achitophel,</hi>
                  <pb n="237" facs="tcp:14830:129"/> and <hi>Iudas,</hi> that ſtrangled<note place="margin">Act. 1. 18.</note> themſelues, left to all poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie as moſt fearefull ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacles of GODS venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance? (For, as for the fact of <hi>Sampſon,</hi> it is extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie; and more (as Saint<note place="margin">De Ciu. Dei</note> 
                  <hi>Auſtine</hi> obſerueth) <hi>Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus latenter hoc iuſserat: The Spirit of God had ſecretly commanded it.</hi>) Beſides; the ſame <hi>Father</hi> doth peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torily affirme, that for a man to ſlay himſelfe, is <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtabile facinu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, &amp; damnabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">De Ciu. Dei l. 1. c. 25.</note> 
                  <hi>A crime, that is both De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable, and Damnable.</hi> Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ns Bodie,</hi> is a <hi>Part</hi> of the <hi>Image of God,</hi> and all the <hi>Three Perſons</hi> in the <hi>Trinity</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 1. 26.</note> conſulted about the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of it; and all the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures
<pb n="238" facs="tcp:14830:130"/> in Heauen, and in Earth, are not able to make the leaſt <hi>haire</hi> of ones head. <hi>Laſtly,</hi> after death, <hi>Locu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lubris</hi>
                  <note place="margin">De Ciu. Dei l. 1. c. 25.</note> 
                  <hi>Poenitentiae non datur; There is no fitting place for Repentance:</hi> and therefore, O man, ſtay thy hand; and commit not that <hi>Murder</hi> in one inſtant, which thou canſt neuer waſh out with thy teares, in infinite <hi>Milli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> of yeeres.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="63" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. LXIII.</hi> Certaine forcible Reaſons a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Deſpaire.</head>
               <p>TO the end the <hi>Deuill</hi> may not ſinke downe the ſoule irrecouerably in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Hell,</hi> the diſtracted ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb n="239" facs="tcp:14830:130"/> is to know, that none in this life are apparant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly debarred from hope of <hi>forgiueneſſe,</hi> but onely the <hi>Reprobate angels. Diaboli, &amp;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Enarrat. in Pſa. 54.</note> 
                  <hi>angeli eius</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Auſtin) manifeſtati ſunt nobis, quòd ad Ignem aeternum ſunt deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nati: Ipſorum tantùm deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randa eſt Correctio: Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Deuill and his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, moſt certaine it is, that they are Praedeſtinate to euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting fire: and we are to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire of their correction only.</hi> Againe, it muſt bee well weighed, that there is no Offender ſo helliſh, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominable, but that the <hi>Church of God</hi> receiues him into her armes, vpon his vnfained <hi>Conuerſion:</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="240" facs="tcp:14830:131"/> to that ſweete ſaying of S. <hi>Auguſtine: In quibuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>
                  </hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tom. 10. Hom. 27.</note> 
                  <hi>peccatis, non perdit viſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cera, Pia Mater Eccleſia: Our Holy Mother, the Church, doth not forgoe the bowels of her loue, in any ſinne, be it neuer ſo hainous.</hi> Of this very mind is the bleſſed <hi>Martyr Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian: Nec quiſquam</hi> (ſaith<note place="margin">Ad Demetr.</note> he) <hi>aut Peccatis retardetur, aut annis, quò <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>inùs veniat ad conſequendam ſalutem: Let no man bee kept backe from ſeeking mercie, haue he been neuer ſo mighty, neuer ſo inueterate a Tranſgreſſour. In iſto adhuc mund<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> manenti, nulla Poenitentia ſera eſt: ſo long as a man is in this World, Repentance neuer commeth too late. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> ſub ipſo licet exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu,
<pb n="241" facs="tcp:14830:131"/> &amp; vitae temporalis occ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſu pro delict is roges, venia con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitenti datur, &amp; ad Immortal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem, ſub ipſa morte tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur: Though thou haue d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred the crauing of forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, euen till thou bee draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on, and (in a manner) at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he laſt gaſpe: yet, if thou then p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rforme it ſincerely, thy ſins a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e pardoned, and thou art p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſed from death to life.</hi> Which words are not writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by this godly <hi>Father,</hi> to bolſter vp any man in his preſumption; but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to comfort the diſtreſſed ſoule, ſurcharged with his iniquities.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eouer,</hi> the wounded <hi>Sinner</hi> is to take notice, that to adde <hi>Deſpaire</hi> vnto
<pb n="242" facs="tcp:14830:132"/> his other wickedneſſe, is (with the <hi>Amorites</hi>) to make it <hi>Full.</hi> For it is the iudgement of Saint <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tom. 10. Hom. 27.</note> that <hi>Iudas</hi> ſinned more grieuouſly by <hi>Deſpay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring,</hi> than by <hi>Betraying Our Sauiour.</hi> His wordes are theſe: <hi>Iudam Traditoren, non tam ſcelus, quod con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſit, quàm Indulgeniae Deſperatio, fecit penitùs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terire: It was not ſo much the curſed fact of Iudas the Traytour, that caſt away his ſoule, as the Deſpairing of the Mercy of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lastly,</hi> the <hi>Sinne</hi> of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire</hi> is ſo notorious, that ſome learned men haue thought it to be the <hi>Vnpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donable ſinne against the
<pb n="243" facs="tcp:14830:132"/> Holy Ghost:</hi> becauſe it is<note place="margin">Di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nyſ-Carth. in Euang. Math. c. 27. Pet. Lomb. l. 2. Diſt. 43</note> committed <hi>directè contra Diuinitatem; Directly againſt the Godhead: videlicet, contra Infinitatem Bonitatis, &amp; Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſericordiae Dei; that is, against the Infinitenes of Gods Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and Mercie.</hi> The <hi>Lord,</hi> for his <hi>Christs</hi> ſake, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme vs in the aſſurance of his fauour, by the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of his <hi>Spirit,</hi> and the comfortable fruits of a <hi>Sanctified life;</hi> that after this weariſome pilgrimage, we may keepe holy to him, an euerlaſting <hi>Sabbath</hi> in the <hi>Heauens.</hi> Amen.</p>
               <closer>Deo Gloria.</closer>
               <argument>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Qui primas non potuit habere Sapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiae; ſecundas habeat partes Modeſtiae.</hi> 
                     <bibl>Aug. in lib. Retract.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </argument>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
